<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth with time, or, Certain reasons proving that none of the seven last plagues or vials are yet poured out neither will the time of their pouring out begin till after the rising of the two witnesses and the fourty months of the Beast's reign be expired : likewise an answer to the said reasons with a reply further the author hath here set down (in a brief exposition) his opinion of the first vial / by John Canne.</title>
            <author>Canne, John, d. 1667?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 249 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C443A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23893</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07918669</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07918669</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40449</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33252)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40449)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1200:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth with time, or, Certain reasons proving that none of the seven last plagues or vials are yet poured out neither will the time of their pouring out begin till after the rising of the two witnesses and the fourty months of the Beast's reign be expired : likewise an answer to the said reasons with a reply further the author hath here set down (in a brief exposition) his opinion of the first vial / by John Canne.</title>
                  <author>Canne, John, d. 1667?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 101, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Livewel Chapman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [103]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>End of the world.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40449:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Truth vvith Time: OR, CERTAIN REASONS PROVING, That none of the <hi>ſeven laſt Plagues,</hi> or <hi>Vials,</hi> are yet poured out: neither will the time of their pouring out begin, till after the riſing of the <hi>Two Witneſſes,</hi> and the <hi>fourty two months</hi> of the <hi>Beast's reign</hi> be expired.</p>
            <p>LIKEWISE, An ANSWER to the ſaid REASONS; With a REPLY.</p>
            <p>FURTHER, The <hi>Author</hi> hath here ſet down (in a brief Expoſition) his opinion of the FIRST VIAL.</p>
            <p>By JOHN CANNE, Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jer. 51.10.</hi>
                  </bibl> Come, let us declare in Zion the work of the Lord our God.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Dan. 12.10.</hi>
                  </bibl> But the wicked ſhall do wickedly; and none of the wicked ſhall underſtand: But the wiſe ſhall underſtand.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.C.</hi> for <hi>Livewe! Chapman,</hi> at the Crown in Popes-head-Alley. 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40449:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40449:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40449:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40449:3"/>
            <head>To all the <hi>Mourners</hi> in <hi>Zion,</hi> now waiting by faith and prayer, for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the great promiſes of the laſt Times.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Precious Ones,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord ſaith by his Prophet,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5</note> 
               <hi>Gather ye to me my gracious Saints, that have ſtricken my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with ſacrifice.</hi> Who are meant here, I ſhall not ſay: but this I ſay, The time draws nigh, in which the <hi>ſanctified and mighty ones of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah</hi> ſhall be gathered together to him; even the <hi>hundred fourty and four thouſand ſtanding with the Lamb on Mount</hi> Zion.</p>
            <p>It is poſſible, this Work of mine at firſt ſight may ſeem ſtrange to you, being contrary to what hath been generally received; and withal, may occaſion ſome diſcouragement, as if <hi>the day of the Lords vengeance, and the year of recompenſes for the controverſie of Zion,</hi> were further off then you thought before. For the <hi>firſt,</hi> I ſhall refer you to the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> it ſelf: but for the <hi>later,</hi> that is, <hi>taking None of the Vials yet begun,</hi> it will be for your encouragement and advantage many ways.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Here you may ſee, what choice and ſingular Priviledges the Lord hath reſerved for YOU the Saints of the laſt times as, to be particularly THESE, <hi>Rev. 14.1, 2, 3, &amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>called, choſen, and faithful,</hi> Chap. <hi>17.14.</hi> The <hi>Angels to come out of the Temple, with ſeven golden Vials, full of the wrath of God:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>To do vengeance on the heathens, reproofs in the nations: To binde their Kings in chains, and their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in fetters of iron: To do on them the judgement writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten;
<pb facs="tcp:40449:4"/> this comely honour is to all his gracious Saints. Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelu-jah.</hi> It never grieves a childe, to know more then he did of the Portion which his father left him. I have in this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> acquainted you with ſomething more, then what (probably) you knew before concerning your <hi>lot</hi> (how eminent it is) being fallen in the <hi>laſt days.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> If the Lord will thus honour you the Saints of the last times with high and glorious employment, <hi>What manner of perſons ought ye to be, in all holy converſation and godlineſs?</hi> How ſhould ye ſtudie<note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>to be meet for the Maſters uſe; workmen that need not to be aſhamed?</hi> Surely<note n="*" place="margin">Levit. 16.21.</note> 
               <hi>he will ſend by the hand of fit men.</hi> Were a man choſen to any great Office in the Commonwealth, he would take pains to have inſight in it, and to have all meet <hi>qualifications</hi> for the diſcharge thereof. In for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, as Saints ſaw that their work then was to ſuffer for <hi>the teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> ſo they went to God, by inſtant and earneſt prayer, for faith, patience, courage, conſtancie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that they might <hi>not love their lives unto the death.</hi> We are come, without doubt, neer <hi>the time of the end,</hi> viz. <hi>the period of the Beaſt's reign, and the Vials to begin.</hi> Hence we ſhould minde what our Work is NOW, and for THIS be calling upon God day and night, for ſpirits ſutable to the Work.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> I know nothing (if duly weighed) of more weight then this, to heal all preſent Breaches amongst <hi>the faithful of the Land,</hi> and to gather them in (as <hi>one</hi>) with and for the <hi>Lamb.</hi> Never was there a time more unſeaſonable then now, for <hi>brethren to be at oddes,</hi> whether about <hi>Forms,</hi> or the like; but rather (bearing each with other in their Opinions) to joyn together in Faſting and Prayer, that they may all know the Lord, as to the proper work of the day; and therein (as all alike concerned) ſtand fast together in the defence thereof. I have obſerved it a long while, that nothing more draws out the hearts of Chriſtians to peace and <hi>oneneſs,</hi> then the <hi>underſtanding of the Times.</hi> Men walking in a dark room, are apt to ſtumble and fall one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It is want of <hi>Generation-light,</hi> that <hi>Ephraim envies Judah, and Judah vexeth Ephraim.</hi> Could Saints but ſee, that <hi>the day breaks,</hi> and the <hi>ſhadows are flying away;</hi> thoſe <hi>Forms</hi> and other things which men now are earneſt for, God is ſhaking,
<pb facs="tcp:40449:4"/> and <hi>making all things new:</hi> they would lay their hands upon their mouthes, and ſay, <hi>Once have I ſpoken, yea twice: but I will proceed no further.</hi> If a Maſter ſhould come and finde his ſervants quarrelling about ſome ſmall matter, and in the mean time nothing done concerning things of more weight and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; though ſome might be leſs in fault then others, and ſo leſs blamed; yet they would be all reproved, as having neglected the greater and more weighty buſineſs. It is true, in theſe Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, as ſome have more Truth on their ſide then others; ſo their fault is the leſs: nevertheleſs, not having ſerved their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but contended onely about things of leſſer importance; for this they may ALL ſtand aſhamed before the Son of man at his coming.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> If no <hi>Vial</hi> yet be poured out, and the <hi>Vial-Angels are to come out of the Temple;</hi> this conſidered, ſhould ſtir up the Churches of the Saints to <hi>hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches. They have ſeen thy goings, O God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.24</note> 
               <hi>even the goings of my God, my King, in the Sanctuary.</hi> My opinion is, near the time of the <hi>Vials,</hi> the Spirit of God will move among the Saints at their <hi>holy Meetings,</hi> in ſome ſtrong and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way; as to <hi>the ſhaking of the houſe,</hi> as <hi>Act. 4.31.</hi> or as in <hi>Acts 13.2. And the Temple was filled with ſmoke from the glory of God, and from his power.</hi> And therefore,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.8.</note> as emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and infallible confirmations and aſſurances are to be ask'd; ſo God's Anſwers and Returns are to be heeded: for now Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are to expect the great promiſe of the Father, <hi>to be endued with power from on high;</hi> and to have <hi>the Spirit of truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.13.</note> 
               <hi>to guide them into all truth, and to ſhew them things to come.</hi> Again, as wonderful and extraordinary things are to be attempted, things new, and in former ages unheard-of: ſo the wonderful appearances of God, as moving and leading men there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, are to be obſerv'd; which are no other then Gods call to the Angels of the Vials in the Temple: <hi>Go your ways, and pour out the Vials of the wrath of God upon the earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.1.</note> 
               <hi>Who is wiſe, and he ſhall underſtand theſe things; prudent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.9.</note> 
               <hi>and he ſhall know them? For the ways of the Lord are right, and the juſt ſhall walk in them; but the tranſgreſſors ſhall fall therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb facs="tcp:40449:5"/>
               <hi>5.</hi> To hold that ſome of the <hi>Vials</hi> are begun, it draws ſuch a cloud and darkneſs over mens eyes, as it cannot but diſadvantage Saints many ways. For, <hi>1.</hi> Thoſe who now ſuffer upon the account of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>run not after the errour of Balaam for reward;</hi> what improvement can they make of their <hi>Teſtimony?</hi> I ſay, how little (comparatively) doth it tend to? If the <hi>Sackcloth-Witneſſes</hi> have poured out Vials upon the <hi>Earth, Sea, and Fountains of waters;</hi> truly the <hi>houſe of Auſtria</hi> is a buſineſs far off, and the following Vials yet further; and in my underſtanding, all yeelds very little comfort to thoſe whoſe preſent expectation is raiſed up after great and high things nearer home.</p>
            <p>Again, granting ſome <hi>Vials</hi> poured out; but how many, and when, where, and how; here all uncertain: This muſt needs wrap a ſoul into a world of doubts; as, what to pray for, and where we are, and what work to prepare for. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith well, <hi>It is good to be zealouſly affected always,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.18.</note> 
               <hi>in a good thing.</hi> For my part, I ſincerely ſpeak it, taking the <hi>Vials</hi> begun, the more I conſider where we are, and what to pray for, and prepare for, (as to preſent <hi>Generation-work</hi>) the leſs I am ſatisfied, as to have things bottom'd and well grounded.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, taking the Vials not begun, here methinks things are <hi>eaſie and plain to him that hath underſtanding,</hi> as to the knowledge both of our Time and Work. Beſides, for the <hi>Priſoners of hope,</hi> here is that will <hi>ſtay them with flag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>and comfort them with apples. For out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he cometh to reign.</hi> The <hi>riſen Witneſſes</hi> are to begin the work upon the <hi>Earth-ſtate Apoſtacie.</hi> After <hi>three years and half,</hi> (which I take to be the whole time of the laſt <hi>State-Apoſtacie,</hi> and the Witneſſes lying ſo long ſlain) that in <hi>Job</hi> will be made good:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 17.8.</note> 
               <hi>The innocent ſhall ſtir up himſelf againſt the hypocrite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> Were this Doctrine concerning the Vials rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, it would awaken many carnal and corrupt Profeſſors; as <hi>Formaliſts, Neuters, Time-ſervers,</hi> &amp;c. It is no marvel that this ſort of men are ſo little affected or affrighted with the <hi>ſeven laſt plagues:</hi> For if <hi>three</hi> of the <hi>Vials</hi> (as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly held) are poured out, and yet all things continue as they
<pb facs="tcp:40449:5"/> were from the beginning; Why may not the later do as little as the former did? Whereas, did the Hypocrites and Apoſtates of this Age know, that none of them are yet poured out; and withal, were they informed who will be the ſubjects of each Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and what the effects: this would be like thunder in their ears: <hi>Alas, who ſhall live when God doth this?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 24.23.</note> Now we ſhould ſee <hi>the ſinners in Sion afraid; fearfulneſs would ſurpriſe the hypocrites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Specially when they ſhall hear, that the <hi>firſt Vial,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> is the <hi>Earth,</hi> is ſhortly to be poured forth upon an <hi>earthly and carnal Intereſt,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Grand Apoſtates of the laſt times,</hi> deſcribed in <hi>2 Tim. 3.2, 3, 4. For the time is come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.17</note> 
               <hi>that judgement muſt begin at the houſe of God;</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his way of old; <hi>and begin at my Sanctuary:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 9.6.</note> And in taking this courſe, all mouthes will be ſtopp'd: <hi>Be ſilent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zech. 2.13</note> 
               <hi>O all fleſh, before the Lord: for he is raiſed up out of his holy habitation.</hi> What will <hi>Rome, Spain, France, Germany,</hi> &amp;c. have to ſay, when it comes to be their <hi>Turn</hi> to feel the weight and wrath of the Vials, when they ſhall hear how the Lord <hi>began firſt at his Sanctuary;</hi> namely, with thoſe had a <hi>Form</hi> of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, but <hi>denyed the power thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> Neither is the knowledge of this, altogether without ſome uſe to the preſent <hi>Powers of the world,</hi> eſpecially ſuch, who ſay they believe that Christ ſhall have a <hi>viſible and glorious Kingdom;</hi> onely they differ from their Brethren in point of time. It was much, that <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould tell <hi>David, I know well</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that thou ſhalt ſurely be king,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 24.20.</note> 
               <hi>and that the kingdom of Iſrael ſhall be eſtabliſhed in thine hand.</hi> One would think he ſpake not as he thought; or at least, not as he would have it; when no ſooner were the words out of his mouth, but he ſought by all the ſubtil ways he could deviſe, how to take away <hi>Davids</hi> life, that he might not be king.</p>
            <p>But now, to remove jealouſie from men in Authority, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to thoſe who already cry <hi>Hoſanna to the Son of David,</hi> GOD SAVE KING JESUS, <hi>bleſſed be he that cometh in the Name of the Lord;</hi> and do aſſert him the <hi>onely Potentate,</hi> and that he ſhall break all other <hi>Potentates and Powers of the world, and alone be exalted:</hi> This
<pb facs="tcp:40449:6"/> Apologie I dare give forth to the whole world, in their behalf, I ſpeak of thoſe <hi>who bear witneſs to the fifth Kingdom,</hi> That they do abhor all ſecret Deſignes and Plots; neither is it in their hearts to act as men, nor for men; no, nor to appear in the work of the Lord, till they ſhall <hi>ſee one of the days of the Son of man,</hi> that is, the Lord eminently riſen, in lifting up the <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard</hi> for his People. So that as they ceaſe from man, and from truſting in Chariots and Horſe-men; ſo it is belowe their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to provide Pikes and Muskets, or any ſuch Ammunition: for they know, when their time and work comes, if they ſhall need then any ſuch Weapons, their Enemies will ſpare them enough, as caſting away all they have, that they may flie the faster to Rocks and Mountains, whereby to be hid from the fierce wrath of the <hi>Lamb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whereas there is a great Rumour thorow the Nations, of wonderful Actions and Changes at hand;<note place="margin">Mat. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>(When Herod heard theſe things, he was troubled, and all Jeruſalem with him:)</hi> hence it is ſuggeſted, as if the <hi>Aſſertors</hi> of Christ's glorious and viſible Kingdom, had fix'd a certain, definite &amp; determinate Time when the <hi>Stone cut out without hands, ſhould begin to ſmite the Image upon his feet that were of Iron &amp; Clay, and break them in pieces.</hi> But this is not true. Yet this we confeſs, (for we deſire, as our hearts are known to God, ſo to have them naked and opened unto the eyes of all men) we are of opinion, That <hi>the Lord will ariſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 102.13.</note> 
               <hi>and have mercy upon Zion: for the time to favour her, yea the ſet-time is come. The viſion which was for an appointed time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>is at an end, and will ſpeak.</hi> The <hi>fourty and two months,</hi> and <hi>one thouſand two hundred and ſixty days, are neer their periods;</hi> and there ſhall be <hi>time no longer, either for the Beaſt, or other Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, to bear rule over the Saints of the moſt High.</hi> But what of this? Here is no ground for action: for until the Lord himſelf make it clear and certain, by his own infallible appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that the time is come; mens Conjectures are nothing, as to move any to ſuch undertakings.</p>
            <p>And therefore I ſay further, Had theſe men who believe that Christ will ſhortly deſtroy all <hi>worldly powers,</hi> as great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages againſt any of them, as <hi>David</hi> had againſt <hi>Saul</hi> when he
<pb facs="tcp:40449:6"/> fell into his hands, they would not (I ſpeak as I believe) ſtir, or act any thing, meerly as having ſuch an Advantage or Oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: for they <hi>eye</hi> more then what men call Providence, (which Thieves of all ſorts may pretend to:<note place="margin">Num. 23.21.</note>) <hi>The Lord God muſt be with them, and the ſhout of a King among them.</hi> And until <hi>the Lord of hoſts muſter the hoſt of the battel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 13.4.</note> thoſe that <hi>rejoyce in his HIGHNESS</hi> will remain in their <hi>Chambers,</hi> having their doors ſhut about them.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not this, as if there were the least unwillingneſs in the <hi>Aſſertors of the Fifth Kingdom</hi> to ſuffer in the behalf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For I am confident, they are as willing as ever were Saints in any Generation, to hold forth (with their lives in their hands) this Testimony of Jeſus Christ, namely,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.15.</note> THAT CHRIST AS MAN SHALL BE THE ONELY POTENTATE, INSOMUCH AS ALL WORLDLY DOMINION,<note place="margin">Dan. 2.35.</note> RULE, GOVERNMENT, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> SHALL BE BRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KEN TO PIECES, AND BECOME AS THE CHAFF OF THE SUMMER-THRESHING-FLOOR, AND NO PLACE FOUND MORE FOR IT:<note place="margin">Dan. 7.14, 2.7.</note> BUT CHRIST WITH HIS SAINTS SHALL HAVE THE DOMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NION, GLORY, AND GREATNESS, UNDER THE WHOLE HEAVEN.</p>
            <p>But what I write, is to wipe off the Scandal and Reproach which ſome ſeek to faſten upon them, by matching them with Cavaliers and Malignants; and as if great Plots (I know not what) were under Conſultation amongst them: A thing deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as moſt unſutable to the glorious Cauſe and Interest which they profeſs. Beſides, they know well enough, as Christ will take the Kingdoms of the world into his own hands: ſo, when that time ſhall come, (as we hope it is not far off) he will come with power enough: we need not to take any thought about it: <hi>For the zeal of the Lord of hoſts will perform this.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus far endeavoured to remove needleſs Fears, it were well (notwithſtanding) if the Great Ones of the world would take notice of what was hinted before, That Jeſus Chriſt is deſigning against them, (though we are not) <hi>to root them out, and to pull them down, and to deſtroy and overthrow
<pb facs="tcp:40449:7"/> them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 28.22.</note> 
               <hi>Now therefore be not mockers, leſt your bands be made ſtrong. For I have heard from the Lord God of hoſts, a conſumption even determined upon the whole earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 23.9.</note> 
               <hi>He hath purpoſed to ſtain the pride of all glory, and to bring to contempt all the honourable of the earth.</hi> What greater folly in men, then to take care to have the walls of their houſes high and ſtrong, but no covering to it, whereby to keep off hurt and danger from above, and over head? That BLOW which the Powers of the world may expect next, it's from above, even <hi>The finger of God:</hi> and therefore if they have not made it well and ſtrong over-head, (ſtrong enough to keep off the hand of God) what will their Souldiers and Guards about them, ſtead them? <hi>Your Covenant with death ſhall be diſannulled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 28.18.</note> 
               <hi>and your agreement with hell ſhall not ſtand: when the overflowing ſcourge ſhall paſs thorow, then ye ſhall be trodden down by it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 8.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Alſo, aſſociate your ſelves, O ye people, and ye ſhall be broken in pieces; take counſel together, and it ſhall come to nought.</hi> When fire takes hold of ſticks bundled together, the one rather furthers then hinders the others burning. When <hi>the day of the Lord of hoſts ſhall be upon every one that is proud and lofty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 2.12.</note> the more they combine together by Power and Policie, the faſter they will run, and deſtroy one the other. No man (I think) could have done more (whether Machiavilian or Atheist) then <hi>Herod</hi> did, to prevent the great Deſigne of God, when Jeſus Christ came first into the world!<note place="margin">Pro. 21.30.</note> But it would not do. For <hi>there is no wiſdom, nor underſtanding, nor counſel, againſt the Lord.</hi> So a while after, to hinder Chriſts Reſurrection, what could the devil have ſuggeſted, (as a Plot more probably to take effect) then to <hi>make the ſepulchre ſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27.66</note> 
               <hi>ſealing the ſtone, and ſetting a watch?</hi> But this would not do neither: for Christ aroſe in the appointed time, notwithſtanding all the <hi>depths of Satan</hi> in the chief Priests and <hi>Phariſees;</hi> notable Types of the Rulers and Priests of the last days. Whilst ſome, like the <hi>Wiſe-men,</hi> are asking, <hi>Where is he that is born King of the Jews?</hi> and <hi>mourning</hi> with the Diſciples, to ſee him crucified in his Cauſe and Witneſſes: others, with <hi>Herod</hi> and the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> are taking crafty counſel how to hinder his Kingdom, Power, and
<pb facs="tcp:40449:7"/> Greatneſs: But this will not do:<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>Yet have I ſet my Son up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my holy hill of Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither will Christ ſtand to that Diviſion and Share which theſe men have ſet out to him, <hi>viz. Spiritualties:</hi> for ſo they have divided the Government of Nations between Him and Themſelves. As for all outward things, <hi>Crowns, Kingdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Compare</hi> Luke 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Power, Greatneſs, Glory, Riches, Laws,</hi> &amp;c. this is their Share. Now there is another thing, which they call <hi>Spiritual,</hi> or <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>inviſible;</hi> this they allow to Chriſt; and no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel: for they know not how to get it out of his hands. But the Prophet ſpeaks of another <hi>Decree,</hi> which is,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.7.</note> That Jeſus Christ ſhall have <hi>all;</hi> and their <hi>fleſh</hi> (that is, their Revenues, Riches,<note place="margin">Rev. 19.17, 18.</note> Greatneſs, Power, Places, <hi>&amp;c.) ſhall be given to the fowls that flie in the midſt of heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall ſay no more, as having little hope that ſuch ſayings as theſe, will take with them. For the <hi>old ſubtil Serpent,</hi> who loves to be with them in the <hi>Garden,</hi> tells them, (when ſuch things come to their ear) <hi>YE SHALL NOT SURELY DIE.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> And here I may not forget, what help and advantage Saints have, by the knowledge of theſe things: as, to be kept and preſerved from the Errours of the laſt times. For, what is it that doth occaſion many poor ſouls ſo eaſily to be led aſide into that <hi>NOTHING</hi> of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> but their ignorance of the Viſions and Prophecies of the Scriptures not yet fulfilled? Hence (knowing little of the viſible and glorious Kingdom of Chriſt, as the <hi>Son of man</hi>) they turn all things either into Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories, or a Chriſt within them; and ſo make all the great coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and purpoſes of God of no effect. As for this ſort of people, truly I love them, and pity them: I love them, for many good things which I ſee in them; as, their honeſt walking, and civil righteouſneſs; and for that Publike Teſtimony which they hold forth againſt the ſcandalous practices of corrupt men. And I pity them much, to ſee how, pretending to Perfection, and to have the higheſt Light and Diſcoveries of Truth, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be found in their Writings, Speeches, Lives, but what is very lowe, and ſignifies NOTHING, as to be a People raiſed up for the work of the laſt days. They tell us of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> and the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> of the
<pb facs="tcp:40449:8"/> 
               <hi>Seals, Trumpets, Vials;</hi> the <hi>Beaſt, falſe Prophet,</hi> and the <hi>Great Whore,</hi> &amp;c. But alas, poor hearts, nothing do they make of it, either as to the truth of the matter in it ſelf, or in their own way, as they apply it, and would be underſtood. And therefore well may their Way be call'd <hi>NOTHING:</hi> for nothing is held forth by them concerning the great things of Christ which Saints now wait for, according to the promiſe of the Father.</p>
            <p>But to return to you, who are haſtening the day of the coming of Chriſt: Give me leave in the <hi>Cloſe</hi> to ſpeak one word more. As the expectation of Saints everywhere is exceeding high, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtrange and wonderful things: ſo the Prophecies of the Scriptures (ſuch I mean as reſpect the laſt days) are the more diligently to be <hi>ſearch'd,</hi> as the Grounds of our Faith and Hope. And howſoever all of them are of excellent uſe, whereby to know what muſt ſhortly come to paſs, and how to be in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Nevertheleſs, the matter of the <hi>Vials</hi> (in my opinion) is a thing wherein Chriſtians ſhould labour to have ſpecial light and knowledge, as containing the whole Work of God, till <hi>the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners be conſumed out of the earth, and the wicked be no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither will there lie ſuch Darkneſs on the <hi>Vials,</hi> if we once (through Christ) have found the beginning. For as in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Books, the last word of the Page gives direction to what follows, and how to finde it: ſo (I conceive) in every <hi>Vial,</hi> there is a light of ſome direction, whereby to carry us over to the knowledge of the next, and from it to what follows<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo of the reſt: which will occaſion the humble ſearcher to ſay, <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God!</hi> But here no common or ordinary <hi>frame</hi> is ſufficient: but we muſt labour for high and choice ſpirits, to be ſtrengthened with might by the Spirit in the inner man, and filled with all the fulneſs of God.</p>
            <p>Now that ſuch a meaſure of the Spirit may be poured out
<pb facs="tcp:40449:8"/> upon all the Lords Servants and Handmaids waiting everywhere for the ſame, is the daily prayer of him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours In the love and ſervice of the Truth, JOHN CANNE.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From Hull,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this HOPEFUL YEAR 1656.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="reasons">
            <pb facs="tcp:40449:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40449:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Time with Truth tryed:</hi> OR, Certain Reaſons to prove that none of the <hi>ſeven last Plagues</hi> or <hi>Vials</hi> are yet poured out; neither will the time of their pouring out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, till after the <hi>riſing of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> and the <hi>one thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty days,</hi> or <hi>fourty and two months</hi> of the <hi>Beast</hi>'s Reign be expired.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant, how much it doth ſavour of affecting Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity, to publiſh <hi>a new Doctrine,</hi> as the <hi>Athenians</hi> ſaid of <hi>Paul;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 18.19.</note> eſpecially being a thing contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the common received opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of good men. But here I have not onely my own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to witneſs otherwiſe for me; but I hope, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40449:10"/> all ſuch as are wiſe, and truly godly, I ſhall finde better and more charitable thoughts, when they have duly weighed the Grounds of this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed <hi>New Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That none of the ſeven last Plagues are yet poured out,</hi> c&amp;. it ſeems to be a Truth, for theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt: If that be granted, which Mr <hi>Tillinghast</hi> and others affirm, that by the <hi>hundred fourty and four thouſand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">But that I think Mr <hi>Till.</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion here is not queſtioned by waiting Saints, otherwiſe I could give ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Reaſons, that the riſing of the Witneſſes, and the <hi>144000,</hi> do contemporize.</note> Rev. 14.1. the <hi>Gentile-Saints</hi> are ſignified; and their <hi>ſtanding on mount Sion with the Lamb,</hi> is to be after the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes;</hi> then I think there will be very little reaſon to carry the beginning of the <hi>ſeven last Vials</hi> any higher, For though it be the opinion of learned and godly men, that ſome of the <hi>Vials</hi> are poured out; yet ſo, as they hold likewiſe, that the <hi>hundred fourty and four thouſand</hi> have already ſtood with the Lamb on <hi>mount Sion.</hi> And indeed, this hath Reaſon and weight in it, That where we begin the time of the <hi>one hundred fourty and four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand,</hi> there we ſhould alſo take the beginning of the <hi>Vials.</hi> And the order of the matter ſeems to make this clear. The holy Ghoſt having, <hi>chap.</hi> 14. ſpoken of the <hi>Harvest</hi> and <hi>Vintage,</hi> that is, what ſore plagues the Lord will bring upon <hi>Babylon</hi> and the <hi>followers of the Beast;</hi> comes preſently, in <hi>chap.</hi> 15 &amp; 16, to ſhew how, and by what means, <hi>the earth ſhall be reaped, the cluſters gathered, and cast into the great wine-preſs of Gods wrath;</hi> namely, <hi>ſeven Angels ſhall come out of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, having the ſeven last plagues,</hi> &amp;c. So then, to take the <hi>one hundred fourty and four thouſand</hi> to be after the <hi>Witneſſes are riſen;</hi> and to begin the pouring out of the <hi>Vials</hi> before the <hi>Witneſſes are riſen,</hi> in my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40449:10"/> it is very improper to the ſcope and drift of the Prophecie, and croſſeth that excellent order which the Spirit ſeems to obſerve.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly: I do not conceive (under favour) how the pouring out of <hi>Plagues,</hi> and <hi>Vials</hi> full of divine wrath, in any good ſence, and according to Scripture-uſe, may be applied to, and underſtood of the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the glad tidings of the Goſpel. Truly I think, that the publiſhing of the ſweet and moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſoul-ſaving Truths of Jeſus, all the time of the the <hi>Beasts reign,</hi> even the <hi>fourty and two months,</hi> or <hi>one thouſand two hundred and ſixty days,</hi> is in another way, and by other words expreſſed; and not by <hi>Vials full of wrath:</hi> See <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.9, 10, 11. And therefore by the <hi>ſeven last plagues filled up with the wrath of God,</hi> Rev. 15.1. I underſtand real and proper plagues, and not the preaching of the Goſpel, either by <hi>Grosthead, Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff, Luther, Calvin,</hi> &amp;c. but rather ſuch temporal plagues as ſhall be in the laſt days poured out upon wicked men, for deſpiſing and perſecuting the Truth:<note place="margin">No doubt the <hi>Alleluiahs,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. <hi>19.1, 2, 3, &amp;c.</hi> are for what was done under the firſt, ſecond &amp; third Vials, as for the effects of the reſt. Now how in the preaching of the Goſpel by <hi>Wickliff, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. God avenged the blood of his ſervants on the great Whore, I do not yet ſee.</note> 
               <hi>In her was found the blood of the Prophets and Saints,</hi> Rev. 18.24.</p>
            <p>It is true, <hi>Luther</hi> and others, in diſcovering the corruptions of perſons and things, and lifting up their voices like Trumpets, againſt the abominations of their Maſſes, Croſſes, Indulgences, Purgatory, Penance, Pilgrimage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did therein <hi>take the little book, and propheſied before many people, nations and tongues.</hi> That they did this, we have the Word to believe it: but that in preaching the Word of life, and opening the Goſpel of the Kingdom, to the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and blinde world, by which means multitudes were brought from darkneſs to light, and from Idols
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40449:11"/> to the ſerving of the living and true God:<note place="margin">Obſerv, it is not ſaid, that the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als ſhall be wrath, or turn to wrath; but, <hi>In them is filled up the wrath of God.</hi>
               </note> That in this (I ſay) they poured out <hi>Vials filled up with the wrath of God,</hi> I cannot ſo take it; neither have I ſeen Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Grounds why it ſhould be ſo underſtood.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> But thirdly: Suppoſe it be granted, there is a <hi>Vial of wrath</hi> poured out, (which to me ſounds harſhly) and that <hi>Wickliff, Huſs, Ierome of Prague, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. were the <hi>Angels;</hi> The queſtion then is, Who before them poured out their <hi>Vials</hi> upon the earth: For it is ſaid, Theſe <hi>ſeven Angels had the ſeven last plagues;</hi> ſignifying, that there were Plagues before; although for time, perſons, matter, and manner of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and other circumſtances, unlike.</p>
            <p>Beſides, I ſee no reaſon, why ſome will have the pouring out of the <hi>Vials</hi> to begin at <hi>Luther;</hi> others, at <hi>Armachan</hi> the Iriſh Biſhop; ſome, at <hi>Robert Groſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi> To me their opinion ſeems fairer, (taking the <hi>Vials</hi> for the preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel) who carry the thing higher, (as <hi>Mede</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) even to <hi>Waldo:</hi> yea, and why not further, as to <hi>Arnulphus, Arnoldus Brixianus,</hi> &amp;c. who publikely witneſſed againſt the Tyranny and Primacie of the Pope, boldly reproved the wicked lives of the Prieſts; and many other faithful Witneſſes, both of<note n="*" place="margin">Which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year <hi>1134.</hi>
               </note> that time, and before? If we look into Hiſtories and Records of Nations, for ought I yet ſee, granting ſome of the <hi>Vials</hi> already poured out, <hi>viz.</hi> in witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againſt the blaſphemies and beaſtly vanities of Antichriſt,<note place="margin">Thoſe who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, that ſome of the Vials are poured out, ſhould do well to give ſome Reaſons why they take their beginning from ſuch a man, or ſuch a time; and why not before or after?</note> there is more reaſon to take their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning 6 or 700 years paſt, then to pitch upon any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons of later times.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40449:11"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> Fourthly: I have not ſeen any reaſon why ſo much time is allowed between the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſecond Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als:</hi> ſome allow a hundred years, others two,<note place="margin">From <hi>Armach.</hi> the Iriſh Biſhop, to the Sweden Wars in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> is neer <hi>300</hi> years. <hi>Rob. Groſted</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> was before him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>100</hi> years. Again, from <hi>Luther</hi> to our Parliament, <hi>an. 1640.</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>120</hi> years. To the rest of the Vials there is not allowed half the time.</note> and ſome more; namely, from the pouring out of the <hi>first Vial,</hi> to the beginning of the <hi>ſecond;</hi> and to all the reſt, not half the time. Truly I think this is worth enquiry, Why from the firſt <hi>Vial,</hi> before the ſecond begins, longer time is alotted, then to the Six other <hi>Vials.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If thoſe <hi>Vials,</hi> or <hi>last plagues,</hi> have an alluſion to the <hi>plagues of Egypt,</hi> (as it is generally held) then it is probable, when there is once a beginning, they will be ſuddenly all poured out.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Willet</hi> from <hi>Pererius</hi> col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of <hi>27</hi> days, or about a month, all the plagues of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> were fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. on</hi> Exod. <hi>7.</hi> Quest. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> Some have obſerved from the Hiſtory in <hi>Exodus,</hi> that within the ſpace of <hi>thirty days,</hi> the <hi>ten Egyptian plagues</hi> (from the firſt to the laſt) were executed. Now if we reckon a day for a year, (as it is often in Prophetical Types) within <hi>thirty years,</hi> the <hi>ſeven last plagues</hi> of the <hi>ſeven Angels</hi> will be finiſhed. Neither is it to be doubted, but a ſhort work will the Lamb make upon the earth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.28. when thoſe <hi>Vials</hi> begin to be poured out. Wherefore is <hi>Babylons fall</hi> ſet forth under the ſigne of <hi>a great milſtone caſt into the ſea by a mighty Angel? Rev.</hi> 18.21. not onely to denote her irrecoverable deſolation, but what ſpeedy and quick diſpatch the Lord will make, when he calls his Angels out of the Temple: <hi>Therefore ſhall her plagues come in one day,</hi> Rev. 18.8. <hi>in one hour,</hi> verſ. 10, 17, 19. <hi>in a moment, ſuddenly,</hi> Iſa. 47.9, 11.</p>
            <p>I know, the deſtruction of <hi>Babylon,</hi> mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. is by many reſtrained to the burning of the City of <hi>Rome:</hi> but, in my opinion, there is far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ground to take <hi>Babylon</hi> there, for the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40449:12"/> and Dominion of the Beaſt everywhere: And let him that hath underſtanding read the Chapter, he ſhall clearly ſee, that it muſt be underſtood of the univerſal Antichriſtian State, even all that which is to be deſtroyed under the <hi>five first Vials.</hi> Neither do I think that any of the <hi>Vials</hi> will be poured forth till the Angel there <hi>come down from heaven, having great power, and the earth is lightned with his glory,</hi> Rev. 18.1. For it ſeems to me, as the pouring out of all the <hi>Vials</hi> will be the great work of Saints, <hi>at the time of the end;</hi> ſo the Lord will make way wonderfully for them: For they ſhall be enlightned and ſatisfied, as to the knowledge of their work and time. So then, in ſhort, I think it is a miſtake, to apply (as ſome do) <hi>the fall of Babylon</hi> to the burning of <hi>Rome;</hi> or (as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) to the<note n="*" place="margin">I deſire this may be well obſerved, That the <hi>fall of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> Rev. <hi>18.</hi> is to be referred to the five firſt <hi>Vials</hi> equally. Neither comes any of the <hi>7</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels out of the Temple, til that mighty Angel deſcend from heaven, <hi>Rev. 18.1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>fifth Vial.</hi> For, as I ſaid before, there are manifeſt proofs in the Chapter, that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and State of the <hi>Beast</hi> (everywhere) is to be underſtood; and that the other <hi>four Vials</hi> going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, concern alſo the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> Fifthly: Though I would be loth to detract from any, but deſire to have the memory of the Juſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, eſpecially ſuch who have born any good Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt the <hi>Beast;</hi> yet I cannot conceive how any of the perſons to whom the <hi>firſt, ſecond and third Angels</hi> are ordinarily applied, do fairly or fitly pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel and agree with what the Scripture holds forth. Certain it is, none of the Angels come out of the Temple, till <hi>Iohn ſaw as it were a ſea of glaſs mingled with fire, and them that had gotten the victory over the Beast, and over his image, and over his mark, and over the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his name, ſtand on the ſea of glaſs, having the harps of God; and they ſing the ſong of Moſes the ſervant of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40449:12"/> God, and the ſong of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 15.2, 3. All this well agrees with the deſcription of the <hi>one hundred fourty and four thouſand,</hi> Rev. 14.1, 2, 3. But to carry theſe things to <hi>Grostead, Armachan, Wickliff, Luther, &amp;c.</hi> if need were, I could ſhew by many reaſons the improbabilitie of it.</p>
            <p>There is a great difference between <hi>not receiving the mark, or the name of the Beaſt, or the number of his name;</hi> and <hi>getting the victory over the Beast, and over his image, mark, name,</hi> &amp;c. It is true, in the former ſence, there were many of Gods people which in the time of the <hi>Beaſts reign</hi> received not his <hi>mark,</hi> &amp;c. but that any of them, during the <hi>fourty and two months,</hi> got the <hi>Victory</hi> over the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> or over his <hi>image, mark, name,</hi> &amp;c. to this I cannot aſſent.</p>
            <p>Neither is their opinion well bottomed, (I ſpeak as I think) who hold, that this <hi>victory over the Beast,</hi> and <hi>ſinging the ſong of Moſes, and the ſong of the Lamb,</hi> to be before the riſing of the Witneſſes, even the time that they <hi>propheſied in ſackcloth,</hi> and whilſt the <hi>woman was</hi> ſtill <hi>in the wilderneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Under favour, I think, that their opinion is better grounded, (I ſpeak as to conſonancie of parallel Scriptures) who taking the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> already riſen, do carry this <hi>victory over the Beast,</hi> and the <hi>ſong of Moſes</hi> and of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> to the time of their riſing; and ſo begin the <hi>Vials.</hi> But to hold the Witneſſes not riſen, nor the <hi>woman out of the wilderneſs,</hi> and yet to hold the <hi>victory over the Beast</hi> paſt, (the <hi>ſong of Moſes</hi> and of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> to be ſung ſome hundred yeers ago, and ſo to begin the Vials) this, to me, ſeems little leſs then evident<note n="*" place="margin">That the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man whilſt ſhe abode in the wilderneſs, and the Witneſſes propheſying in ſackcloth ſhould ſing the ſong of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Lamb,</hi> it ſeems a contradiction: yet I ſee not how ſuch as hold ſome of the Vials poured out, and yet the woman not out of the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nor the Witneſſes riſen, can avoid it.</note> contradiction.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>6</label> Sixthly: My opinion is, that none of the <hi>ſeven
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40449:13"/> laſt plagues</hi> or <hi>Vials</hi> are yet poured forth, nor will be, till after the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes,</hi> for this reaſon; namely, becauſe none of the <hi>ſeven Angels</hi> come forth with their golden Vials, until the Tabernacle of the Teſtimony is opened in heaven,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mede</hi> perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place to be ſo directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him and others who hold ſome of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als poured out, puts it off thus: <hi>Truly</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that which is there ſaid of the Temple, of the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth not to the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but to the event of the Vials.</hi> But by his leave, he takes more then the place allows him.</note> 
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.5. But that part of the Tabernacle of the Teſtimony is to be ſhut all the time of the Witneſſes their propheſying in ſackcloth, as may be gathered from <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1. with verſ. 19. Hence this Argument might be fram'd:
<q>
                  <l>No Angel is to come forth with his golden Vial, till the</l>
                  <l>Tabernacle of the Teſtimony in heaven be opened.</l>
                  <l>But the Tabernacle of the Teſtimony is not to be opened</l>
                  <l>till after the riſing of the Witneſſes:</l>
                  <l>Therefore, no Angel with his golden Vial is to come forth</l>
                  <l>till after the riſing of the Witneſſes.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The proof of the Argument, are the Scriptures before, <hi>viz. Rev.</hi> 15.5. with Chap. 11. verſ. 1, 19. Now if any do think that the four laſt Angels ſhall come out from the Temple opened in heaven, and not the firſt three; ſuch an opinion is againſt the Text expreſly, which ſaith, that <hi>the ſeven Angels come out of the Temple,</hi> verſ. 6. Neither do I know any ground they have, who think that the Angels pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the four laſt Vials, ſhall have more light, zeal, faith, holineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then the former had. There is no ſuch thing to be gathered from the Text. But if we may uſe liberty of conjecture, I ſee no reaſon (ſuppoſing pre-eminence) why the firſt ſhould not have it; as he that fights the Enemy, and engageth firſt, ſhews himſelf the moſt valiant and beſt-deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Souldier.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>7</label> Neither (ſeventhly) do I think, that the effects of any of the Vials (which ſome ſuppoſe are poured
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40449:13"/> out,) make good what is ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.4. <hi>For thy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are made Manifeſt.</hi> The place to me hath much more in it, then what followed the Doctrines &amp; wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Groſtead, Wickliff, Huſs, Luther, Melancthon,</hi> &amp;c. or the <hi>Swethen wars,</hi> or the <hi>Parliament in England.</hi> For Gods judgements, notwithſtanding what hath been yet done, remain ſtill dark, doubtfull, diſputeable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> eſpecially to the world, wherein his <hi>Iudgements</hi> ſhall be <hi>Manifeſt</hi> in the effects of the Vials.</p>
            <p>As the <hi>Egyptians</hi> under their plagues, though hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſin, yet acknowledged the <hi>finger of God</hi> upon them, <hi>Exo.</hi> 8.19. So the <hi>followers of the Beaſt,</hi> when the Vials are poured out, notwithſtanding their blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming God, and not repenting, to give him glory, ſhall ſee the hand of God lifted up, &amp; be aſhamed for their envie at his people, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.11. So manifeſt at this time will his judgments be, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9. But hitherto the<note n="*" place="margin">Should we in the particulars conſider, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either at <hi>Groſtead, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machan, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. or where elſe, and come down to our own times, very little can be ſaid as to Gods <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> upon the Antichriſtians <hi>yet Manifeſted.</hi> Neither did the <hi>Swethen</hi> wars nor <hi>Ours,</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie much as to what ſhould be <hi>Manifeſted</hi> in the effects of every <hi>Vial</hi> being poured out.</note> providentiall appearances &amp; Actings of God have been ſo darke and hidden, his movings ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; backward, I mean as to his judgements, that ſhould we begin at <hi>Groſtead, Armachan, Luther,</hi> or anywhere elſe ſince the riſe of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and come down to this time, there hath been very little of Gods Judgements yet Manifeſted to his own people, much leſſe to the Enemie: And hence it is that <hi>Babylon ſaith in her heart, I ſit a Queen, and am no widow, &amp; ſhall ſee no ſorrow,</hi> Rev. 18.7. Yea, hence it is that the Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, in their writings, and ordinarie diſcourſes, doe ſtiffly maintain, that Gods judgements have been as manifeſt, and ſtill are, upon the <hi>witneſſes,</hi> the <hi>woman in the wilderneſſe,</hi> and all parties oppoſing them, as they are in reſpect of them. Now howſoever this may be denyed, yet hitherto we have not had matter, nor the cauſe ſo on our ſide, as by the judgments of God
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40449:14"/> againſt them to put them to ſilence. But confident I am, the effects of all the Vials ſhall be ſuch (the 1. 2. 3. as well as the reſt) in the manifeſtation of Gods Judgements againſt the <hi>great whore</hi> and all her hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, <hi>that the righteous ſhall ſee it and rejoyce, and all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie ſhall ſtop her mouth,</hi> Pſa. 107.42.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>8</label> Eighthly: It is ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3. <hi>I will give power unto my two witneſſes, and they ſhall Propheſie</hi> 1260 <hi>days clothed in ſackcloth;</hi> neither did they put off their <hi>ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth till they had finiſhed their Teſtimony, ver.</hi> 7. But theſe <hi>Angels</hi> which pour out the laſt plagues (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven all 7) have put off their <hi>ſackcloth,</hi> and are <hi>clothed with pure and white linen,</hi> Rev. 15.6. hence it muſt needs follow (if I have any underſtanding of the glorious propheſies to be fulfilled in the laſt times) that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note n="*" place="margin">If any ſhall object, that <hi>Groſtead, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machan, Huſſe, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. in one reſpect wore <hi>ſackcloth,</hi> and in another re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect had <hi>fine linen;</hi> I anſwer, In my opinion, this cannot be: for they never changed their condition, after they were <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> but were always ſufferers for the truth to their dying day; yea ſome of them layd down their lives for it.</note> 
               <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Huſſe, Luther, &amp;c.</hi> can be meant by any of the 7 <hi>Angels clothed with white linen.</hi> For they never had their <hi>ſackcloth</hi> taken off, but wore it to their graves. What is meant by being <hi>clothed with white li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen,</hi> the Scriptures ſhew, it was an enſign of honour, which great perſons uſed to weare, their condition and ſtate being changed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.42. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Pro.</hi> 31.22. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.10. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 30.11.</p>
            <p>The truth is, if we take not heed to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>ſackcloth</hi>-time of mourning Saints, and the time in which they are <hi>clothed with white linen,</hi> that is, raiſed out of the duſt, and ſet with Princes, even with the Princes of his people, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 113.7, 8. but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found theſe times (which ought to be kept diſtinct and apart) we ſhall want an excellent light and helpe, to bring things to their due and proper places. I cannot deny but many learned and godlie men doe carrie up the beginning of the Vials, to <hi>Luther, Melancthon, Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius,</hi> and ſome higher; but withall this they hold,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40449:14"/> that <hi>Luther,</hi> and ſo the reſt, had put off their <hi>ſackcloth,</hi> the time of the 1260 <hi>days</hi> being expired, of the 2 wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes propheſying in <hi>ſackcloth.</hi> But to thinke, that any of the <hi>Vials</hi> ſhould be poured out, and the <hi>ſackcloth-time</hi> not out, I ſay, the witneſſes not having finiſhed their Teſtimonie, to expreſs my ſelf humblie and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, I think here is another contradiction: for there cannot be a wearing of <hi>ſackcloth</hi> and <hi>fine linen</hi> at one time, and by the ſame perſons. Neither are the <hi>ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth-witneſſes</hi> againſt <hi>Babylon, the white-linen-Angels</hi> which muſt pour out the laſt plagues upon her, until they have finiſhed their Teſtimony, and after they have been ſlain ſtand upon their feet through the Spirit of life from God, entring into them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>9</label> The 9. Reaſon I take from <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.21. <hi>And a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Angel tooke up a ſtone like a great milſtone, and caſt it into the ſea, ſaying, Thus with violence ſhall that great citie</hi> Babylon <hi>be thrown down, and ſhall be found no more at all.</hi> If this place belong to the <hi>Vials</hi> (as to me it ſeems moſt evident) ſurely then whatſoever is attributed to <hi>Groſtead, Armachan, Wickliff, Huſſe, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. or to the <hi>Swethen</hi> wars, or to the <hi>Engliſh Parliament,</hi> &amp;c. is far from the works of the <hi>Angels</hi> which ſhall pour out the 7 laſt plagues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THVS ſhall Babylon, &amp;c.</hi> The Compariſon eſpecially holds in two things: firſt, a great milſtone in the ſea doth not one while ſink and another while ſwim; now is falling, then riſing again. <hi>Thus,</hi> that is, when any of the 7 Angels pour out their Vials, the worke ſhall ſo proſper in their hands, as it ſhall goe ſtill vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly forward, and not be hindred or retarded, by any <hi>Adverſary-power</hi> whatſoever: It ſhall not be now (as hitherto it hath been) one while the enemie hath been ſinking, another while riſing and ſwimming; but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40449:15"/> where the Vials (whether Firſt, Second, Third, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) doe fall, the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his party ſhall be alwaies falling &amp; ſinking down to the bottome under them.</p>
            <p>Secondly: As <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall be always ſinking under the <hi>Vials;</hi> ſo where ſhe is once brought to the bottom, there ſhe ſhall remain and abide, without recovering her ſelf any more at all. But theſe things we have not<note n="*" place="margin">I deſire the Judicious rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeriouſly to conſider whether he conceives any thing yet done againſt the <hi>Kingdom of the Beaſt,</hi> which looks like a <hi>Vial.</hi> It is true Gods hand hath been againſt it many ways: But we are to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between common Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and <hi>Vials filled up with the wrath of God: ſee Iſa. 13.19. Jer. 50.40.</hi> the wrath is every Vial is no ordinary wrath, as I thinke.</note> ſeen, as the effects of the Vials ſuppoſed to be poured out. For neither hath her ſinking been like a <hi>Milſtone;</hi> nor hath ſhe kept at the bottome, being down. But that I have intended at this time to be brief, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I could eaſily ſhew, how Interpreters in their application of the effects of Each Vial, taking the ſubjects of the Vials to be either this or that Country, doe make very little of the matter, to what the Spirit of God declares ſhall be the effects of everie Viall upon the Antichriſtian Kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>10</label> Tenthly: If my judgement fails not, there ſeemes to follow an abſurditie, taking the effects of the <hi>Vials</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready poured out, to be as they are underſtood and applied. The abſurditie ſeemes thus: <hi>When all the Vials are poured out, verie little may be ſignified or done by them, but Tyranny and Idolatrie in perſons and things, over all nations, people and tongues, as before.</hi> To prove this, thus I reaſon. If after the pouring out of three <hi>Vials</hi> (yea, as ſome reckon, 4, 5, 6.) what tyranny and Idolatry was ſuppreſt and put down (as the effects of the <hi>Vials</hi>) did riſe and ſpread it ſelfe again in the ſame places; Then may the effects of the later <hi>Vials</hi> be ſo too: That is, what corruptions and abuſes are for a while ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt (as the effects of the <hi>Vials</hi>) the ſame, whether Tyranny or Idolatrie, may be eſtabliſhed againe among the people where formerlie they were put down. If ſo, then the concluſion will ſtand good,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40449:15"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John de la March</hi> ſaith the ſixth Vial was poured out upon <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> about the year <hi>1632</hi> and ſo forward. The effect whereof (<hi>viz.</hi> the drying up of it, appeared firſt in <hi>Scotland, An. 1639.</hi> in the ſentence of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation againſt the Hierarchy. <hi>Complaint of the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, pag. 19.</hi> By ſuch reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning we ſhall have little don by the Vials.</note> that <hi>after all the Vials are poured out, very little may be done or ſignified; but the cauſe and intereſt of Chriſt, and the condition of Gods people, whether Iews or Gentiles, no better then it was before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any ſhall object, that under the Vials not poured out (as the 4, 5, 6, 7,) the German Empire, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Beaſt, the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; I anſwer, The Queſtion is not what ſhall be the effects of the later <hi>Vials;</hi> but being granted that 3 are poured out, and where they fell, what Tyranny and Idolatry ſoever was for a time put down, (as the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of ſuch <hi>Vials</hi>) in the ſame countries (which were the ſubjects of the Vials) the former Tyranny &amp; Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry were eſtabliſhed again: The Queſtion, I ſay, then is, why the effects of the later <hi>Vials</hi> may not prove &amp; be as the effects of the former; That is, whatſoever Tyranny and Idolatry ſhall be ſuppreſt (as the effects of the laſt Vials) the ſame may be ſet up againe in the Nations, as it was before in the caſe of the former Vials; and ſo in Concluſion all may be poured out, &amp; the times immediately after as corrupt as before.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>11</label> My 11 Reaſon why I thinke none of the <hi>Vials</hi> are yet poured out, is taken from <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.8. where it is ſaid, <hi>And the Temple was filled with ſmoke, from the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, and from his power; and no man was able to enter into the Temple, till the ſeven plagues of the ſeven Angels were fulfilled.</hi> How this can be fairly applied to the perſons whom I have often mentioned, <hi>viz. Groſtead, Armachan, Wickliff, Luther,</hi> the King of <hi>Swethen,</hi> or our Late <hi>Parliament;</hi> I ſee no reaſon at all for it.</p>
            <p>For 1. If there hath been no ſuch <hi>Temple</hi> yet, <hi>filled with ſmoke from the glory of God</hi> (as I beleeve there hath not) then conſequently none of the 7 <hi>Last plagues</hi> have been poured out.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:40449:16"/>
            <p>But 2. Suppoſe ſuch a Temple 3 or 400 yeers paſt; Yet how will it appeare, that in all this time, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the multitudes which have ever ſince ſeparated from the falſe Church, not <hi>one man</hi> of them was able to enter into the Temple?</p>
            <p n="3">3. For the perſons who are thought to be the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> already gone out of the Temple with Vials of wrath, give them their due and more too, yet I doubt, if things be duly weighed, whether groundedly it can be proved, I ſpeake as to any of them, that the Temple was<note n="*" place="margin">I am much unſatisfied that not any of the <hi>Vials</hi> are yet poured out, in regard I ſee ſo little proportion and ſutableneſs between the perſons who are ſaid to be the Angels; &amp; how the Spirit of God deſcribes the perſons and worke.</note> FILLED <hi>with ſmoke from the glory of God and from his power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, I am ſomething confirmed in my opinion, not onely to obſerve, how unſuteably the matter of the <hi>Vials</hi> is applied to things already done; I ſay, the diſproportion between the one and the other: But what contrarieties and differences there are amongſt good men about them.<note n="a" place="margin">Of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion are good men.</note> Some think Three are pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out,<note n="b" place="margin">So Mede.</note> others ſay Four;<note n="c" place="margin">Thus holds <hi>Mayer.</hi>
               </note> ſome Five,<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>So thinks</hi> John dela March.</note> others Six. Now truly my mind gives me, if ſuch things were paſt, being of ſo great concernment, Gods people would not be ſo divided and loſt therein.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it is my opinion (and I ſhall ere long give reaſons for it) when the time comes, that theſe Vials ſhall begin to be poured out, the Lord will ſet it<note n="*" place="margin">I Queſtion whether <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliff, Huſſe, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. or the King of <hi>Sweth,</hi> or our <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> either the one in preaching the Goſpel, or the other in going forth to war, had it put upon their hearts by the Spirit of God, that what they did was in order to the fulfilling of this Propheſie, that is, they knew they were called out of the <hi>Temple</hi> to poure out ſuch and ſuch of the laſt plagues upon the Antichriſtian Kingdome. But I doe not queſtion, when the ſet-time is come that the Vials in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed muſt be poured out, but ſuch as ſhall be the inſtruments and miniſters thereof ſhall fully know that they are the Angels appointed for that worke.</note> home upon the hearts of the Saints, as their worke; and not onely ſhall they be Spirited and fitted for it, but they ſhall know by ſome divine appearance that the ſet-time is come; now, as his choſen, &amp; called, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40449:16"/> faithfull, they muſt follow the Lamb with golden Vials in their hands. <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.7. &amp; 16.1. &amp; 18. 1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50.4, 5. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1.</p>
            <p>Howſoever I have thus far declared my ſelf, that none of the <hi>ſeven laſt plagues</hi> are poured out, yet I muſt confeſſe, conſidering how in this thing, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from what hath been, and ſtill is the common received opinion of moſt pious and pretious Saints; I deſire to be very humble and ſober in my thoughts: and in this regard, I profeſs in the preſence of God, &amp; before the whole Iſrael of God, that I ſhall be moſt willing and thankfull (through the good hand of Chriſt, aſſiſting me) to receive better light, from the leaſt of the Flock, if I am miſtaken about the time. And becauſe <hi>the knowledge of the times,</hi> to wit, when the <hi>Vials</hi> are to take their beginning, is a thing of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial concernment; for here if we miſtake, we build upon a ſandie foundation, and the whole Fabrick is mar'd by it: Beſides, the matter of the <hi>Vials</hi> is the main thing, which all waiting Saints at this time are dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to enquire after, as their GENERATION-WORKE. For theſe and other like conſiderations, it is my humble requeſt, that whoſoever amongſt the <hi>Little remnant of the woman,</hi> is not ſatisfied with theſe <hi>reaſons,</hi> but thinks he can produce ſtronger Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (that ſome of the Vials are poured out,) then thoſe which I have brought, that in the ſpirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſo much may be made known to the <hi>followers of the Lamb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to the end the <hi>Anſwer</hi> may be the more full and ſatisfactory to the Saints everywhere, I will here adde a few <hi>Queries,</hi> the which being anſwered with the <hi>Reaſons,</hi> will give the more light to the point in controverſie.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:40449:17"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>1</label> Firſt, If by the <hi>Angel</hi> pouring out the <hi>firſt Vial,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Groſtead, Armachan, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. be meant, who then is the <hi>one of the</hi> 4 <hi>Beaſts which gave unto the</hi> 7 <hi>Angels the</hi> 7 <hi>golden vials?</hi> Rev. 15.7. By the <hi>four Beaſts</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> all Learned and godly Expoſitors do underſtand the Miniſters &amp; Preachers of the Goſpel. If ſo, how then can they who<note n="*" place="margin">If the place be well weighed, I think ſuch will ſee their miſtake who apply any of the Vials to the preaching of the Goſpel. It is one thing to ſtir up another to his work, and another thing to take the work out of his hand.</note> deliver over the <hi>Vials</hi> to be poured out by others, be the doers thereof themſelves?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>2</label> Secondly: whereas the 7 <hi>laſt plagues</hi> are to be poured forth <hi>by</hi> 7 <hi>Angels,</hi> The <hi>Queſtion is,</hi> whether by each Angel a ſingle perſon be meant, or a number. If a number of perſons, then whether all godly, or ſome (ſuppoſe the greater number) ſhall be taken into the work, which are viſibly prophane and wicked, even ſuch as carry the <hi>Marke of the Beaſt.</hi> It ſeems by the Scripture that none ſhall be called to the work of the <hi>Vials,</hi> nor have a hand in the pouring of them out, but<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.6. &amp; 17.14. &amp; 14 1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 102.18. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.45. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6.</note> Saints by calling: If ſo, then how is the 2 or 3 Vial applyable to the <hi>Sweden</hi> or <hi>Engliſh</hi> wars?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, why ſhould the <hi>Song of Moſes &amp; of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 15.34.<note place="margin">I doe not denie but the Lord hath done much for his Church and people in theſe later times; but it will not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow that he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them ſuch victories &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances as to ſing the ſong of <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp;c.</note> be carried up to the times before the <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the witneſſes;</hi> and the <hi>new ſong,</hi> Rev. 14.3. brought down many hundred yeers after? This ſeems to be, 1. Againſt the order of the propheſie. 2. The matter of the ſong, if rightly obſerved, is not ſuteable to any time in which the Beaſts reigned. Neither, laſtly, can it be ſhewed (in my opinion) that ever the Churches of the Saints, ſince the riſe of Antichriſt to this day, have had occaſion, through any deliverance or Victory, <hi>to ſong the Song of</hi> Moſes <hi>and of the Lamb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, That ſome of theſe <hi>Vials</hi> ſhould be pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out in the preaching of the Goſpel, by <hi>Wickliff, Huſſe, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. Others by Parliaments, Armies,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40449:17"/> Navies, &amp;c. Though it be ſo taken, yet I do not ſee any Reaſon for it: for their opinion to me ſeems better grounded (I mean as to order) who apply all the <hi>ſeuen laſt Plagues</hi> either to the<note n="(a)" place="margin">I would have this thing wel conſider'd why we ſhould underſtand in preaching of the goſpel Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als &amp; plagues to be poured out.</note> preaching of the Goſpel onely, or onely to temporal Judgments executed by Civil Powers: But to underſtand one <hi>Viall</hi> poured out in a Spiritual way, another in a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil way, here I deſire proof, as being unſatisfied.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>5</label> Fifthly, That the effect of the <hi>firſt Viall,</hi> whether by <hi>Groſtead, Armachan, Wickliff, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. poured out, ſhould no further extend, then to the diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome particulars of the groſſer ſort of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, as Purgatory, Maſs, Penance, Corporal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, Praying to Saints, Pilgrimages, Indulgences, &amp;c. with a Reformation of ſome people from the practice of ſuch Corruptions; Many groſs Lyes and Errors of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> neither diſcovered nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved at the ſame time by the perſons before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: This I queſtion, becauſe when any <hi>Viall</hi> is poured out, whereſoever it falls, it ſhall<note n="(b)" place="margin">That any of the vials ſhould be like a net, which holds ſome of the greater fiſh, &amp; lets the leſſer goe through the holes, I am not of that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Iſa. 13.9, 16 <hi>Pſ.</hi> 137.9 nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I think that any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation which hath been formerly in Church or State is to be brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any of the Vials.</note> break the Kingdome of Antichriſt fully and wholly; I ſay, not ſome part of it, but extirpate all his Idolatries and Blaſphemies root and branch.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid concerning applying other <hi>Vialls,</hi> whether to the Wars of <hi>Germany,</hi> or ſince here in <hi>England.</hi> The truth is, ſo much Idolatry and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition is unſhaken even to this day, where the <hi>Vials</hi> are ſaid to fall (as the ſubjects of them) as I have ground to think, that nothing yet hath been done ſutable to the nature and effect of any <hi>Viall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>6</label> Sixthly, whereas it is ſaid <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.8. <hi>And the Temple was filled with ſmoke from the glory of God, and from his power; and no man was able to enter into the Temple till the ſeven plagues of the ſeven Angels were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40449:18"/> fulfilled.</hi> Firſt, If by <hi>ſmoke</hi> we underſtand the wrath of God inflicted upon the Antichriſtians for their wicked Idolatry, as ſome do; The queſtion then is, How it can be ſaid, that ſince the Vials began to be poured out, their darkneſs and blindeneſs hath been more and greater then before.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, If by the <hi>Temple filled with ſmoke from the glory of God, &amp;c.</hi> the Spirit alludes to the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Tabernacle, which in the dedication thereof, was wholly filled with a <hi>Cloud</hi> of the glory of the Lord, ſo as <hi>Moſes</hi> could not enter into it, <hi>Exo.</hi> 40.33, 34. And to the hiſtory of the Temple, which likewiſe at the dedication, was filled with the <hi>Cloud</hi> of the glory of God, ſo as the Prieſts could not ſtand to miniſter, ſo long as the glory of <hi>Jehovah</hi> filled the houſe: I ſay, if the place be thus applied (as moſt do) and that <hi>filling</hi> to be a teſtimony and ſigne of Gods glorious preſence and approbation: Then here is ſignified a pouring out of the Spirit upon the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, before they go forth, as tarrying in the Temple (as the Diſciples did at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) untill they ſhould be endued with power from on high, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.59. Indeed this great promiſe of the Father, concerning the ſending of the <hi>Comforter</hi> to teach us all things, and to bring all things to our remembrance, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26. is by Saints now prayed for, and waited for even day and night; but as yet that Spirit is not<note n="(c)" place="margin">It is my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that no Vial ſhall be poured out until the ſaints have the ſpirit poured out upon them, which was promiſed to be given in the laſt days: now if we have not that ſpirit yet, I may well conclude <hi>Groſtead; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machan, Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff, Luther, &amp;c.</hi> had it not in their dayes.</note> given forth from the glory of God, and from his power: Neither probably ſhall we receive it, until the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be out of the wilderneſs. <hi>Who is this that cometh out of the Wilderneſs, like pillars of ſmoke perfumed with myrrhe and frankincenſe, with all powders of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant? Behold his bed, which is Solomons: threeſcore va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant men are about it, of the valiant of Iſrael, &amp;c.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40449:18"/> Go forth, O ye daughters of Zion, and behold King Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the Crown wherewith his mother crowned him in the day of his eſpouſals, and in the day of the gladneſs of his heart,</hi> Song 3.6, 7, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>7</label> Seventhly, Whereas upon the opening of the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Seal,</hi> the firſt Angel of the <hi>ſeven,</hi> which had the <hi>ſeven Trumpets,</hi> ſounded, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.1, 7. The queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, Whether (obſerving order) the <hi>firſt Viall</hi> of the ſeventh is to be poured out, till after the ſounding of the <hi>firſt Trumpet?</hi> If ſo, then we are not to begin the <hi>Vials</hi> until after the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes;</hi> as is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.12, 15. Such as think ſome <hi>Vials</hi> are poured out, do likewiſe hold that the<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Brightman</hi> holds that the ſeventh trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſounded in the year 1558.</note> 
               <hi>ſeventh Trumpet</hi> hath already ſounded. But to grant that ſome <hi>Vials</hi> are paſt, and the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet</hi> not yet ſounded; here ought to be firſt good conſideration, if we will not be children in underſtanding. That the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet</hi> hath not yet ſounded, I think it muſt be granted by all, who hold the Witneſſes not riſen. But that any of the <hi>Vials</hi> are to be poured out, till after the ſounding of the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet,</hi> truly in my opinion, whoſoever ſhall humbly and ſoberly obſerve the Propheſie, ſhall finde little ground to think otherwiſe. <hi>In the dayes of the voyce of the ſeventh Angel, when he ſhall begin to ſound, the myſtery of God ſhould be finiſhed, as he hath declared to his ſervants the Prophets,</hi> Rev. 13.7. Now unleſs by <hi>finiſhing the myſtery,</hi> here is meant the pouring out the ſeven laſt Plagues, I know not what is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. It is ſaid before, <hi>That there ſhould be time no longer,</hi> ver. 6. that is, upon the ſounding of the laſt Trumpet, the ſeven Angels which had the ſeven laſt Plagues, ſhould (obeying the heavenly voyce) go their wayes and pour out the Vials of the wrath
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40449:19"/> of God upon the earth: and ſo <hi>no more time,</hi> viz. for the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet, or any other wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ones to oppreſs the Lords people, whether Jews or Gentiles.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>8</label> Eighthly, I deſire to know, Whether the <hi>ſeven laſt Plagues</hi> do not contemporize with the <hi>third Woe, Rev.</hi> 8.13. If ſo, then no Vial is yet poured out: For the <hi>third Woe</hi> is not to be, until after the riſing of the Witneſſes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.11, 14. Again it is ſaid, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the third Woe cometh quickly;</hi> which is not meant (as I conceive) of ſhortneſs of time betwixt this and the former <hi>Woe,</hi> but of a ſpeedy and quick diſpatch, as to the great work of God at this time. As if he ſhould ſay, When this <hi>Woe</hi> comes upon the world (which I take to be no other then the pouring out of all the Vials) it ſhall be (though ſharp, yet ſhort) not for ſpace of time, any way in compariſon either to the firſt or ſecond <hi>Woe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly, as I have ſaid before, howſoever ſome good men do give many hundred years to the time of the <hi>Vials,</hi> yet for my part, I think otherwiſe; to wit, that after there is a beginning, they ſhall be all poured out, and the work finiſhed in leſs then fifty years. <hi>Behold the third Woe cometh quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reader, Thou mayeſt well perceive in framing theſe Queſtions, that I expect no Anſwer from an Adverſary, but (if any anſwer be made) from a friend or brother, one that ſeeks with the like ſpirit after the underſtanding of the times, to know what <hi>Iſrael</hi> ought to do. And ſhould theſe <hi>Reaſons</hi> upon examination, be found not ſufficient to prove the matter for which they are brought; yet I ſhall have comfort in what I have done, conſidering what
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40449:19"/> 
               <hi>PUBLICK ADVANTAGE</hi> may follow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this occaſion, as to have this <hi>Great Point</hi> the more diligently ſearcht into. I may well call it a GREAT POINT, for I know nothing more neceſſary for Saints, who deſire to follow, Chriſt fully, in the preſent work of their Generation, then to have clear light and knowledge concerning the <hi>Vials;</hi> that is, <hi>Whether any be paſt</hi> (as is the common received opinion) <hi>or none of them yet poured out,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſmall portion which I have in the knowledge of holy things.</p>
            <q>That which I ſee not, teach thou me: If I have done iniquity, I will not offend any more, <bibl>
                  <hi>Job 34.32.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="answers">
            <pb facs="tcp:40449:20"/>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40449:20"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>AFter I had ſent the former Reaſons to the Preſs, there came this <hi>Anſwer</hi> to my hands. It is true, I had a long time expected it, but hearing nothing from my Friend about it, I thought good to publiſh that little by it ſelf, as intending (if I ſhould ſee a providence in it) to ſet forth ſome thing larger upon the <hi>Vials.</hi> Now to have the <hi>Reaſons</hi> printed, and to keep the <hi>Anſwer</hi> by me in ſecret (though I can truly ſay, I knew nothing of the <hi>Anſwer,</hi> till after the <hi>Reaſons</hi> were at the Preſs; yet) to conceal it, it might be judg'd not lovely, and of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port: And therefore I have publiſhed the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer (with a ſhort <hi>Reply</hi>) as it came to my hands: Thus.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall bring out of my poor treaſure (which I have received) in anſwer to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious lines, <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Quaeres,</hi> which were very ſeaſonable and acceptable to me, and not at all offenſive, trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome or unprofitable to me; although I cannot, as yet, concurre with your Opinion therein.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:40449:21"/>
               <head>Anſwer to the 1. Reaſon.</head>
               <p>For <hi>1.</hi> I ſee no ground for that opinion which makes the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the pouring out of the Vials to be at the ſame time with the Witneſſes riſing, and the <hi>144000</hi> muſtering upon <hi>Mount Sion:</hi> And although ſome godly men ſay ſo, that the <hi>144000</hi> and Vials begin together, yet it is no more Argument to me, then that the <hi>1000</hi> years, <hi>Rev. 20.</hi> are begun (and were begun with <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi>) becauſe ſome godly men ſay ſo. <hi>2.</hi> Nor doth the order of the matter (in my eye) manage it. For the holy Ghoſt tells us, in <hi>Chap. 15.1. of another ſigne,</hi> viz. ſeven An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: <hi>ſo that it was another</hi> diſtinct from that in <hi>Chap. 14, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply to the <hi>1.</hi> Anſw.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. The ſtrength of the Reaſon lies not in what godly men do ſay, but in the ground and proof they have for what they ſay: And here I finde nothing in the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> why it ſhould not be ſo.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe <hi>two ſignes,</hi> therefore <hi>diſtinct</hi> as not to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to one time: This will not follow; for in <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. the Primitive Church is repreſented unto <hi>John</hi> by <hi>a wonder</hi> or <hi>ſigne in heaven;</hi> and in ver. 3. there <hi>appeared another ſigne, behold, a great red Dragon, &amp;c.</hi> the which later, is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the <hi>Roman-heathen Emperors,</hi> perſecuting the ſaid Church at the ſame time. So <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in his dreams had <hi>two ſignes,</hi> yet not another <hi>diſtinct,</hi> for both ſignified one thing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.22, 32. But 2. it is called <hi>another ſigne,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. reſpecteth perſons more then things; the latter, things more then perſons: In the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer we have the inſtruments by whom the <hi>Beaſts domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed, in the latter the work it ſelf; that is, how, and in what manner the Judgement written ſhall be executed. But 3. why ſhould theſe words (viz. <hi>another ſigne</hi>) be underſtood <hi>diſtinct</hi> from that in <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. ſeeing in that <hi>Chapter</hi> there is no mention
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40449:21"/> made of any ſigne: More probably therefore they ſhould be carried back to <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. as another, or diſtinct from that <hi>ſigne;</hi> there being no other that I know.</p>
                  <p>Anſw. <hi>And as ſome ſay, I do think he brings there exegeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, with what</hi> Chap. 11, <hi>&amp;</hi> 12, <hi>&amp;</hi> 13, <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. <hi>mention but darkly and cloſely, of the plagues which ſhall come upon the Beaſts dominion gradually by the two Witneſſes: and ſo the order and place of</hi> Chap. 15 <hi>&amp;</hi> 16 <hi>is at</hi> Rev. 11.6. <hi>where the two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> ſmite the earth with plagues, <hi>according</hi> to Chap. 16. 1, 2. Pour out your Vials on the earth: <hi>and ſo</hi> Rev. 11.6. they turn waters into bloud; <hi>according</hi> to Chap. 16.3, 4. the rivers and fountains of waters become bloud; <hi>and this was before the Reſurrection or Slaughter. So that both our Grounds and Order ſeem good: for what can theſe plagues where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the two Witneſſes ſmite the Antichriſtian earth and waters, be, but Vials, and the laſt plagues which are to fall upon the Beaſts dominion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repl.</hi> Firſt, I think the Prophecies of this Book are the more dark to us, through our miſ-placing of things, and carrying them diſorderly forward and backward, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the holy Ghoſt keeps a better Method. For thus in brief I take it: The <hi>Witneſſes</hi> being treated of, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. and the <hi>wilderneſs-ſtate</hi> of the woman, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. he proceeds to the Tyranny and Idolatry of the <hi>Beaſt, Chap.</hi> 13. and ſo ends the whole Hiſtory, or Acts, of the <hi>two Witneſſes, Woman,</hi> and <hi>Beaſt,</hi> viz. as to the 42 months or 1260 <hi>days.</hi> What follows from the beginning of <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. they are things afterwards to come to paſs: that is, The <hi>Witneſſes</hi> being riſen, and the <hi>Woman out of the wilderneſs,</hi> in the 144000 ſtanding with the <hi>Lamb on mount Sion, Chap.</hi> 14. the Lord now will ſend forth the Rod of his ſtrength out of <hi>Sion, Chap.</hi> 15 <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. But becauſe the carrying on of this great work cannot be without underſtanding the Prophecies of the laſt time; hence, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. one of the <hi>ſeven Angels
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40449:22"/> which had the Vials,</hi> ſhews unto <hi>John</hi> (repreſenting the Church near the time of the end) <hi>the judgement of the great Whore:</hi> ſignifying, that theſe mighty ones whom the Lord hath called for his anger, ſhall have it not onely in their hearts to fulfil his will; but what they do, ſhall be know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly in order thereunto: ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9, 10. &amp; 22.8. Then follows, <hi>Chap.</hi> 18. the total and final deſolation of the <hi>Beaſts dominion,</hi> fuller and clearer than before: for which, <hi>Chap.</hi> 19. there is <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> ſalvation, and glory, and honour, and power, given unto the Lord our God. Thus it is a continued Hiſtory, without breach of order: onely ſomething concerning the <hi>laſt Vial, Chap.</hi> 14.19, 20. and the <hi>Armageddon-battel, Chap.</hi> 16. is the ſame with <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.11, 12, 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. As I ſee no order in taking the <hi>ſackcloth-Witneſſes, Rev.</hi> 11. to be any of the <hi>ſeven Angels, Chap.</hi> 15. ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, what you ſay for it, to me ſeems no Ground at all; as, <hi>ſmiting the earth, turning waters into blood,</hi> &amp;c. For the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> before their <hi>riſing</hi> poured out no plagues upon the <hi>Earth, Sea, Fountains,</hi> &amp;c. what they did, was no other then did the Prophets of old, who pronounced, indeed, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral judgements againſt the Nations: <hi>The burden of the Lord upon Babylon, Egypt, Damaſcus, Nineveh,</hi> &amp;c. and in this ſence were ſet over the Nations, and over the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, to root out, and to pull down, and to deſtroy, and to throw down, <hi>&amp;c. Jer.</hi> 1.10. ſo, to take the wine-cup of fury from the hand of the Lord, and to cauſe all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to drink it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 25. but in this they were no <hi>Vial-Angels,</hi> as to the execution of any temporal and real plagues. So the <hi>ſack-cloth-Witneſſes,</hi> in ſmiting the <hi>earth,</hi> what did they? they <hi>propheſied againſt many peoples, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and tongues, and kings:</hi> Rev. 10.9, 10, 11. In this way I confeſs they <hi>poured out</hi> Vials, <hi>ſmote the earth, turned waters into bloud,</hi> &amp;c. but not otherwiſe.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:40449:22"/>
                  <p>I might adde, how <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (her Walls, Temple, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) was ſmitten, and turned into bloud as by <hi>Nebuchad-nezzar,</hi> ſo by the Prophets too. Now we all know, this was not done neither at one time, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like: what the later did, was by mouth, prophetically; what the other did, was by hand, as making good the word of the Lord in the mouth of his Prophets. So <hi>Joaſh</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> at the Prophet's bidding, took arrows and ſmote on the ground, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.17, 18. here was a ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the <hi>Syrians,</hi> and victory over them: yet ſo, as dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering far, from the Plagues and Vials afterwards pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out. For Application, thus: The <hi>Sackcloth-Witneſſes ſmite the earth, and have power over waters to turn them into blood:</hi> but obſerve the place; this is done in <hi>the days of their prophecie,</hi> Rev. 11.6. evidently ſhewing, that what they did was by prophecie, expreſſed a little before, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.11. that is, they foretold the fall of <hi>Babylon, Popes, Cardinals, Biſhops, Prieſts, Tythes, Maſs,</hi> and the reſt of her, Fornications: but here was no execution of the <hi>laſt plagues;</hi> that was left for others to do afterward; <hi>viz. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Angels come out of the Temple,</hi> &amp;c. Rev. 15.</p>
                  <p>But again, ſhould I grant (which I do not) that the <hi>ſmiting of the earth, and turning waters into bloud,</hi> Rev. 11. is for the matter and manner alike with <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.2, 3, 4. yet this would not prove the ſame to be all one, in reference either of the Inſtruments or Time. They were Plagues and Vials which were poured out upon the old world, <hi>Sodom, Egypt,</hi> &amp;c. yet we all know, they are things di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and apart. But to come nearer, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.8. it is ſaid, <hi>The third part of the ſea became bloud:</hi> are the <hi>ſackcloth-Witneſſes</hi> here the inſtruments? Howſoever I do not think there lies much weight meerly in words and phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet it is much better (in my underſtanding) to refer the Acts of the <hi>ſackcloth-Witneſſes,</hi> viz. <hi>turning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> into
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40449:23"/> blood,</hi> &amp;c. as the effects of the <hi>Trumpets,</hi> rather then of the <hi>Vials.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have been the larger in this Point, becauſe the main Ground which the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> and others have, in holding the <hi>Sackcloth-Witneſſes</hi> and <hi>Vial-Angel</hi> all one; it is, for that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.6. mention is made of <hi>turning waters into blood,</hi> and <hi>ſmiting the earth;</hi> and ſomething like it (for it is but ſomething, and very little, as I ſhall ſhew after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) expreſſed, <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.2, 3, 4. Now truly, in my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, the Foundation is too weak to lay ſo much weight upon it.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, that the <hi>earth</hi> is <hi>ſmitten,</hi> and <hi>waters turned into bloud,</hi> by <hi>Waldo, Groſted, Armachan, Wickliff, Huſs, Luther, &amp;c.</hi> preaching the Word of Truth, and ſo pouring out a Vial; and other Vials are poured out by Civil Powers, in their Armies, Navies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this is more, I think, then is in the text. For if the <hi>Vials</hi> are fill'd with the Goſpel of the Kingdom, then I ſay there is no War in them; if War, then no Goſpel: to take them both ways, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be.</p>
                  <p>Anſw. 3. <hi>Beſides, if ſo be (as you ſay) that</hi> Chap. 15. &amp; 16. <hi>begin with the full harveſt and vintage mentioned</hi> Chap. 14. verſ. 15, &amp;c. <hi>then methinks you do not make the Vials and the</hi> 144000 <hi>in verſ.</hi> 1, 2. <hi>to contemporize (which is your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) becauſe the</hi> 144000 <hi>in the former part of the Chapter, are up before the full harveſt or vintage of the whole earth, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this later part of the Chapter: and the firſt, ſecond, and third Angels have work to do, between the riſe of the</hi> 144000 <hi>and the harveſt of the earth ripe. But the Vials are begun before the harveſt of the whole earth: ſo that this Expoſition cannot be the order of the holy Ghoſt, in my judgement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repl.</hi> I confeſs, the Truth brings forth no Abſurdity or Contradiction; neither do I ſee how any ſuch thing can be fairly concluded from the <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:40449:23"/>
                  <p>For 1. I finde not in the Reaſon, where it is ſaid that the 144000 do contemporize with the <hi>Harveſt</hi> and <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi> But 2. Let it be ſo; yet here will follow no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction: for though, in a ſenſe, a man may be ſaid to be before his work, as making himſelf fit and ready for it; yet may he and his work be together. That the 144000 may be riſen before the <hi>harveſt of the earth</hi> is ripe; I ſay, ſuppoſe this, (though I hold it not) yet may the 144000 contemporize with the <hi>harveſt,</hi> as being the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers thereof.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That <hi>three Angels</hi> have <hi>work to do between the riſe of the</hi> 144000 <hi>and the harveſt;</hi> to this I ſay, 1. The <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> are of the number of the 144000; for that is a Type of the Lords whole hoſt muſtered againſt <hi>Babylon.</hi> 2. For the work there, of the three Angels, it belongs to the <hi>Harveſt</hi> (as part of it) now ready to be reap'd. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.10, 11, 12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Scripture will warrant us to ſay, that the <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of the earth</hi> was ripe at the riſing of the <hi>Witneſſes.</hi> When the <hi>four hundred yeers</hi> were expired, which the Lord ſpeaks of unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 15.13. the <hi>iniquity of the Amorites was then full:</hi> ſo the <hi>fourty and two months</hi> being out, the <hi>Beaſts dominion</hi> is ripe. As a field of Corn is not cut down aſſoon as it is ripe, neither is it cut down all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but by degrees: ſo <hi>Babylon,</hi> though ripe at the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> (the <hi>fourty and two months</hi> of her reign being ended) nevertheleſs, as the <hi>Beaſts dominion</hi> ſhall not be deſtroyed all at one time, ſo there will be ſome preparation to the work, (as <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6, 7, 8, 9. and 18.1, 2, 3, 4.) as well as the execution of it. True it is, if we conſider the times of <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Groſtead, Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan,</hi> &amp;c. the <hi>harveſt</hi> then was not ripe, and therefore they could not be any of the <hi>ſeven Angels,</hi> Rev. 15. for the whole dominion of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> muſt be ripe, before any of the <hi>ſeven laſt plagues</hi> will be poured out.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40449:24"/>
                  <p>Anſw. 4. <hi>Moreover, if this your interpretation were the genuine ſenſe, I ſuppoſe every Vial would be an univerſal Vial, as on the whole earth: but it is very apparent, that every Vial is not an univerſal Vial, nor any, until the Armageddon-day. And therefore ſome think, (upon good grounds) this in</hi> Rev. 14.14. <hi>of the harveſt of the whole earth, and that of the Armageddon,</hi> Rev. 19. <hi>contemporize.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. If any ſuch thing may be infer'd from the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, it is otherwiſe then I hold; for I hold the contrary. Indeed, this I have ſaid, and am ſtill of the opinion: 1. Though no <hi>Vial</hi> be <hi>univerſal,</hi> yet whereſoever any falls, (whether firſt, ſecond, third, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) the effects thereof ſhall be ſuch, on the ſubject where it is poured, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Idolatry and Tyranny is thereby ſuppreſs'd and put down, the ſame ſhall be there no more.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Though I think no Vial <hi>univerſal,</hi> yet this I think, that by <hi>earth,</hi> Rev. 16.2. is not meant <hi>the groſſer parts of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> viz. Maſſes, Pilgrimages, Indulgences, Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, praying to Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the word <hi>earth</hi> is often uſed in this Book, and elſewhere; but never, to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is it taken in ſuch a ſenſe, <hi>viz.</hi> for half, or part of the whole. And therefore, as I ſaid, though <hi>no Vial be univerſal,</hi> (as extending everywhere and in all places) yet in ſome ſort univerſal, that is, whereſoever any <hi>Vial</hi> falls, not onely there ſhall the <hi>groſſer</hi> and greater parts of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry be deſtroyed, but the <hi>finer</hi> and leſſer, (as ſome call it) that is, all the fornications of the Whore, root and branch. As for the preſent, I ſee nothing yet, that looks like a <hi>Vial.</hi> We may take up our complaint in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's words: <hi>Like as a woman with childe, that draweth near the time of her delivery, is in pain, and cryeth out in her pangs: ſo have we been in thy ſight, O Lord: we have been with childe, we have been in pain; we have as it were brought forth winde: we have not wrought any deliverance in the earth, neither have
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40449:24"/> the inhabitants of the world fallen.</hi> Iſai. 26.17, 18.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That ſome think the <hi>harveſt of the whole earth,</hi> Rev. 14.14. and that of <hi>Armageddon,</hi> Rev. 19. <hi>contemporize;</hi> it is true: but that it is (as you ſay) upon <hi>good ground,</hi> this I queſtion: For the holy Ghoſt there, makes a plain di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between the <hi>harveſt</hi> and the <hi>vintage;</hi> and the former to be meant of the <hi>Beaſts dominion,</hi> which ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh under the <hi>five firſt Vials;</hi> the later, which begins at <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. belongs to the <hi>Armageddon-battel,</hi> Rev. 19. and falls under the <hi>ſeventh Vial,</hi> and part of the <hi>ſixth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anſw. 5. <hi>And laſtly, I think there is a miſtake in what you ſay in the margin, that the</hi> 144000 <hi>are the Angels of the Vials, ſeeing the holy Ghoſt ſpeaks of them beſides, as the remnant of the womans ſeed,</hi> Rev. 12. ult. <hi>and the called, faithful, and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi> Rev. 17.15. <hi>(who I know ſhall go along with the execution, and ſerve in it) but he ſpeaks in the ſingular number of Angel to every Vial, and never above two, as in the third Vial. So that I neither incline to the two Witneſſes, as I ſaid before, with whom the remnant go along, and to whom the power of the plagues is given as oft as they will,</hi> Rev. 11.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repl.</hi> Firſt, (as I ſaid even now) I take the 144000 to be an Univerſal Type, repreſenting the perſons of all the Saints, who after the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes</hi> ſhall follow the <hi>Lamb</hi> in executing the vengeance of the Lord, and the vengeance of his Temple upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> the people whom he ſhall create for his praiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.18. that is, the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> Chap. 14, &amp; 15, &amp; 16. So the <hi>called, choſen and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> Chap. 17. 14. and the <hi>Angel,</hi> Chap. 18. 1, 2, &amp;c. it is the ſame number that were <hi>ſealed,</hi> Chap. 6.4. and why not the like ſignificant Type?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If I do not miſtake you, the <hi>remnant of the womans ſeed,</hi> and the <hi>one hundred fourty and four thouſand,</hi> you make to be all one: But to this I agree not: for, 1. The <hi>War</hi> in <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. ult. is <hi>the Dragon</hi>'s; this, <hi>the Lamb</hi>'s. 2. There,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40449:25"/> he firſt fights; but here, others begin with him. 3. That <hi>War</hi> ſeems to be before the <hi>riſing</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes:</hi> The <hi>Dragon</hi> not prevailing againſt the <hi>woman in the wilderneſs,</hi> falls upon her <hi>ſeed,</hi> nearer home; a <hi>remnant,</hi> which did not at all flie into the wilderneſs; the <hi>woman</hi> being weak, (and therefore call'd <hi>the weaker veſſel,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.7.) and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to make reſiſtance againſt the Dragons wrath in the Beaſt, ſeeks by flight to ſave her ſelf: But the <hi>remnant of her ſeed,</hi> that is, a generation after, through providence have oportunity and advantage to withſtand him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eſcaping in ſuch a way. And this war of the <hi>Dragon</hi> with the <hi>remnant of the womans ſeed,</hi> Rev. 12. <hi>ult.</hi> may probably have ſome reference to the <hi>Swethen wars</hi> in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many;</hi> ſo unto <hi>ours,</hi> and to the <hi>Civil wars</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>But 3. I do not well know what you mean, by ſaying <hi>The holy Ghoſt ſpeaks in the ſingular number, of Angel, to every Vial,</hi> &amp;c. Do you mean, that the 144000 cannot be the Angels, Chap. 16. becauſe the number is too great? If you underſtand (as I think you do) by the <hi>firſt Angel,</hi> all the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> from <hi>Waldo</hi> to <hi>Luther,</hi> it will exceed by far the <hi>number</hi> here. Beſides, though I hold the <hi>ſeven Angels</hi> to be a part of that <hi>company;</hi> yet I do not ſay the <hi>ſeven An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> are the whole number, much leſs that every Angel takes in the <hi>one hundred fourty and four thouſand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, whereas you ſay, <hi>I rather incline to the two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> &amp;c. for my part, I think, if their perſons, work, and time, be duely weighed by you, your inclination will be ſome other way.</p>
                  <p>Anſw. 1. <hi>The preaching of the Goſpel is</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſweet; and yet, for all that, very bitter, and full of plague, in the effects thereof, to the enemies of Chriſt: for ſo was Chriſts own preaching a great plague to the Phariſees, Rulers, and Jews. Now we ſay, The effects thereof were plagues to the Popiſh earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:40449:25"/> in <hi>Groſted</hi>'s, <hi>Wickliff</hi>'s, <hi>Waldo</hi>'s, <hi>Huſs</hi> and <hi>Luther</hi>'s <hi>time, and made them rage, fret, ſtorm, burn, and break out into filthy ulcers, diſeaſes and diſtempers; and ſo there fell upon them a real and proper plague under this Vial: and God's wrath upon them, was ſo eminently ſeen, that</hi> Bellarmine <hi>himſelf ſayes, That ever ſince</hi> Luther, <hi>and thoſe Men preached the Pope to be Antichriſt, their Church decreaſed, and many fell from it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. It gives cauſe of ſuſpition, That a Text is wreſted, when it is <hi>alone,</hi> and hath not another to help it: as I ſaid before, by <hi>Earth,</hi> Rev. 16.2. to underſtand the <hi>groſſer part of Popery;</hi> I queſtion, whether ſuch an Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition can be confirmed by the mouth of two or three Witneſſes. So here, if this Text by Conſequences and Effects prove the Cauſe, it ſtands alone, (by it ſelf) for ought I know. The Text ſaith, <hi>And I ſaw another ſign in heaven, great and marvellous, ſeven Angels having the ſeven laſt plagues: for in them is filled up the wrath of God,</hi> Rev. 15.1. Not one word here of Effects, but what is in the Vials, to be <hi>wrath; full of the wrath of God.</hi> No Goſpel ſo much as named.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Howſoever I grant, (as being moſt true) it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for men in the hearing of the Word, to be thereby more wicked and vile, than they were before; yet the Word is no <hi>Vial of wrath,</hi> neither are the Publiſhers, <hi>Angels of Vials of wrath:</hi> the Cauſe is not in the Word, nor in the <hi>Angels;</hi> but by accident: as when purblinde people come forth into the Sun, their ſight is hereby darker, and more obſcure, not that the Sun is the cauſe, but the cauſe and fault is in themſelves.</p>
                  <p>That the <hi>Phariſees, Rulers and Jews;</hi> ſo the <hi>Popiſh Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> in hearing the Word, by <hi>accident,</hi> were blinded; it's true: but to conclude therefore, (as it muſt be ſo, or it's nothing to the matter) That either <hi>Chriſt, Groſted, Wickliff,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40449:26"/> Waldo, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. were Angels of wrath, and it was the wrath of God which they poured out of their <hi>Vials;</hi> Here I hope, men will be rather ſober than raſh. True it is, Mr. <hi>Tilling.</hi> ſaith, <hi>The matter of each Vial is pure wrath; yea, full wrath,</hi> as Chap. 15. 1, 7. Chap. 16.1. Then I ſay, No Vial is poured out in preaching the Doctrines of Chriſt: for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tter of the Goſpel is not <hi>pure and full wrath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Popiſh Earthlings</hi> through the preaching of <hi>Groſted, Wickliff, Waldo, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. did <hi>rage, fret, ſtorm; broke out into filthy ulcers,</hi> &amp;c. it being nothing to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I leave it. Howbeit, I could ſay much againſt it, as it is applied: but let the effects of their preaching be as you ſay, yet this proves no <hi>Vial;</hi> For 1. there was preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and writing againſt the <hi>Popiſh Earthlings,</hi> long before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, even from the firſt riſe of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> with the like effects. Conſequently then, the Vials muſt take their beginning from the firſt riſing of the <hi>Beaſt.</hi> 2. Such effects of preaching belongs not to the <hi>Vials.</hi> If we bring <hi>Waldo, Groſted, Wickliff, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. to the <hi>Trumpets,</hi> here we ſhall finde ſome ſutableneſs and accord, as to the Time, Perſons, Work and Effects.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It was no <hi>wrath of a Vial,</hi> that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> either ſaw or ſpoke of: for when the time comes, that theſe <hi>Vials</hi> ſhall be poured out, the Prieſts (whether in <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) will have little leaſure or heart to write Books a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Intereſt and Cauſe of Chriſt, (or ought elſe in that kinde) but ſtudy rather how to eſcape the conſuming fire every way about them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.15, 16. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.7, 8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.46.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. <hi>Secondly, we aſſent to you alſo, that thoſe good men before mentioned,</hi> did eat up the Book, and propheſie, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.8, 9, 10, 11. before or againſt many Peoples, Kings and Nations. <hi>Now the eating of the Book and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying, was the preparing of it; but when it was opened, then the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40449:26"/> Vials come out, and ſo executed God's wrath upon that Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo that both theſe will ſtand together,</hi> viz. <hi>the propheſying, and the plaguing them, as the effects of their propheſying: for all the Angels of the Vials muſt eat the Book.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rep.</hi> What is meant by their <hi>propheſying,</hi> I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before: Now there is ſomething here, which I do not well underſtand.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. How <hi>eating the Book</hi> and <hi>propheſying,</hi> ſhould be before the <hi>Book is open.</hi> I think rather, the <hi>Book</hi> muſt be <hi>opened</hi> firſt, and <hi>propheſying</hi> follows after, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.30, 31. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.10, 11.</p>
                  <p>Neither 2. do I know the diſtinction between <hi>propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as preparing, then opening the Book for the Vials to come out.</hi> As for <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. they had no <hi>Vials of wrath,</hi> nor did they prepare any ſuch thing for the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: they neither intended nor deſired mens deſtruction, but rather their peace, health, life and ſalvation in Jeſus Chriſt. It is true, the <hi>Angels of the</hi> 7 <hi>last plagues,</hi> will come out to execute God's wrath: this I ſay will be their work, for to make way for the everlaſting Goſpel to be preached, unto every Nation, and Kindred, and Tongue, and People; a work altogether different from the <hi>Witneſſes propheſying in ſackcloth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. If all the <hi>Angels of the Vials must eat the Book,</hi> it will hardly be proved, whether ſome who are held to be the <hi>Angels,</hi> did ever <hi>eat that Book:</hi> for if the Tree be known by the Fruit, they were ſo far from <hi>eating</hi> it, as that they were viſible and profeſt perſecutors of ſuch as in truth did <hi>eat</hi> the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Howſoever I believe that all the <hi>Angels of the Vials</hi> ſhall be wonderfully enlightned with the knowledge of the times, as to ſee their works and movings plainly before them, far beyond what either <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machan, Huſs, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. had; yet that <hi>eating of the Book,</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:40449:27"/> Rev. 10.9, 10. is another thing, then properly to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to any <hi>Angels of the Vials.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anſw. <hi>It is not preaching alone, or the miniſterial witneſs onely, that plagued them; but the magiſtratical alſo; who joyned with the miniſterial in every Generation: ſo that the</hi> 2 <hi>witneſſes were together in their effects or plagues that fell upon them. And therefore your ſecond Reaſon in my Opinion is ſomewhat uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and upon a miſtaken Ground or Principal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. There is nothing in this <hi>Anſwer,</hi> (ſhould it be all granted) to the matter. For though Miniſters and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates joyn together againſt the <hi>power of the Beast,</hi> it doth not follow, therefore together they pour out any one of the <hi>last plagues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Should I follow you, and begin at <hi>Waldo,</hi> and ſo downward to our times, I could ſhew you (if need were) not <hi>in every Generation</hi> did the <hi>magistratical and ministerial witneſſes joyn together.</hi> For in ſeveral Ages the faithful Servants of Chriſt had no aid or ſuccour from the civil Powers at all, much leſs helped them to <hi>plague the Whore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. For ſome of thoſe <hi>Vials</hi> (which you apply) as poured out by the <hi>ministerial</hi> and <hi>magistratical witneſſes joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> I think they were rather the actions of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtians themſelves, one plaguing another, for worldly and baſe reſpects.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, It is a great miſtake (I think) to make worldly imployment (as wars and fighting the Enemy) a work of the <hi>ſackcloth-witneſſes;</hi> for their work is <hi>propheſying,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they ſmite the <hi>Beast's Dominion</hi> any other way than <hi>ſpiritually,</hi> though it do concern civil things. There are many wayes to hold forth <hi>a witneſs</hi> and <hi>Testimony</hi> for Jeſus Chriſt: but for that place in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3, 6. it takes in no <hi>magistratical witneſs,</hi> if the thing be meerly civil: And this is plain in the very Text, <hi>They ſhall propheſie</hi> 1260 <hi>dayes.</hi> Again, <hi>In the dayes of their propheſie,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:40449:27"/>
                  <p>And here it will not be amiſs to declare briefly my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion concerning the 2 <hi>witneſſes,</hi> Rev. 11. <hi>The witneſſes</hi> I take to be a <hi>Generation-Confeſsion or Testimony in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of Christ, againſt the Idolatries and Blaſphemies of the Beaſt, and all his Helpers, during the time of the</hi> 42 <hi>months.</hi> I call it firſt a <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> to diſtinguiſh a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> from a <hi>Truth.</hi> A man may profeſs and practiſe many excellent and eminent Truths, and yet not have <hi>the Teſtimony of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> Rev. 12.17. for this conſiſteth in declaring againſt the evils of perſons and things. Secondly, I call it a <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration-witneſs,</hi> becauſe it muſt be proper to a man's own time, <hi>viz.</hi> as to own what is of God, <hi>then</hi> oppoſed and perſecuted; and what is of the <hi>Dragon</hi> and <hi>Beaſt,</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, commanded, authorized, <hi>then</hi> to teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it: and if we do not this, we are no <hi>Generation-Confeſſors,</hi> or <hi>Witneſſes.</hi> I ſay, whatſoever <hi>Truth,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, we acknowledge, it is not to the matter, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7, 8. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.8. &amp; 4.19, 20. &amp; 13.31. &amp; 8.25. &amp; 18.5. &amp; 23.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.2, 9. &amp; 6.9. As a Souldier, if he ſee the Enemy dead at his foot, will not ſtand cutting and hacking of him; but leaving him, follows and fights the ſtanding Enemy: ſo to declare againſt Idolatry and Tyranny which is already put down (and nothing elſe;) this is not <hi>Souldier-like,</hi> and as becomes a brave Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt: it muſt be (to be a <hi>Witneſs</hi> indeed) the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtanding abominations of our preſent time, which we muſt boldly and openly teſtifie againſt.</p>
                  <p>Again, they are ſaid to be <hi>two Witneſſes,</hi> not in reference to <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> and <hi>Miniſtery;</hi> but <hi>two,</hi> as to the things ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther witneſſed for or againſt; that is, as being compriſed in two heads, (neither more nor leſs:) 1. <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> or <hi>Spiritual:</hi> 2. <hi>Civil,</hi> or <hi>Secular.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now whereas neer or toward the end of the 1260 <hi>days,</hi> this <hi>two-fold Witneſs</hi> ſhall riſe and ſpeak out with more
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40449:28"/> clearneſs, and in the Demonſtration of the Spirit, and of power, then before; ſuddenly and ſtrangely it ſhall be ſlain: which <hi>ſlaying</hi> I take to be no other way, then in the <hi>Teſtimony;</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſt's witneſs,</hi> ſo high and eminent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is knock'd in the head. In ſome, it is <hi>ſlain</hi> through Preferment, Honour, great Places: In others, through a Baſe ſpirit, and Fear of ſufferings: In others, through Bonds and Impriſonment: In ſome, through Hypocriſie, Apoſtacie, and a fearful Departing from God. So that the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> relate not to the perſons of men, (for the perſon may live, though his Witneſs be ſlain) neither to any Office or Calling, (whether Magiſtracie or Miniſtry) but meant of a <hi>Generation-teſtimony</hi> for Truth and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, againſt all Ungodlineſs and Unrighteouſneſs of men.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>third Reaſon.</hi> To your third Reaſon, the integral of which lies in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Queſtion, What reaſon there is, to begin there, as you ſay, and not after nor before; I anſwer, <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe, till then, the Beaſt was not grownfull enough for the Vials: but then he was at a full growth, and all the world wondered after him.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. Here again you are much miſtaken, to think that the <hi>Beaſt was grown full enough for the Vials,</hi> in the times of <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Huſs, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. For he comes not to his <hi>growth for the Vials,</hi> till the time of his reign be expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that is, the <hi>fourty and two months.</hi> The ſins of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morites,</hi> no doubt, were many and great, in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s time; yet not grown full enough for the <hi>Vials,</hi> till the <hi>four hundred years</hi> were expired, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.13, 16. To make the iniquity either of a Perſon or State full, the time muſt run out which God hath appointed.</p>
               <p>Hence then I might frame this Argument: <q>
                     <p>Till the Beaſt be grown full for the Vials, they are not to be poured out upon him. <hi>(So you.)</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:40449:28"/>
                     <p>But till the fourty and two months are expired, the Beaſt is not grown full enough for the Vials. <hi>(So the Scripture.)</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore none of the Vials are to be poured out upon the Beaſt till the fourty and two months are expired.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But 2. had you ſaid that the Beaſt in <hi>Waldo</hi>'s or <hi>Luther</hi>'s time, was <hi>grown full enough,</hi> as to be diſcovered and known to be the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> therein I would agree with you: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin elſe where you will, (for it is all one) whether at <hi>Waldo</hi> or <hi>Luther,</hi> or four hundred years before either of them, the <hi>Beaſt</hi> might be ſaid to be grown full enough for the <hi>Vials;</hi> the time onely excepted, which is the main thing.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 2. <hi>Becauſe then (and not before or after) the</hi> groſs earth of Papacie, <hi>in all manner of filthy traſh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>appeared in height eminently, and moſt univerſally, as the adequate ſubject of the firſt Vial.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. I have once or twice touch'd this <hi>wreſt-inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation;</hi> and the rather, leſt we ſhould fall into the fault of our fore-fathers, who, becauſe Errours for a while had paſs'd currant from hand to hand, at length believed them, without any tryal. That by <hi>earth,</hi> Rev. 16.2. ſhould be meant <hi>the groſſer parts of Popery,</hi> truly in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, it is as weakly gathered from that place, as a thing can be. For among the ſeveral acceptations of the word <hi>(earth)</hi> in Scripture, not one will be found to <hi>ſecond</hi> ſuch a ſence. It is no good way, to have the Scriptures follow things; but rather, let things follow the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. Becauſe we ſee, by the preaching of <hi>Waldo, Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff, Armachan, Huſs, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. nothing fell, but a little of the <hi>groſſer part of Popery:</hi> therefore we muſt expound <hi>earth</hi> to be that <hi>groſſer part of Popery:</hi> this is not to give pre-eminence to the Scriptures: but, on the other hand, when the Word hath its latitude, fulneſs, perfection; to apply then what is ſutable and agreeable to that, this is to give honour to whom honour is due.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:40449:29"/>
               <p>But 2. and to come nearer to the Anſwer: <hi>Then</hi> (ſay you) <hi>and not before or after.</hi> Truly I think, this will not appear ſo, in either of your ways; though by <hi>earth</hi> we ſhould underſtand the <hi>groſſer parts of Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For 1. The <hi>groſſer part of Popery</hi> appeared in height, eminently and univerſally, ſome hundred years even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Waldo,</hi> (yea, and witneſſed againſt) as in his time, though not ſo publickly, boldly, and clearly oppoſed, as then. 2. Neither did the <hi>good men</hi> you mention, put down the <hi>groſſer part of Popery;</hi> it remained in moſt places in height, eminently and univerſally, as before. It is, in my opinion, a ſtrange ſence, that by <hi>earth</hi> ſhould be meant the <hi>groſſer part of Popery,</hi> as the <hi>adequate ſubject of the firſt Vial;</hi> and <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Armachan, Groſted, Huſs, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. the Angel of it; and yet the <hi>earth</hi> (the <hi>adequate ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Vial</hi>) not touch'd in moſt places, as to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying and rooting of it up. 3. To ſay, <hi>Nor after,</hi> I may ſay, <hi>What meaneth then the bleating of the ſheep?</hi> &amp;c. Is there not, in <hi>Rome, Italy, France, Spain, Germany, Poland,</hi> &amp;c. as much of this <hi>groſs earth,</hi> as was in <hi>Waldo</hi>'s or <hi>Luther</hi>'s time?</p>
               <p>Anſw. 3. <hi>Becauſe then (and not before or after) were the effects of the firſt Vial,</hi> viz. <hi>plague-ſores, burning, broyling, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ulcers, breaking out, and begun to appear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> To let paſs what is ſuppoſed, but not proved, <hi>viz.</hi> that the <hi>Sackcloth-witneſſes</hi> are <hi>Vial-angels;</hi> the <hi>plague-ſores, burning, broyling,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.2. the effects of <hi>Waldo</hi>'s and <hi>Luther</hi>'s <hi>preaching:</hi> I ſay, The <hi>Beaſt</hi> raged, and had ſuch ſores and boils upon him, (as you ſpeak of) many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years before their times; occaſioned by other <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> who ſpake boldly againſt the Tyranny and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the <hi>See of Rome.</hi> I could name many who ſuffered for their faithful Teſtimony this way. 2. The <hi>Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, Non-conformiſts,</hi> &amp;c. (as they are call'd) by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40449:29"/> their Doctrines and Practices, <hi>ſmote the earth,</hi> (as you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand) more eminently and effectually then either <hi>Waldo</hi> or <hi>Luther</hi> did; and yet theſe came forth after them. And, to ſpeak the truth, to begin the <hi>Vials</hi> at theſe men, it hath more ſhew of ſomething like a <hi>Vial,</hi> then the other. For, to bring in <hi>Groſted</hi> and <hi>Armachan,</hi> and ſuch men, as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels clothed in pure and fine linen, and having their breſts girded with golden girdles;</hi> the oddes and diſparity (in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) is too great as once to be named.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 4. <hi>Becauſe till then, the ſeventh part of the ſixth Trumpet, or the plagues by the hands of the Turks,</hi> (Rev. 9.14, 15, 16, &amp;c. <hi>the four Angels looſed from the river</hi> Euphrates) <hi>were executing upon the Papists; ſo that theſe last plagues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan not before: and that they began not after, I ſuppoſe the effects of</hi> Groſtead, Armachan, Waldo, <hi>(whom we exclude not)</hi> Wickcliff<hi>'s,</hi> Huſſe<hi>'s,</hi> Luther<hi>'s preaching, eaſily prove. That is a miſtake, to think we leave out</hi> Waldo, <hi>or the Witneſſes of his time, ſeeing we apply it not to perſons, but to Witneſſes. And ſeeing the earth (the ſubject of this firſt Vial) was ſo univerſal,</hi> viz. <hi>in all carnal Chriſtendom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. In ſaying, that <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Armachan,</hi> &amp;c. began the <hi>Vials</hi> under part of the <hi>ſixth Trumpet,</hi> you quite loſe the matter ſo much pleaded for; becauſe the <hi>Vials</hi> begin not till the beginning of the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet,</hi> as the Trumpets begin not till the opening of the <hi>ſeventh Seal,</hi> Rev. 8.1, 2, 3. So then, according to the time which you apply them to, they may be Angels (and indeed, I think ſo they were) of the <hi>Trumpets,</hi> but not Angels of the <hi>ſeven laſt plagues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. I do not ſee what Ground there is, in the leaſt, to take the beginning of the Vials from the <hi>Turks executing plagues upon the Papiſts:</hi> for the Papiſts were plagued by them, both before <hi>Waldo</hi>'s time, and long after. Beſides, for the <hi>four Angels looſed from the river Euphrates,</hi> though I
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40449:30"/> conſent with you, that the <hi>Saracens</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> are there meant; yet to what time the place ſhould be applied, it is doubtful. <hi>Brightman</hi> refers it to the riſe of the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire,</hi> about the year 1300: and gathers, that the power of the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhall continue to the year 1696, and then finally be broken. <hi>Mede</hi> thinks the <hi>four Angels</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie ſo many <hi>Sultans</hi> or <hi>Kingdoms</hi> into which the <hi>Turks</hi> were divided, when firſt having paſſed over <hi>Euphrates,</hi> they had ſpread themſelves into the neighbouring Coaſts of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> about the year 1080. Others aſcend high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, even to <hi>Mahumet</hi> himſelf, the firſt Author of the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Impieties and Blaſphemies, about <hi>anno</hi> 620. So <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger, Illiricus, Pareus, Mayer,</hi> &amp;c. And, in my opinion, they have the better ground who take it thus: which was many hundred years before <hi>Waldo</hi>'s time.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, whereas you ſay, <hi>It is a miſtake, to think we leave out</hi> Waldo, <hi>or the Witneſſes of his time, ſeeing we apply it not to Perſons, but to Witneſſes:</hi> Firſt, then, here you dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from Mr <hi>Tilling.</hi> who ſaith expreſly, <hi>The times of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff, Huſs, the Waldenſes and Albigenſes, could not be any part of this Vial;</hi> and therefore ſtrictly begins at <hi>Luther.</hi> 2. Seeing the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> were to <hi>propheſie in Sackcloth</hi> 1260 <hi>days,</hi> (the whole time of the Beaſt's reign) I ſee no reaſon (according to your opinion) why any of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> ſhould be left out; but to begin the Vials at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the 1260 <hi>dayes,</hi> with the <hi>firſt Witneſſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>fourth Reaſon.</hi> There is (I conceive) conſiderable reaſon to allow more time to the firſt Vial then to the last, for their pouring out; ſeeing firſt, every true <hi>motus eſt velocior in fine.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. This Anſwer is two ways defective. For, 1. The Queſtion is not, Why more time is allowed to the <hi>firſt;</hi> but, Why more to the <hi>firſt,</hi> then to the <hi>ſix other Vials.</hi> 2. Neither is the Queſtion ſimply about the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40449:30"/> time, but why <hi>four</hi> or <hi>five hundred</hi> years are allowed to the firſt Vial, and not <hi>one hundred</hi> to all the reſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the Rule which you bring from a Natural Cauſe, as it proves nothing in things Spiritual and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, ſo it is not rationally true, as you apply it. For ſuppoſe ſeven men ſhoot one after another, (or together) it will not follow, that his Arrow which went out laſt, flies faſter and ſwifter then the firſt. It is true, as every Arrow comes nearer the Centre, ſo the motion may be ſaid to be the ſpeedier. Theſe <hi>ſeven Angels</hi> are diſtinct; they have not one motion: and therefore if any thing may be gathered from that Rule, it is applicable onely to each Vial, as a part and independent.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 2. <hi>Seeing the ſubject of the firſt Vial,</hi> viz. <hi>the</hi> earth, <hi>was ſo univerſal, and took up ſo much ground at that day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> Not to repeat things over and over, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groundedly (in my opinion) the <hi>firſt Vial</hi> is interpreted; I ſay, 1. By <hi>earth,</hi> Rev. 16.2. to underſtand it univerſal, is againſt the Text. True it is, verſ. 1. <hi>earth</hi> there is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal; but as the ſubjects of the other Vials, <hi>viz. ſea, fountains, ſun,</hi> the <hi>Throne of the Beaſt, Euphrates,</hi> are not u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal, but limited: ſo <hi>earth,</hi> Rev. 16.2. is not univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, but reſtrained to a particular ſubject. 2. Be it gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, (though it is not ſo) that the <hi>earth</hi> is univerſal; yet I ſee no reaſon therefore to conclude, that it muſt take up ſo much time, <hi>viz.</hi> three or four hundred years more then the other Vials: eſpecially conſidering, 1. That the <hi>ſubject</hi> of the <hi>firſt Vial</hi> is onely the <hi>groſſer part of Popery,</hi> the leſſer part, and ſo the eaſier and ſooner to be ſmitten. Then 2. The <hi>last Vials</hi> contain the whole affairs of the <hi>Jews;</hi> a thing more univerſal, and for importance far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the firſt, as it is applied.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, to take the earth for the <hi>groſſer part of Popery,</hi> and <hi>univerſal;</hi> ſeeing ſince the firſt Vial began to be
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40449:31"/> poured forth, there are paſt four or five hundred years, and this <hi>earth</hi> notwithſtanding in moſt places yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touch'd; there may be allowed as much time more, (<hi>viz.</hi> four or five hundred years) before by the effects it may prove to be a Vial.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 3. <hi>Seeing the effects of the firſt Vial aroſe in a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent manner from the following, namely,</hi> ex ſe, <hi>as the Greek inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, the ulcers ariſing out of their own bodies, were the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this firſt Vial; whereas the effects of the following Vials, were from others; theirs from within, them from without. Now the ſubſequent Vials muſt needs be with quicker diſpatch then this Vial, becauſe a ſore or ulcer is riſing by degrees to a head or perfection, and ſo takes up a long time; whereas the cutting off with the ſword, and by other hands,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>makes a quicker work and end of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> Not knowing where the ſtrength of this Anſwer lies, it is poſſible I may not hit it. Howſoever,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Though the holy Ghoſt, ſpeaking of the effects of the <hi>firſt Vial,</hi> mentioneth a noyſom and grievous ſore, (or, as the Greek reads, <hi>evil and wicked</hi>) alluding to the <hi>ſixth plague of Egypt,</hi> Exod. 9.10. yet I think this is not to be taken in the letter, but metaphorically; and ſo the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation impertinent and improper. Some indeed expound the ſores to be the <hi>Neapolitan diſeaſe</hi> that came upon the <hi>Beaſts warriors,</hi> Anno 1494. But the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> (I know) doth not take it ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Should I grant the Compariſon, <hi>viz.</hi> between <hi>a ſore riſing by degrees,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and cutting off with the ſword;</hi> yet I do not ſee, that therefore <hi>the ſubſequent Vials muſt needs be with quicker diſpatch then the firſt.</hi> For, 1. My opinion is, that the effects of every Vial, will be <hi>cutting off by the ſword;</hi> and ſo all alike, as to the matter and kinde of plagues; though as to perſons and things, more may be cut off under one Vial, then under another. 2. Neither is the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40449:31"/> always true: for a Plague-ſore may aſſoon diſpatch a man, as the ſword; and without taking up longer time.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 5. <hi>Another Reaſon is, the want of the meaſure of the ſpirit of life in the firſt and ſecond Vials, which is given to them that execute the laſt. Now the more Spirit, the more ſpeed. So that it muſt needs be, that more time is allowed for the pouring out of the firſt, then of the laſt, according as the Spirit from on high, in a more greater meaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. It was a great fault, which is charged on ſome of the Spies, that they brought up an evil report of the Land which they had ſearched, unto the children of <hi>Iſrael, Num.</hi> 13.32. I think there is more here, then is meet, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the <hi>firſt Angels,</hi> as if the work in their hands would go the ſlower and harder on, in not having that meaſure of the Spirit which ſhall be given afterward to others. I am ſure, the Scripture countenanceth no ſuch thing; but they are all alike gifted, ſpirited, and qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the work.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To ſay that <hi>it must needs be,</hi> &amp;c. the Conſequence follows not: for a man may have the Spirit from on high in more and a greater meaſure then another, and yet not finiſh his work aſſoon as he. The <hi>twelve Apoſtles</hi> (and <hi>Paul</hi> too) after Chriſt's aſcenſion, had as much of the Spirit (if not more) then the <hi>Baptist</hi> had; yet more time was allowed them, then to <hi>John.</hi> There needs no Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 6. <hi>And for that God will cut ſhort his work in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 9.28. <hi>which is not meant at the beginning, but at the later end God will do it: ſo that in the last Vials a ſhorter work is to be expected, according to Gods promiſe, then in the firſt; and then it is, that for the elects ſake, the days ſhall be ſhortned. So that in my judgement, there is much reaſon to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low more time to the firſt then to the laſt Vials.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. Under favour, it is more I think then can be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40449:32"/> proved, 1. To ſay poſitively, By God's cutting ſhort his work, is not meant at the beginning. 2. For the Elects ſake, that this muſt be applied to the <hi>laſt Vials,</hi> ſhould a man with the Prophet go into the Sanctuary of God, and humbly enquire in his Temple, I believe he would be taught otherwiſe. As theſe are <hi>the ſeven laſt plagues,</hi> ſo this <hi>cutting ſhort</hi> is meant from the beginning, till the whole myſtery of God be finiſhed: and ſo for the elects ſake, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.14. &amp; 10.6, 7. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.22.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Touching your judgement, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>there is much reaſon to allow more time to the firſt,</hi> &amp;c. beſides what is ſaid, I adde, 1. You have miſs'd the Queſtion, which is (as I ſaid before) Why more to the firſt, then to all the reſt? and why ſo much? 2. Should a man take the like liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he might, for your ſix Reaſons, give out as many more, to prove that more time ought to he allowed to the <hi>laſt Vials</hi> then to the <hi>firſt,</hi> and as much weight and reaſon in them as I finde there.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>Nor do I finde much weight in your alluſion to what</hi> Willet <hi>from</hi> Pererius <hi>aſſerts of the</hi> 27 <hi>or</hi> 30 <hi>days-time, when the ten plagues fell upon</hi> Egypt, <hi>intending a day for a year; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the holy Ghoſt made no mention of it there, of the Vials in Scripture: and ſeeing from the</hi> 1290 <hi>(which I ſuppoſe periods, as Mr</hi> Till. <hi>ſaith, with the</hi> 1260 <hi>days, when you judge the Vials begin) to the year</hi> 1335, <hi>is</hi> 45 <hi>years: and ſeeing it is grounded (in my poor opinion) upon meer preſumption and ſuppoſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It is true, I cited <hi>Willet:</hi> now whether the holy Ghoſt doth intend any thing in it, as to the time of the <hi>Vials,</hi> as I do not affirm it, ſo, for your ſaying it is <hi>grounded upon meer preſumption,</hi> &amp;c. that ſignifies as little. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, this further: Adde to the <hi>thirty days,</hi> the days from the <hi>laſt plague of Egypt,</hi> to their drowning in the <hi>Red-ſea,</hi> (which might be a Type of the <hi>laſt Vial</hi>) I think the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber will amount to yours here, <hi>viz.</hi> 45.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:40449:32"/>2. It is true alſo, that Mr. <hi>Till.</hi> periods the 1290 with 1260: Not to gainſay what he hath ſaid in the thing; here ſome Cautions might be minded: 1. Then the 1290 muſt not be carried to the <hi>ſixth Vial;</hi> for the 1260 peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ods, before that <hi>Vial</hi> begins to be poured out. 2. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt the coming in of the ten Tribes, be underſtood of this Period, (whoſe return in ſpecial I think is meant) <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12. by <hi>the kings of the eaſt,</hi> coming from the Land of <hi>Sinim,</hi> Iſai. 49.12. (which we call <hi>China</hi>) the furtheſt Empire in all the Eaſt. 3. Seeing <hi>blindneſs</hi> is to remain on the Jews, <hi>until the fulneſs of the Gentiles come in,</hi> Rom. 11.25. I conceive the <hi>Beaſt's dominion</hi> muſt be deſtroyed, and the <hi>everlaſting Goſpel</hi> preached, before any thing very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable will appear amongſt the Jewiſh nation. So then, taking the 1290 to end with 1260, it muſt be ſome lowe ſtirring among ſome few of that People, not appearing ſo eminent and glorious as the <hi>riſen Witneſſes</hi> in their work.</p>
               <p>But laſtly, the <hi>Anſwer</hi> is ſhort of the <hi>Reaſon:</hi> for allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>the plagues of Egypt,</hi> I ſaid, <hi>It is probable, when the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als begin, they will be ſuddenly all poured out, as were the ten E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian plagues.</hi> And this <hi>is probable:</hi> for the Scripture ſeems plainly to expreſs as much, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.8, 10, 17.9.21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47.9, 11. But to allow three or four hundred years to the firſt plague upon the Beaſts dominion, before the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond begins; I think it is not <hi>probable,</hi> but as far from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture as from the Alluſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer <hi>to the</hi> fifth Reaſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The characters given to the ſeven Angels,</hi> Rev. 15.2, 3. <hi>of victory over the Beaſt, his Image, Mark,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>all are to be found in all together; but not all together (as I conceive) in one Angel or Generation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. The Text allows no ſuch diſtinction, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the contrary.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:40449:33"/>2. Grant ſuch a <hi>Suppoſition;</hi> then it may be ſuppoſed, that ſome of the <hi>Angels</hi> had <hi>overcome,</hi> others had not: one had the <hi>Beaſts mark,</hi> another had not: ſome <hi>propheſied clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in ſackcloth,</hi> others not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I forbear to mention what ſtrange things might be hence inferred.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>But</hi> 2. <hi>In every generation, according to the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie up againſt the Beaſt, his Worſhip, Image, Mark,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the Angels of the Vials have the victory over him and his matters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. It doth not appear from <hi>Waldo</hi> to <hi>Luther,</hi> (nor yet at this day) that any of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> got victory over the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> whether we conſider their Perſons or their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2, 3. It is true, in the dark times of Popery, ſome (through grace) were kept from commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>fornication</hi> with the <hi>Whore,</hi> (at leaſt, from much of her groſſeſt blaſphemies) but for <hi>victory</hi> they had not, as may eaſily be ſeen, by comparing their times with that text.</p>
               <p>But 2. Taking the word <hi>(overcome)</hi> in a ſenſe, or large acceptation, ſo indeed a Chriſtian holding forth his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt the errours and corruptions of men, though impriſoned, baniſhed, murdered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be ſaid to <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come;</hi> but this muſt be underſtood as to his <hi>witneſs,</hi> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, conſtancie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Not that the Enemy thereby was overcom'd, and put to ſilence, and the errors and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions no more practiſed, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2, 3. intends. Mr. <hi>Tillingh.</hi> on the place, hath theſe words: <hi>The meaning is,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as I conceive, that Saints immediately before the Vials begin to be poured out, ſhall ſo far have gotten the victory over the Beaſt, as concerns either the ſafety of their own perſons, or the doing of their work: Antichriſt ſhall not have power over them, to make them ſubject themſelves to him, allow of his Image, Mark, the Number of his Name, or elſe to perſecute them, or kill them with the ſword, as in former times he hath done: nor ſhall he have ſuch a power, as to hinder them in the work they are about, of pouring out the Vials.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:40449:33"/>
               <p>I think, from this, a man may fairly conclude, that the <hi>Vials</hi> begun not with <hi>Waldo,</hi> nor <hi>Luther,</hi> nor yet are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun. For Saints have not <hi>gotten victory over the Beaſt,</hi> ſo far as concerns their ſafety either of body or ſoul. They have been, from <hi>their days,</hi> hitherto all along, perſecuted and kill'd; and the work they were going about, ſtop'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually. The million of Martyrs ſince <hi>Waldo,</hi> viz. in <hi>France, Germany,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands, Italy, Spain, Bohemia, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c. is proof enough: And therefore, in my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, there is very little reaſon to begin <hi>there,</hi> the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory of the Saints over the Beaſt, where the Beaſt begun his victory and triumph by ſlaughter over the Saints.</p>
               <p>It is worthy of memory, that in the time of the <hi>Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth-Witneſſes,</hi> when the people of God were under cruel perſecution, they made uſe of that Prophecie, (as then proper to them) <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7. <hi>And it was given unto him to make war with the Saints, and to overcome them:</hi> this they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied as an argument of comfort and conſtancie. This being ſo, how that ſhould be the time, wherein Saints had gotten victory over the Beaſt, <hi>as to the ſafety of their own perſons,</hi> &amp;c. and in regard of ſo great deliverance and enlargement, <hi>ſung the ſong of Moſes,</hi> &amp;c. even then when the <hi>Beaſt made war with them, and OVERCAME THEM:</hi> I ſay, How theſe two things can ſtand together, viz. <hi>the Beaſts victory over the Saints,</hi> Rev. 13.7. and the <hi>Saints victory over the Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 15.2, 3. as to be in reſpect of time and perſons all one; truly this, or my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is much out of the way.</p>
               <p>Thus far I agree with that holy man, That before the Vials begin to be poured out, the Lord will ſo fit and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit his <hi>Angels</hi> for the work, as they ſhall go proſperouſly forward: Neither ſhall the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> or any of his <hi>Helpers,</hi> after they begin to be poured out, prevail againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> or his people, in any Nation under the Sun.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:40449:34"/>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>So</hi> 3. <hi>Mr.</hi> Till. Waldo, Groſted, Luther, <hi>were qualified in their ſeveral Ages and Generations, having victory over the Beast, and his Mark, and the number of his Name, (then reigning, and reſisting the truth and faith of Christ) as over Popes, Cardinals, Prelates, Maſs-Priests, Maſſes, Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, the Whores Cup, Pilgrimages, Tranſubſtantiation, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, Superſtitions, and a world of Popiſh traſh, which were rife, and which they witneſſed against in their days: ſo that, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the height and degree of the Testimony and Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, they had the victory over the Beast,</hi> &amp;c: <hi>and held the harps of God in their hands: yea, they were (ſor their Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) the called, faithful, and choſen, the upright hearts, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Lamb, redeemed from men, firſt-fruits to God and the Lamb, that left all for him, denyed themſelves, took up the croſs, and followed him where-ever he went, in the witneſs of their days against the Beast, and overcome him; and ſo (as I humbly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) did ſweetly anſwer the Characters of the holy Ghost: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, had light in their preaching, and ſo (with others) poured out the Vial upon the Beast,</hi> viz. <hi>the earth, or groſs element.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> This being no more (though more words) then what was ſaid before, I ſhall be the briefer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whatſoever was done by <hi>Waldo, Grosted, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. againſt <hi>Popes, Cardinals, Prelates, Priests,</hi> was no other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory then in the ſenſe I nam'd before.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Neither did they finde fault with the Places, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Callings of ſuch men, (though unlawful and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian) but for ſome abuſes and miſcarriages therein. It is well known, that <hi>Armachan, Grosted,</hi> and others, were Prelates, Prieſts, Maſs-Prieſts; and never renounced their Calling.</p>
               <p>So 3. For many of the particulars here ſet down, they bare no Teſtimony againſt them, but allowed and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed a multitude of Ceremonies, Superſtitions, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh traſh.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:40449:34"/>4. To ſay they had <hi>the harps of God in their hands;</hi> here again I am at a loſs. Whilſt the Jews were in <hi>Babylon,</hi> they <hi>hanged their harps upon the willows,</hi> Pſal. 137.2. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, when the Lord turned again the Captivity of <hi>Sion,</hi> then was their mouth filled with laughter, and their tongue with ſinging, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.1, 2. I had thought that the <hi>harps of God</hi> come not into the hands of Saints, till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes:</hi> But by this, it ſeems, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before or after, the times are all one, as to <hi>Victory, Triumph, Singing,</hi> &amp;c. onely in meaſure and degree ſome oddes. Poor encouragement and comfort for ſuch who expect to have all things new!</p>
               <p n="5">5. I think, what is ſaid of <hi>Waldo, Grosted, Luther,</hi> and others, as to be the <hi>called, choſen, and faithful, followers of Lamb, redeemed from men, firſt-fruits to God and to the Lamb,</hi> &amp;c. it is more then their due, if referred to <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.14. and Chap. 14.3, 4, 5. It is ſaid of <hi>Job,</hi> that <hi>he was a perfect man, upright, one that feared God, and eſchewed evil,</hi> Job 1.1. Now howſoever the like may be ſaid of others, and truly too; yet it would be abſurd to ſay, that in that Text they are ſo deſcrib'd. Whatſoever theſe men were in their Generation, (I ſay, to give them their due to the full) none of the <hi>Characters</hi> in <hi>Rev.</hi> 14 &amp; 15. belong to them, <hi>viz.</hi> the matter there, it relates not to them. Beſides, it is a great darkning of the holy Prophecies, and deſtroys all Order, to apply to the laſt times, things paſs'd many hundred years before.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>And yet</hi> 4. <hi>I do not finde a perfection or full anſwer to theſe Characters in every point, as having the full victory and triumph over the Beast till the Armageddon-battel be over, or the ſeventh Vial. So that for theſe and ſome other Reaſons, I think your fifth is of no force.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. Seeing neither <hi>Waldo, Grosted, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. had the Characters, and ſo conſequently were none of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40449:35"/> 
                  <hi>ſeven Angels;</hi> it is nothing to our matter, whether there ſhall be <hi>perfection and full victory,</hi> or not, <hi>till the Armageddon-battel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But 2. To give ſome light here, (according to the light I have received) That which you call <hi>perfection or full vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, as to the Characters,</hi> is to be conſidered two ways. 1. <hi>Particular;</hi> and thus the effects of every Vial ſhall be perfect and full, according to the ſubject; not one Vial to carry on and perfect, what was left by the other unfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. 2. <hi>Univerſal,</hi> that is, when the <hi>last Vial</hi> is pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>all is done,</hi> as <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17.</p>
               <p>It hath been thought, (but whence taken, I know not) the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſecond Vials</hi> not being full and perfect; the <hi>third</hi> and <hi>fourth</hi> falling on the ſubjects of the former, are to finiſh what the other left undone: and this is one great cauſe of mens miſtake about the beginning of the <hi>Vials;</hi> which is neither ſo, nor ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer to the ſixth Reaſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>This ſeems ſomewhat conſiderable, and genuous; yea, at first ſight, to have much force: yet I muſt confeſs, I am not ſatisfied with it. For,</hi> 1. <hi>I think, the Tabernacle of the Testimony is opened gradually, (as the Witneſs or Testimony riſe) out of which the Angels of the Vials go,</hi> Rev. 15. <hi>So that in every generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuch a Tabernacle hath been opened, with the Testimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Beast, in proportion more or leſs, whence the Vials have iſſued: and therefore I must deny the Aſſumption of your Argument, and ſay, The Tabernacle of the Teſtimony was in a degree opened in</hi> Luther's <hi>time, in the</hi> Browniſts <hi>time, and is at this day againſt the Beaſt, in a proportionable purity and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuality of Worſhip, amongſt the remnant of the womans ſeed; and ſo</hi> Wickliff, Huſs, Luther, Zuinglius, the Puritans <hi>(ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led)</hi> Independents, <hi>and others, and now the holy and upright ones, called</hi> The Fifth Monarchy-men, <hi>were in the Tabernacle of the Teſtimony worſhipping, whence the Angels of the Vials come out.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:40449:35"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. If I underſtand any thing of this <hi>Anſwer,</hi> it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies 2 things: 1. The <hi>Teſtimony of the Tabernacle in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> was never ſhut whileſt the <hi>ſack-cloth Witneſſes</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied the 1260 <hi>dayes:</hi> for if <hi>in every generation, ſuch a Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle hath been opened, with the Teſtimony againſt the Beaſt, in proportion more or leſs,</hi> &amp;c. admit it were <hi>gradually;</hi> The Concluſion cannot be denied. 2. That the pouring out of the Vials, hath been ever ſince the <hi>ſack-cloth Witneſſes</hi> began to propheſie, and ſo began with the 1260 <hi>dayes.</hi> Neither is it ſtrange, that ſuch things ſhould paſs; for taking the Vials to begin before the riſing of the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> it cannot be avoided.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now the Reaſon (I conceive) of this miſtake, is, not obſerving (though the Scripture is cleer in it) the diſtinction which the Holy Ghoſt makes between the <hi>Temple</hi> and the <hi>Tabernacle of the Teſtimony.</hi> It is true, the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> and the <hi>Woman in the Wilderneſs,</hi> had a <hi>Temple</hi> to worſhip God in, and an <hi>Altar,</hi> (which is Chriſt) by which to have acceſs to the Father: See <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1. which ſeems to be the ſame, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.6, 14. viz. the <hi>place prepared of God, for their feeding and nouriſhment.</hi> But for the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of the Teſtimony;</hi> that is, the innermoſt part of the Tabernacle, called, the <hi>holy of holieſt,</hi> and the <hi>moſt holy place,</hi> where the 2 <hi>Tables</hi> were put in the <hi>Ark,</hi> Deut. 10.5. 1 King. 8.5. and that <hi>Ark</hi> placed in the innermoſt part of the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> or <hi>Temple,</hi> 1 King. 8.6. Heb. 9.3, 4. that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained <hi>ſhut;</hi> neither could men ſee into it, out of the <hi>Court</hi> or <hi>Temple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But 3. and more plain, the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> is miſtaken, in taking the <hi>Tabernacle of the Teſtimony,</hi> for the <hi>Temple:</hi> for theſe are not only two, and diſtinct in ſound; but as much in ſence and ſignification. What is ſaid in the <hi>Anſwer</hi> of <hi>Lutherans, Browniſts, Independents, Puritans,</hi> &amp;c. it is thus far true, That in every Generation a <hi>Temple</hi> hath
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40449:36"/> been <hi>opened,</hi> that is, ſome good people (more or leſs) ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the abominable Idolatries and Blaſphemies of the <hi>Beast,</hi> have ſeparated from the ſame, according to their preſent Light: and being thus far out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> have joyned together in a more holy Communion. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (as the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſaith very well) this hath been <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually:</hi> for if we conſider this <hi>Temple,</hi> that is, either <hi>Church, Ministery, Worſhip</hi> or <hi>Government,</hi> we ſhall finde it hath been <hi>gradual</hi> indeed, both in eſchewing the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Antichriſt, and practiſing the Truths of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
               <p>But now for the <hi>Tabernacle of the Testimony,</hi> this is another thing within the <hi>Temple,</hi> and ſeldom ſeen, and by the <hi>High-Priest</hi> alone; which I underſtand to be the opening of the Propheſies of the laſt time, as <hi>Daniel and John's Viſions,</hi> ſuch as theſe, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.4, 9, 11, 12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. &amp; 12.6, 14. &amp; 13.13. &amp; 22.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. <hi>It is not for you</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>to know the times or the ſeaſons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.7. Now it is not meant, as if the Queſtion there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the <hi>Apostles,</hi> (namely, <hi>when the Kingdom ſhould be restored again to Iſrael</hi>) was a ſecret never to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed; but it was not then ſeaſonable, nor neceſſary or proper for them (as to their Generation) to have the knowledge of it. So the <hi>Tabernacle of the Testimony</hi> is <hi>ſhut,</hi> whilſt the <hi>Witneſſes propheſie in ſack-cloth,</hi> becauſe the things therein belong not to their Work or Age, yet to be opened neer or about the time of the end, as being then (and not till then) neceſſary and ſeaſonable.</p>
               <p>Neither doth Mr. <hi>Tilling.</hi> in his 3 <hi>Propoſition,</hi> pag. 42. differ from this, ſpeaking, <hi>That God's call to the Angels of the Vials is to be principally looked for, out of the Temple. I underſtand</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>not ſo much of the general call, as a more particular and ſpecial Call, peculiar to this time of the Vials. The general Call to Generation-Work is diſpenſation; but now
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40449:36"/> at this time, (beſides the Call of God's Diſpenſations) the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments God ſhall raiſe up to ruine the Whore, ſhall have a more particular Call to this Work, to the end they may neither flag nor draw back, namely, the loud and unceſſant cry of the Temple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence two things may be gathered: I. The Vials are not began; for ſuch a <hi>particular and ſpecial Call,</hi> hath not been <hi>yet out of the Temple.</hi> It is true, God hath raiſed up ſome men, and brought them forth againſt <hi>Babylon;</hi> as in <hi>France, Germany, England,</hi> &amp;c. But this hath been no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>a General Call:</hi> for 1. They have not moved nor acted like Angels which had <hi>golden girdles upon their breaſts.</hi> Neither 2. hath God's preſence and appearance with them held forth ſuch a thing. Beſides, by the event it hath been well enough ſeen, both in the Work and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, what the <hi>Call</hi> was. So that we need now no other witneſs or proof, <hi>viz.</hi> That neither by the <hi>Swedes</hi> or <hi>Engliſh</hi> any Vials were poured out, then the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. II. That this <hi>particular and ſpecial Call out of the Temple,</hi> cannot be until the <hi>Tabernacle of the Teſtimony</hi> be opened, and the <hi>Ark</hi> ſeen: for what elſe is <hi>God's Call to the Angels of the Vials to pour out their Vials,</hi> but <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Life?</hi> that is, knowing <hi>the</hi> 42 <hi>months</hi> are expired, the <hi>witneſſes riſen;</hi> and that it is the day of the Lord's ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and the yeer of Recompences for the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Sion;</hi> Now as the called of God, they come forth to pour out their <hi>golden Vials:</hi> not like <hi>Jehu,</hi> to raiſe up themſelves by other mens ruine, but to follow the Lord fully and faithfully. And this is according to the Prophet, <hi>I have commanded my ſanctified ones; I have alſo called my mighty ones for mine anger, even them that rejoyce in</hi> MY HIGHNESS, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.3.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 2. <hi>I except against your proof,</hi> Rev. 11.19. <hi>for I do not take that for the Tabernacle of the Teſtimony, as you aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert; but for a full opening of the Temple, in as primitive and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40449:37"/> of ſtate, as the Church was in before the Beaſt aroſe, or in the first</hi> 3 <hi>Centuries, which will not be at the riſing of the</hi> 2 <hi>Witneſſes, nor before the Armageddon-battel: but the Tabernacle is opened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Temple, (as</hi> David<hi>'s Tabernacle was before</hi> Solomon<hi>'s Temple.) Now it is the Tabernacle of the Teſtimony which is opened, and from whence the Vials come; which Tabernacle grows up to the Temple,</hi> Eph. 2.21. <hi>by degrees: but the Temple, when it is opened, is opened all at once, (I conceive) and univerſally (not by degrees) and to all the faithful Saints; whereas the Tabernacle, to the Generation-Saints that are faithful to the Testimony.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. It is no marvel, that taking one thing for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, you may go on thus in miſtakes: 1. To ſuppoſe that <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. is not one with <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.5. there is no ground for it: why is it called, the <hi>Tabernacle of the Testimony,</hi> Numb. 1.5. &amp; 17.17. but in regard of the 2 <hi>Tables</hi> of Stone, whereon was written (as I ſaid before) the Law of God, the Teſtimony of his will, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.28. and theſe <hi>Tables</hi> put into the <hi>Ark,</hi> and that Ark placed in the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt part of the Temple? So that to ſay the <hi>Tabernacle of the Teſtimony was opened and ſeen, and not the Ark,</hi> in my Opinion is no other, than to imagine, what is within a Cheſt or Cloſet may be ſeen, and is open; but the Cheſt or Cloſet it ſelf, neither ſeen nor open. 2. Whereas you would have the <hi>Temple not open, till the Armageddon-battel, but the Tabernacle open</hi> before: If things here be duely weighed, the <hi>Temple</hi> was never ſhut, but onely the <hi>Tabernacle of the Teſtimony:</hi> and therefore what you ſpeak <hi>of opening the Temple all at once univerſally, and not by degrees;</hi> I finde no <hi>Temple</hi> to apply ſuch matter to. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I know any <hi>Tabernacle</hi> David had, otherwiſe than taking care to provide a place for the <hi>Ark,</hi> 2 Sam. 6.17. Pſal. 132.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 3. <hi>This appears more plain from the time this Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is opened, which the Holy Ghoſt tells us in</hi> Rev. 11.19. <hi>is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40449:37"/> after the ſeventh Trumpet ſounds, and Proclamation of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the World to be Christ's,</hi> verſ. 15. <hi>or yet more expreſly under the</hi> 7 <hi>Vial,</hi> Rev. 16.17, 18, 21. <hi>under which we finde the very ſame voyces, thunders, lightnings, Earth-quakes, and hail, mentioned in the aforeſaid</hi> Rev. 11.19. <hi>But the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of the Teſtimony muſt needs be opened before that, as none will deny it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. That <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. contemporizes with <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.5. it is cleer to me; neither do I ſee weight of Reaſon in what is here objected, namely, That <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. <hi>is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the</hi> 7 <hi>trumpet ſounds, and proclamation of the Kingdoms,</hi> &amp;c. If a man have ſeveral things to ſpeak, he muſt have time to deliver them one after another; he cannot ſpeak them all at once. Beſides, it is an excellent order, which the Spirit of God uſeth in ſetting down the Particulars. Having ſpoken of the <hi>riſen Witneſſes,</hi> he ſhews firſt what ſhall be ſome preſent effect, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. then proceeds to the Concomitants, as the beginng of the <hi>third work,</hi> verſ. 14. with the <hi>ſounding of the</hi> 7 <hi>trumpet,</hi> verſ. 15. after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards declares what joy there ſhall be in the Churches of the Saints, that the Kingdoms of the world are falling in to Chriſt, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16, 17, 18. Laſtly, that there might be no doubt made of theſe things, he ſhews how the work ſhall be managed and carried on. <hi>And the temple of God was opened in heaven, and there was ſeen in his temple the ark of his teſtament,</hi> &amp;c. verſ. 19. agreeing to <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.5. meaning a cleer light which the 7 <hi>Angels</hi> ſhall have of their Work, and when to begin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To bring <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. under the 7 <hi>Vial,</hi> I think there is no ground for it, 1. Becauſe there is no mention made under that <hi>Vial,</hi> of the <hi>Ark of the Testament opened in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> ſuch a thing is not ſo much as expreſt. 2. To ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it from <hi>lightnings, voices, thunderings,</hi> &amp;c. in both places; This will not hold: for, 1. Such Expreſſions in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40449:38"/> this Book are frequent, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.5. &amp; 8.5. belonging neither to one time, nor ſignifying one thing. Moreover, for theſe <hi>lightnings, thunders, voices,</hi> &amp;c. they belong to every Vial. Hence in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. they are firſt mentioned, as then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; afterward, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17, 18, 21. as the end: ſignifying, That all the time the <hi>Vials</hi> are pouring out, theſe things will be; as ſhewing thereby both the nature and effect of every <hi>Vial.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, If the 1000 <hi>yeers</hi> take their beginning, (as M. <hi>Till.</hi> ſaith) from the battel of <hi>Armageddon;</hi> how ſhould the <hi>Temple</hi> be opened at that time, ſeeing <hi>John</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>bleſſed new Jeruſalem-State,</hi> ſaith, <hi>and I ſaw no Temple therein?</hi> Rev. 21.22.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 4. <hi>That is yet more amply expreſſed by the holy Ghoſt, that the Vials are begun, before the Temple is opened,</hi> Rev. 11.19. <hi>becauſe when the Witneſſes ariſe, the very ſame hour, verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>is the earthquake, that overthrows the tenth part of the Beaſts dominion, and ſeven thouſand men are ſlain. Now this muſt needs be a Vial or Plague; but this is before the ſeventh Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet blows, or the Temple he opened.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. How I take the order of things in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. I ſhewed before. But I much marvel, why the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſhould be ſo ſtrict, as not to admit ſome things to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporize, becauſe they ſtand three or four verſes diſtant one from another: he knows it is uſual with the <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of this Book, (and himſelf doth it too) to carry places back from Chap. 16. to Chap. 9. &amp; 10, 11, 12, &amp;c. Why then ſo often <hi>it muſt needs be?</hi> as if that in v. 19. may not be joyned with the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes;</hi> and ſo the <hi>third Wo,</hi> and <hi>ſounding of the ſeventh trumpet,</hi> fall in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with the ſame time.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I am of your opinion, that the <hi>earthquake,</hi> in which the <hi>tenth part of the city fell,</hi> is indeed a <hi>Vial:</hi> and truly I think it is meant of the <hi>firſt Vial,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:40449:38"/>1. Becauſe it is preſently upon the <hi>riſing</hi> of the Witneſſes, and ſo no other ſeems to be between it and their <hi>riſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is an <hi>earthquake,</hi> or <hi>ſhaking of the earth;</hi> that is, <hi>earth</hi> is the ſubject of it, the ſame with <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.2. Now howſoever I never finde the word <hi>earth</hi> to be taken for the <hi>groſſer part of Popery,</hi> yet often for worldly and earthly perſons, as Apoſtates, Hypocrites, men of corrupt minds, who make gain their godlineſs, and carry on a ſelf-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and baſe ends, under a form of Religion. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.31. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.16. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.33. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.8. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. and 14, 15, 19. This is that <hi>earth</hi> (I verily think) which <hi>Paul</hi> by the ſpirit of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie foretels: <hi>This know alſo, that in the laſt days perilous times ſhall come. For men ſhall be lovers of their own ſelves, covetous, boaſters, proud, blaſphemers, diſobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy, without natural affection, truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, incontinent, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, traytors, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God, having a form of godlineſs, but denying the power thereof.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. There are <hi>two great Apoſtacies</hi> foretold in Scripture: the firſt, of <hi>things,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.1. the later, of <hi>perſons.</hi> Now this later I take to be the <hi>earth,</hi> the ſubject of the firſt <hi>Vial,</hi> viz. THE GRAND APOSTATES OF THE LAST TIMES. And howſoever there be not in this <hi>ſubject</hi> of the <hi>firſt Vial,</hi> as much <hi>ſea, rivers, fountains of waters,</hi> &amp;c, as in the following; Nevertheleſs, what is wanting here in ſuch particulars, is made up in having the more <hi>earth.</hi> For indeed, it is nothing but <hi>earth;</hi> an earthly and carnal intereſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. My opinion is, where the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> lie <hi>three days and a half</hi> unburied, that place (as <hi>earth</hi>) ſhall be the ſubject of the <hi>firſt Vial.</hi> Now it is well obſerved by judicious <hi>Mede,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the City (which in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. is tranſlated <hi>ſtreet) cannot be underſtood of a Market-place, or
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40449:39"/> any ſtreet or broader place within the walls of the city; but without the city, as no part of the great citie:</hi> and he gives many Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for it. So that it ſeems to me, the place where the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> lie ſlain being without the city, and ſo no part of it, cannot be meant of <hi>Germany, Italy, Spain, France,</hi> &amp;c. for theſe are either buildings or ſtreets within the walls, but this is without, as bordering upon it; being an inlet or thorow-fare, whereby relief and proviſion is brought to the <hi>great Citie,</hi> and a great helper and prop of the <hi>Beaſt</hi>'s dominion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I cannot but take notice, how it is ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13. <hi>The tenth part of the citie fell:</hi> it is not ſaid, <hi>The great citie:</hi> Now I do not finde in all that Book, when the <hi>Beaſt's juriſdiction</hi> is mentioned by City, but it is always <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>that great citie:</hi> which makes me think, that the Tyranny and Idolatry of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> is not here ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly meant, as that <hi>earth-State-apoſtacie,</hi> mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And in very deed, the word GREAT here, is not left out without cauſe, as not worthy to have GREATNESS given to it, Becauſe, 1. It will be <hi>illegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate,</hi> brought forth without law or conſcience. 2. It will have nothing of lovelineſs or beauty in it. 3. Not deſired, but by a few <hi>temporizers</hi> and <hi>turn-coats,</hi> ſuch as were nam'd before, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5. 4. It will be ſcandalous to the whole world, and cauſe that glorious and fearful Name, <hi>Jehovah,</hi> thy God, everywhere to be blaſphemed. 5. It will be upheld by cruelty, injuſtice, arbitrary power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 6. As it will have a ſandy foundation, ſo it ſhall ſoon fall; and great will be the fall thereof.</p>
               <p n="5">5. I think this <hi>earth-State-apoſtacie</hi> will be the ſubject of the firſt Vial, becauſe the <hi>Beaſt which aſcendeth out of the bottomleſs pit,</hi> and by whom the Teſtimony of Jeſus in his ſervants is ſlain, is that ſame Apoſtacie in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo not the <hi>Beaſt nor his image,</hi> Rev. 13. but ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40449:39"/> diſtinct, and more proper to the <hi>later Apostacy.</hi> In the <hi>firſt Apoſtacy,</hi> viz. under the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13. the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſhall ſuffer in their Perſons, by burning, hanging, drowning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but under the <hi>later Apoſtacy</hi> or <hi>Beaſt,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the WITNESS it ſelf, than the Perſons: for through the depths of Satan, there ſhall be at this time ſuch an eminent, high, and glorious WITNESS ſlain, as the like before had not been from the riſe of the <hi>firſt Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, it ſeems to me, that this <hi>Earth-State-Apoſtacy,</hi> doth contemporize <hi>with the ſlaying of the Witneſſes,</hi> and their <hi>lying unburied</hi> 3 <hi>dayes and an half:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe that Apoſtacy is to be in the <hi>laſt days,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.1. Now without doubt, the <hi>laſt days</hi> are the 3 <hi>days and an half,</hi> Rev. 11.8.11. for the Word of God doth not onely diſtinguiſh between times and times, (<hi>viz.</hi> as there is a ſet time to every purpoſe under heaven) but ſhews that all Viſions and Propheſies ſhall have their due accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their appointments. Thus there is a time for the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> to propheſie in ſackcloth, which time muſt be expired before they are ſlain in their Teſtimony. Again, their WITNESS being ſlain, they muſt lie ſo long unbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. To be brief, This <hi>later Apoſtacy</hi> cannot be referred to the 2 <hi>Witneſſes propheſying in ſackcloth;</hi> for that was not the <hi>laſt days,</hi> nor after their riſing; for then this firſt Vial is to be poured upon that <hi>Earth,</hi> as the Subject of it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of neceſſity (neither before nor after) it muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporize with the 3 <hi>days and an half:</hi> ſo that <hi>three yeers and an half</hi> is the whole time of the <hi>later Apoſtacy,</hi> anſwerable to the time of the ſlain WITNESS.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas it is ſaid, <hi>perillous times ſhall come,</hi> or <hi>hard, terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, grievous,</hi> or <hi>difficult:</hi> this muſt be underſtood of a <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Government,</hi> not of ſingle perſons, who have no Rule or Authority in their hands. But as the firſt <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> or
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40449:40"/> 
                  <hi>Beaſt,</hi> was a <hi>State, Kingdom, Dominion;</hi> ſo is the other.</p>
               <p>My Reaſons are, 1. To apply the place to ſingle and inconſiderable perſons, (though <hi>lovers of themſelves, covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, proud,</hi> &amp;c.) this were no more than what hath been in all Ages before, and ſo to put ſomething impertinent and abſurd upon the Holy Spirit. Neither 2. would the time be <hi>terrible;</hi> for what hurt or damage could the WITNESS ſuffer by a few naked and unarmed perſons, as to the <hi>ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of it?</p>
               <p>It muſt therefore (to be <hi>terrible</hi>) be underſtood, as I ſaid, of a <hi>State-Apoſtacy;</hi> and ſo indeed it will be terrible and hard againſt the <hi>Witneſs,</hi> ſlay it outright, and let it lie like a dead body in the ſtreet.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe of a multitude of Sycophants and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſites, who for their belly will ſay any thing againſt the WITNESS, having ſuch <hi>Earth</hi> to reward them for it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Terrible</hi> and <hi>hard,</hi> becauſe of the cruel E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts and Laws made againſt the WITNESS; ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it may have no Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, this <hi>later Apoſtacy</hi> for ſubtilty and craft will exceed the former: ſo, that there ſhall be neither truſt nor truth in it. <hi>This will be found</hi> (<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir</hi> Henry Vane <hi>meditat. c.</hi> 23. <hi>p.</hi> 380.</note> ſaith a late writer) <hi>by experience, a moſt certain truth, that Hypocrites and Apoſtates, when once they come to wilful ſinning, and with</hi> Saul <hi>to diſcern that</hi> God hath left them, and is departed from them <hi>(as to what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine preſence and fruits of it they had before been made ſenſible of) none will be more ready to joyn avowedly with the Devil, and the worſt of his Inſtruments to accompliſh their rage againſt the ſuffering Saints of Chriſt.</hi> Hence <hi>the Beaſt is ſaid to aſcend out of the bottomleſs pit,</hi> Rev. 11.17. Therefore <hi>terrible</hi> to the VVITNESS.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, The more <hi>perillous,</hi> becauſe the <hi>grand Apoſtacy of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40449:40"/> the laſt times</hi> ſhall be clothed over with a <hi>form of godlineſs,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.5. Hence the <hi>Beaſt</hi> having ſlain the VVIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESS, in Churches and Church-Officers, by Promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Honour, great Places, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he will make uſe of theſe Perſons to ſlay <hi>It</hi> in others: I ſay, By their Mouths, Pens, Examples, to murder It out-right in all places.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To open the words a little further: <hi>And the tenth part of the citie fell, and in the earthquake were ſlain of men ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thouſand; and the remnant were affrighted, and gave glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the God of heaven,</hi> Rev. 11.13. There are <hi>four effects</hi> of this Vial.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It reacheth to the carnal Church, Miniſtery, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Government, as being part of the <hi>Apoſtacie,</hi> and which joyned with the <hi>Beaſt</hi> in ſlaying the WITNESS. This is ſet down in the word TENTH, wherein the holy Ghoſt cloſely intimates, how the riſe of this <hi>earth-apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> ſo far as the Clergy are concerned in it, and ſhould be carried forth with madneſs (not zeal, like <hi>Paul</hi> when he was a Perſecutor) to ſlay the WITNESS, both in themſelves and others, It would be for the TENTH: for otherwiſe they would not nave made ſhipwrack of Faith, and a good Conſcience, in betraying ſo glorious a <hi>Cauſe,</hi> to ſet up THAT SHAME.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid, The <hi>tenth fell;</hi> in Scripture ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſual, <hi>falling</hi> is taken for <hi>ſlain,</hi> ſo the Word ſignifieth in <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.10. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 8.24, 25. <hi>Judg.</hi> 8.10. and many other places: in <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.15. it is ſaid <hi>there fell of Iſrael;</hi> for which in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.15. it is written <hi>there died.</hi> And pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, as this TENTH will be a main cauſe of ſlaying the VVITNESS: ſo when the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> ſhall ſtand upon their Feet, ſome eminent death will be executed upon it. <hi>We to him that coveteth an evil covetouſneſs to his houſe,</hi> Hab. 2.9. <hi>Behold thine end is come, and the meaſure of thy covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> Jer. 51.13.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:40449:41"/>2. It is ſaid, <hi>in the Earth-quake was ſlain names of men, ſeven thouſand;</hi> that is, Men of note, renown, famous, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.4. contrary hereto, is, <hi>men without name,</hi> Job. 30.8. It ſeems to allude to the Rebellion of <hi>Corah, Dathan, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biram, with certain of the children of Iſrael,</hi> 250 <hi>Princes of the Congregation, the called of the Aſſembly, men of Name,</hi> Numb. 16.2. VVorthy <hi>Ainſworth</hi> here noteth, that <hi>theſe were States-Men,</hi> famous and renowned; whereby the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy was the ſtronger. But what became of theſe <hi>men of name?</hi> they were <hi>ſlain by an Earth-quake,</hi> Numb. 16.32, 33. Here may be meant Souldiers and Lawyers, as Prieſts before.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>And the Remnant were affrighted,</hi> &amp;c. we do not finde the like effect of any Vial after: no giving glory to the God of Heaven; but blaſpheming the God of Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.9, 11, 21. The Reaſon may be, becauſe the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Vial is <hi>Earth,</hi> that is, <hi>a meer Earthly and carnal Intereſt,</hi> and ſo no part of the Beaſt's Dominion; I mean, not ſo properly and directly as are the Subjects of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Vials. Hence this <hi>Earth-Apoſtacy</hi> is not obeyed for Love and Conſcience, but either of fear, or for ſome worldly advantage: and therefore no marvel there will be a Remnant (howſoever with it before) ſeeing it ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in the <hi>Earth-quake,</hi> ſhall bleſs God for it, and ſay, <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> Salvation, and Glory, and Honor, and Power unto the Lord our God.</p>
               <p>The laſt Effect is in <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.2. <hi>And there fell a noyſome and grievous ſore upon the men which had the Mark of the Beaſt, and upon them which worſhipped his Image.</hi> Here it is to be obſerved, that theſe have the <hi>Mark of the Beaſt,</hi> and ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the <hi>Remnant</hi> before. The Effects of this Vial extends further then the Subject.</p>
               <p>And therefore whereas it is ſaid, <hi>The firſt Vial falls upon ſuch as had the Mark of the Beaſt, and worſhipped his Image;</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:40449:41"/> This is true, if we underſtand the Effects; otherwiſe, the Subject is onely <hi>Earth,</hi> viz. the <hi>grand Apoſtacy of the laſt times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As they that dwelt upon the Earth rejoyced, and made merry, when they ſaw the VVITNESS <hi>ſtain,</hi> being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid it would have reach'd them, (as doubtleſs it would, had not that <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> been) ſo now they are much more tormented to hear the ſame VVITNESS is riſen again, and hath poured a <hi>Vial</hi> upon that <hi>Earth</hi> or <hi>Beaſt,</hi> by whom it was ſlain. The <hi>Canaanites,</hi> when they heard what the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had done unto the two Kings of the <hi>Amorites</hi> that were on the other ſide <hi>Jordan, Sihon</hi> and <hi>Og,</hi> whom they utterly deſtroyed; aſſoon as they had heard theſe things, their hearts did melt: neither did there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main any more courage in any man, becauſe of <hi>Iſrael, Joſh.</hi> 2.10, 11. Such will be the effect of the firſt <hi>Vial:</hi> when <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall hear by <hi>thoſe poſtes, Jer.</hi> 51.31. what the Lord by his riſen VVitneſſes hath done upon <hi>THAT EARTH,</hi> the other ſide <hi>Jordan;</hi> O what a noiſome and grievous ſore will be upon the <hi>Canaanites!</hi> their hearts will die within them, as fore-ſeeing their deſtruction, in ſeeing the drawn Sword of <hi>Jehovah</hi> in the hands of his Mighty Ones.</p>
               <p>Thus I have given a ſhort <hi>Paraphraſe</hi> of the <hi>firſt Vial</hi> (it is indeed but ſhort, to what might be ſaid) onely I have done it to ſhew, that taking the <hi>Vials</hi> not yet begun, but to begin at the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes,</hi> there is (in my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) more <hi>Scripture-Ground</hi> for it, than to begin at <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Armachan,</hi> &amp;c. or by <hi>Earth</hi> to underſtand the <hi>groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer part of Popery.</hi> But this I leave to the judicious and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reader.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 5. <hi>Laſtly, Should I grant (which I do not) what you ſay, yet out of one and the ſame Temple, all the Angels go. 3 al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not ſo opened to the firſt, as to the laſt. Now whereas you
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40449:42"/> apprehend not a ſufficient ground to ſay the laſt Vials are more perfect, high, or accompliſhing than the firſt; I ſuppoſe there is, ſeeing the holy Ghoſt hath given ſuch a Character of perfection to the laſt,</hi> Rev. 16.17, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>as he hath not given to the firſt. And beſides, it muſt needs be, that as the ſpirit of life comes down from on high more and more, the inſtruments will be purer and purer. And beſides, he is not always the beſt, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageth the firſt, for the engagement may be greateſt and the work hardeſt at laſt; and then the Lord reſerves inſtruments of more excellent principles, and proportionable Faith and courage, as I believe he hath for the Armageddon-battle, and to bring up the rear under the ſeventh Vial. So far for your ſixth Reaſon, which I have been the larger in, becauſe I did take it for one of the Weightieſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. As the difference lies betwixt us, the matter is not much, whether the <hi>Tabernacle of the Teſtimony be not opened to the firſt, as to the last;</hi> ſeeing, till after the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes,</hi> it is not opened at all, and ſo no <hi>Vial</hi> poured out by any of the <hi>Angels.</hi> This was the thing which I aſſerted, and finde nothing in the whole <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the contrary.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the <hi>Characters of perfection,</hi> &amp;c. if there be any thing meant by the holy Ghoſt, in the word (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) to prove it, You ſee more than I; for to me it is no more, than if <hi>ſeven men,</hi> having done <hi>ſeven</hi> ſeveral things one after another, the laſt, (knowing they have all done) ſaith, <hi>They have done.</hi> How this can prove the laſt to be a better inſtrument then the firſt, I know not.</p>
               <p>I confeſs, ſome take the laſt <hi>Angel</hi> to be <hi>Chriſt:</hi> now in this ſenſe it is true, he is more perfect and high, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than the firſt; yea, than all the other ſix, put them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Although, (as I ſaid before) we are here off from the matter, <hi>viz.</hi> that the <hi>Inſtruments of the laſt Vials ſhall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40449:42"/> have more excellent principles, and proportionable Faith, and courage,</hi> &amp;c. yet for the thing it ſelf I queſtion: It is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to overcome a diſmaid Enemy, and broken in his Forces, than when he is in heart, and whole. The <hi>first Vial</hi> (I conceive) ſhall be poured out upon the <hi>Earth,</hi> when <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall ſay in her heart, <hi>I fit a Queen, and am no Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow,</hi> Rev. 18.7. the following <hi>Vials</hi> upon <hi>her,</hi> as being full of fear, terror and amazement; ſo that the work ſeeme to be hardeſt at firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer <hi>to the</hi> ſeventh Reaſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſhall not need to ſay much to this: for not only we have it out of Cardinals and Papiſts mouths, as to the firſt Vial; and ſo as to the Swedes under the ſecond: but now as to the third Vial in the ende wars in Britain (to which indeed it properly appertains) the very Enemies, as well as Friends, have ſaid, True and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are thy judgements, O God, againſt the King, Prelates; yea, the very Cavaliers and Malignants, acknowledging, That the hand of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was againſt them; and that it could be no other than the finger of the Lord: and in time (as the plagues go out) it will appear without diſpute, on whoſe ſide the truth is, to ſuch as will ſee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. That the <hi>three firſt Vials</hi> are thus placed, I never yet ſaw ground for it. To forbear the <hi>firſt,</hi> (having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken of it) why ſhould the <hi>ſecond Vial</hi> be applied to the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and not rather to the <hi>Civil Wars in France,</hi> or <hi>Bohemia,</hi> or to the long Wars of the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> againſt the Papiſts? Sure I am, there was as much of God (if not more) ſeen in theſe wars; and his <hi>judgements</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> manifeſt, as in the <hi>Swedes.</hi> So for the <hi>third Vial,</hi> which <hi>properly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertains</hi> (you ſay) <hi>to Britain:</hi> and why not to <hi>Scotland</hi> in their <hi>Maries</hi> Reign? or, to the <hi>Netherlands?</hi> ſeeing as much was done there in point of Reformation, as here in <hi>England.</hi> Methinks to take in the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and leave out others more conſiderable, ſignificant, and <hi>Vial-like,</hi> (in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40449:43"/> your own way) is not well. But ſome may ſay, There are not <hi>Vials</hi> enough to give ſuch allowance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For <hi>Cardinals, Prelates, Cavilliers,</hi> &amp;c. we have had little yet out of their mouthes. It may be, ſome few, now and then (as it hath been ſo, ſince there were ſuch men) have acknowledged Gods appearing againſt them in ſome remarkable providence. But how? as a <hi>Vial</hi> of wrath? No; but as the Corrections of a Father, making uſe of bad men (as <hi>Roundheads, Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries,</hi> &amp;c.) as his Rod or Inſtruments: hoping, for all this, to recover their loſſes, and to have their former Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Superſtition reſtored. So that <hi>Gods judgements have not been manifeſt,</hi> as to the conviction of enemies: n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> was there more acknowledged amongſt them of God finger, under the two ſuppoſed <hi>Vials,</hi> then what hath been often at other times. And therefore from ſuch a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, I do not ſee but every Fight or Battel muſt be one of the <hi>ſeven laſt Plagues;</hi> I mean, when a few amongſt the Captives and Priſoners ſhall acknowledge that the hand of the Lord was out againſt them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And laſtly, For the place, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.4. <hi>For thy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are manifeſt;</hi> It doth not concern ſo much the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Truth, what they confeſs, as how <hi>manifeſt Gods judgements</hi> are in themſelves. Howſoever therefore ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was manifeſted in the <hi>Swedes</hi> and in <hi>Britain</hi> againſt the Beaſt, (as at other times as much) yet this doth not prove that the <hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>third Vials</hi> were then poured out. I deny that: for when ſuch Plagues ſhall come forth, <hi>Gods judgements then will be manifeſt indeed. Great and marvelous are thy works, Lord God Almighty: juſt and true are thy ways, thou King of Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the <hi>ſeven Vials</hi> allude to the <hi>plagues of Egypt,</hi> it is granted by all. Now howſoever without doubt, whilſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> abode in <hi>Egypt,</hi> God ſmote the <hi>Egyptians</hi> with
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40449:43"/> many plagues, yet none were ſo <hi>manifest,</hi> as the <hi>ten last.</hi> It is my opinion, (and methinks the Scripture is clear for it) that there will be as great difference between <hi>Gods judgements</hi> already executed upon the <hi>Beast,</hi> and what ſhall be made manifeſt when the <hi>Vials</hi> begin to be poured out, as between the twinkling of a Star, and the ſhining Sun at noon-day. As that which lies loweſt at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Cask, are the dregs: ſo the <hi>ſeven last plagues</hi> are the deepeſt, greateſt, and heavieſt, all dregs, wrath without mixture, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.8, 10, 15, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.9, 10, 15, 19, 20. &amp; 14.19, 20. &amp; 34.8, 9, 10. &amp; 63.1, 2, &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.25, 26, &amp;c. &amp; 51. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.7, 8, 9. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 75.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.8, 10.</p>
               <p>Here were a fit occaſion for me to deliver my ſenſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>third Vials;</hi> which the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently carries to the <hi>Swedes</hi> and <hi>Engliſh.</hi> But becauſe I deſire firſt to know what ſatisfaction Gods people have, by this which I have publiſhed in differing from the common received opinion, I ſhall not treat thereof at this time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer <hi>to the</hi> eighth Reaſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>At the first glance, this out of</hi> Rev. 15.6. <hi>may go for very good, till it be well weighed; and then we ſhall ſee,</hi> 1. <hi>That the Witneſſes, during their Sackcloth or ſuffering eſtate, have power to ſmite with plagues,</hi> Rev. 11.6. <hi>or Vials,</hi> Chap. 15.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. I have (I think) ſaid enough, in making it evident and clear, that the <hi>Sackcloth-Witneſſes,</hi> and <hi>Angel-Vials,</hi> are diſtinct both to their works and times; and therefore I ſhall not reply ſtill onely to words. <hi>Herod</hi> holding the opinion of <hi>Pythagoras, Plato,</hi> and other Heathen men, that the ſouls of the dead come again in other bodies, could not but think, (believing that <hi>John Baptist</hi> was riſen) but that great wonders would be done by him now, though <hi>John</hi> in his life-time wrought no miracle. If the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, in their <hi>Sackcloth</hi> and ſuffering eſtate were the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:40449:44"/> Rev. 15. that is, had <hi>gotten the victory over the Beast,</hi> had the <hi>harps of God, ſung the ſong of Moſes,</hi> had <hi>the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of the Testimony opened to them, poured out Vials,</hi> &amp;c. I ſee very little what their <hi>Reſurrection-ſtate</hi> will ſignifie or amount to. The Nations need not (if the caſe be ſo) to be frighted, (as <hi>Herod</hi> was) when they ſhall hear they are ſtanding upon their feet. See <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 2. <hi>By</hi> white, <hi>is not always meant a Change of ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but by</hi> white <hi>(I conceive) is meant uprightneſs, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, truth, integrity: and ſo,</hi> Rev. 19.8. <hi>for the fine linen, is the righteouſneſs of Saints, or the Generation-righteouſneſs, which is as the holy Ghost ſaith,</hi> Rev. 15.6. <hi>the ſeven Angels come out clothed with pure and white linen; by which I think may be meant the Generation-righteouſneſs, purity, and ſanctity: and ſo the two Witneſſes may have the ſackcloth for ſuffering, and white robes for uprightneſs, innocencie and truth too: what ſhould hinder? And ſo the</hi> Waldenſes, Lollards, Huſſites, Lutherans, <hi>&amp;c. in their Generation, were clothed in white.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. Were it true, (as you ſay) <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>white</hi> is not always meant a <hi>change of rayment,</hi> that is, of <hi>condition</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> yet it may be meant ſo, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.6. and I think both you and others, obſerving well the place, will not take it otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>But 2. Grant farther, by <hi>white ſometimes is meant up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs, innocencie,</hi> &amp;c. why in the very ſame place may not <hi>change of State be meant</hi> likewiſe? I do believe, let the Scriptures be ſearch'd, never is <hi>pure and white linen</hi> given to Saints, but a <hi>change of State</hi> is always meant, whatever is meant beſides.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.8. it is to be underſtood of the Jews preparing as a <hi>Bride</hi> adorned for her husband, which is by caſting off her own righteouſneſs which is by the Law, and no other then <hi>filthy rags,</hi> Iſa. 64.6. to put on the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, which is of God by faith. <hi>A most glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous change of State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:40449:44"/>4. For <hi>Generation-righteouſneſs, innocencie,</hi> &amp;c. attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Waldenſes, Lollards,</hi> &amp;c. whatſoever they had of theſe graces; all Saints before them (and ſince) have had the like. Conſidering therefore, that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. nothing is ſet down, but things high, eminent, ſingular; I much marvel the place ſhould be brought ſo lowe; as if nothing were there meant, but what is ordinary and common to every Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, That the <hi>two Witneſſes</hi> ſhould have <hi>ſackcloth for ſuffering,</hi> and <hi>white robes for righteouſneſs;</hi> here I think Mr. <hi>Tilling.</hi> ſays better, who underſtands <hi>ſincerity, uprightneſs and integrity</hi> to be meant by the <hi>golden girdles upon their brests;</hi> according to <hi>Paul, Having your loyns girt about with truth,</hi> Eph. 6.14.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 3. <hi>The word here,</hi> Rev. 15.6. <hi>which is</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>is not the word that is uſed for change of rayment, but ſignifies a plain, eaſie, ſoft, cotton-whiteneſs; which may well be worn with ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth: but the change of rayment is rather</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a brave ſilken whiteneſs, or Princely Robe,</hi> Ezek. 16.13. <hi>and ſo in the places you name, as</hi> Gen. 41.42. Eſth. 8.15. <hi>therefore it is not here meant ſuch a change of Robe as cannot be received till the Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth is put off.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> It is true (as you ſay) the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> but for the explanation and application, I like neither of them. Firſt, not the <hi>Explanation;</hi> as if the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould ſignifie onely ſome <hi>plain and courſe cloth:</hi> whereas rather, it is <hi>fine flax,</hi> (as the <hi>Greek</hi> tranſlateth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.9.) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the Eaſt they made their richeſt and choiceſt linen.</p>
               <p>Nor 2. the <hi>Application:</hi> for the holy Ghoſt (who knew beſt his own meaning) beſides <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is not onely <hi>bright and reſplendent,</hi> but <hi>gorgeous, Prince-like,</hi> ſuch as was worn by Kings and Nobles. Hence <hi>Godwyn</hi> well obſerves, that <hi>Purple, above other colours, was affected
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40449:45"/> by the Emperours and Nobility of Rome, and White by the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Jews: whence the Hebrews termed their Noble-men</hi> Chorim, albatos, <hi>men clad in white: On the contrary, men of mean rank,</hi> Chaſchucim, <hi>men clad with foul garment,</hi> Jam. 2.2. <hi>Pilat his ſouldiers clad Christ in purple,</hi> Matth. 27.28. <hi>and Herod the Tetrarch of Galilee put on him</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>white garments,</hi> Luke 23.11. <hi>both therein applying themſelves to the cuſtoms of their own Countries, clothing him as King, though in deriſion.</hi> Moſes and Aaron, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Beſides, in <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.2, 3. the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is taken for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, quite differing to <hi>a plain, eaſie, ſoft cotton, which may be worn with ſackcloth,</hi> &amp;c. So that (I conceive) if any weight lie in the words, it is not in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>cloth,</hi> but in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (the <hi>colour</hi> or <hi>kinde</hi>) which is <hi>gorgeous, Royal, Prince-like linen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>But</hi> 4. <hi>Were it meant of ſuch a Robe, yet thoſe (fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned) brave Champions of Christ, in their generation, might be ſaid to be clothed therewith by faith, whilst they tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled, and had the generation-victory over the Beast, (as we ſaid before) being above him, and beating him before them, by a most noble and notable ſpirit of faith, courage, and undaunted reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that would not yeeld an inch unto him; and ſo were (as it were) Princes, (in ſpirit) and above ſufferings. But ſo far for your eighth Reaſon, which I take for the most conſiderable and ſerious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. I have ſeen what is extant concerning the perſons (ſpecially <hi>Grosthead</hi> and <hi>Armachan</hi>) ſo often men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; but am not of your opinion, that they were ſuch <hi>brave Champions, as trampling the Beast, and beating him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them,</hi> &amp;c. I do not judge their <hi>Generation-work</hi> amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſo much.</p>
               <p>Neither, 2. <hi>had they any victory over the Beast,</hi> as <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2. For that place intends more then <hi>Generation-victory, viz.</hi> by ſpeaking or writing againſt the errours and evils
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40449:45"/> of men, or beating the adverſary in ſuch a kinde: it is an execution of temporal judgements; which they never did, and therefore could not be the <hi>Angel of the first Vial.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But 3. Should it be granted they were ſuch <hi>brave Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, had generation-victory,</hi> &amp;c. all this might be, and yet not <hi>clothed in Prince-like white,</hi> becauſe <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.6. is to be underſtood of the time after the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes,</hi> whereas they were before.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, taking the Grounds and Principles of ſome men to be true, I do not ſee, why the <hi>fourth and fifth Vials</hi> ſhould not be poured out, as are the firſt, ſecond and third. For in my opinion, there hath been as much of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> poured out upon the <hi>ſun, and throne of the Beaſt,</hi> as upon the <hi>earth, ſea, and fountains of waters:</hi> I ſay, as much as can be ſaid of the other three: And therefore I ſee no reaſon why there is a ſtand at the <hi>third Vial;</hi> and why no <hi>Vial</hi> poured out upon the <hi>houſe of Auſtria,</hi> or <hi>Germane Emperor;</hi> yea, and why not upon <hi>Rome it ſelf.</hi> If there be no more to make up the effects of a Vial, <hi>in trampling and beating the Beast, and to have Generation-victory over him,</hi> then a bare Teſtimony againſt his Idolatries and Blaſphemies. Beſides, more Reaſons, (I think) and better too, may be given, that in the <hi>Swethen and Britain Wars,</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>throne of the Beast</hi> were ſmitten, then either <hi>Sea,</hi> or <hi>fountain of waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there is no <hi>Anſwer</hi> made to the ninth Reaſon, the <hi>Reaſon</hi> is, becauſe that Argument was not ſent with the reſt to my friend. Beſides, there are ſome paſſages added to the Reaſons as they are printed, which were not in the Copie ſent to the <hi>Anſwerer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer <hi>to the</hi> tenth Reaſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nor can I ſee, as you ſuppoſe, an abſurdity in aſſerting the Vials begun, and the effects of them, (as we have ſaid) ſeeing
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40449:46"/> one Vial perfects another, as the following doth the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl. If any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the Oracles of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.11. For my part, I had rather obſerve how things are expreſſed in the Scriptures, then the liberty which men take in their Expoſition. That <hi>one Vial ſhall perfect another,</hi> &amp;c. I am ſure this is not in the text; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be gathered from it, as I conceive. When the <hi>firſt Vial</hi> hath been poured out upon the <hi>earth,</hi> where is it ſaid that the <hi>ſecond, third, fourth,</hi> &amp;c. ſhall follow, to <hi>perfect the work upon that ſubject?</hi> or what Reaſon is there for ſuch an inference?</p>
               <p>Some, in opening theſe <hi>Vials,</hi> allude to <hi>waters;</hi> when one ſtream falls into another, and theſe two into a third; here is no running backward: for though the waters are increas'd, yet their courſe is ſtill forward. It is true, the <hi>firſt Vial</hi> having perfected its work, (as going forward) may fall in with the <hi>ſecond;</hi> and ſo theſe <hi>two,</hi> (the effects of the <hi>ſecond</hi> being perfected) with the <hi>third:</hi> but that the <hi>ſecond</hi> or <hi>third</hi> ſhall run backward; as the ſimilitude taken from waters, is againſt humane reaſon, ſo this againſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truth, in my underſtanding. Now upon this miſtake it is, that many good men ground their opinion, that the <hi>Vials</hi> begun to be poured out by <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. as taking it for granted, that <hi>one Vial perfects another, as the following doth the foregoing:</hi> But the Word of God juſtifies no ſuch opinion; neither ſhall the <hi>earth,</hi> as the <hi>ſubject of the firſt Vial,</hi> have any other poured out upon it; neither is it to be thought needful, no more then when perſons or things are once deſtroyed, to ſay they muſt be put down again by others after.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Tilling.</hi> his <hi>fifth Propoſition</hi> is, <hi>That the effects of one Vial do oft-times run into another Vial.</hi> I anſwer: The effects of each Vial, are the <hi>evils</hi> or <hi>ſufferings</hi> themſelves which
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40449:46"/> lie upon the enemies of God, and their works, by reaſon of the wrath of God formerly poured out; as <hi>ſores, blood, ſcorching men with heat, darkneſs,</hi> &amp;c. Now how ſuch evils or ſufferings do run one into another, I underſtand not. He ſaith, <hi>My meaning is, the immediate following Vial, or the Vial following that, may ſometimes be poured out, before the effects of the fore-going Vial are wholly ceaſed.</hi> This I grant: As for example, Before the <hi>effects</hi> of the <hi>firſt Vial</hi> (whoſe <hi>ſubject</hi> is the <hi>earth</hi>) are ceaſed, the <hi>ſecond Vial</hi> may begin to be pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out upon the <hi>ſea:</hi> So the third Vial <hi>upon the rivers and fountains of waters,</hi> before the effects of the ſecond are over. But hence it will not follow, That the <hi>ſecond Vial,</hi> whoſe proper ſubject is the <hi>ſea,</hi> ſhall fall upon the <hi>earth;</hi> or the fourth, whoſe <hi>ſubject</hi> is the <hi>ſun,</hi> upon the third, <hi>viz. the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and fountains of waters,</hi> as <hi>one Vial to perfect another:</hi> This is onely ſuppoſed, and the holy Ghoſt ſeems to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it quite otherwiſe: for he diſtinguiſheth both the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, Subjects, and effects;</hi> and puts them all a part. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, to take it in the other way, <hi>viz. one Vial perfecting ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> here is meer confuſion: Here <hi>earth</hi> is no more the <hi>ſubject</hi> of the <hi>firſt Vial,</hi> then of the <hi>ſecond;</hi> nor <hi>ſea</hi> the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of the <hi>ſecond Vial,</hi> more then of the <hi>third</hi> or <hi>fourth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. 2. <hi>Seeing the two Witneſſes have power to ſmite with the plagues,</hi> Rev. 11.5. <hi>before their ſlaughter, yet have not power to end any of the Beaſts dominion in any one ſtreet, till after their riſe,</hi> verſ. 13. <hi>becauſe till then, the ſpirit of life which does ſo, comes not into them; and till then, the end of the</hi> 42 <hi>months, or Beaſts period, is not ended; and therefore it is, that their plagues in the</hi> 42 <hi>months are more defective, and at the end of the</hi> 42 <hi>months more perfective: for until then, they could plague, but not period the Beaſts Government in any ſtreet; ſo that no wonder if the Beaſts Tyranny be ſtill up in one kinde or other, till the end comes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> Here are ſtill ſuppoſitions one after another.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40449:47"/> 1. <hi>One Vial perfects another.</hi> 2. <hi>The ſackcloth-Witneſſes are the Angels,</hi> Rev. 15.3. <hi>Before their ſlaughter, defective; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, more perfective,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe being onely Conjectures, without proof, I ſhall ſay the leſs.</p>
               <p>But 1. If <hi>Groſthead, Armachan, Huſs,</hi> &amp;c. were ſuch <hi>brave Champions,</hi> and had all thoſe <hi>Characters,</hi> Rev. 15.2, 3, 4, 5, 6. and Chap. 14.2, 3, 4. I cannot ſee how they were without the <hi>ſpirit of life,</hi> Chap. 11.11. Neither ſo <hi>defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive:</hi> for, in my opinion, the <hi>ſpirit of life</hi> is no other, then what in Chap. 15 &amp; 16 is expreſſed in particulars.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To ſay, <hi>The Witneſſes could plague, but not period;</hi> it is as much as to ſay, They were not the <hi>Angels,</hi> Rev. 15. For every <hi>Vial</hi> ſhall <hi>period;</hi> neither doth the laſt <hi>period</hi> more or further then its proper ſubject.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If you mean, by <hi>end,</hi> the <hi>last Vial,</hi> (as I perceive you do, by what follows) therein I differ: for the <hi>Beast</hi>'s <hi>dominion</hi> ſhall end with the <hi>fifth Vial.</hi> And howſoever there ſhall be a <hi>party at the Armageddon-battel,</hi> gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for the cauſe and intereſt of the Beaſt; yet as to his <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>power</hi> that was broken before, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. We know whoſe <hi>Houſe and Family</hi> is caſt out of this <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> yet there are ſome (had they oportunity) would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly engage to raiſe it up again out of the aſhes. So here.</p>
               <p>I know the <hi>Beast</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> Rev. 16.13. &amp; 19.20. is taken for one: by <hi>Beast,</hi> the Civil power; by <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> the Eccleſiaſtical. But I think, in both places, by the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> is meant <hi>Mahumet,</hi> that is, the <hi>Turkiſh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion or State:</hi> 1. Becauſe it is not probable, that ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a matter ſhould be left out; which muſt be, if it be not here. 2. In both places, where the <hi>falſe Prophet</hi> is mentioned, the things properly belong to the <hi>Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> and fall under the <hi>last Vials,</hi> viz. the great Army of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> God's judgments upon them, and <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40449:47"/> victory, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38 &amp; 39. 3. Neither doth the title, <hi>That falſe Prophet,</hi> belong ſo fitly to any, as <hi>to that monſter Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi> Hence, ſince his riſing, he hath been uſually ſo call'd. 4. Whereas the working of miracles in <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. is referr'd (not to the <hi>Beast,</hi> but) to the <hi>falſe Prophet;</hi> this much ſtrengthens (methinks) the <hi>ſenſe.</hi> For at this time, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans greateſt workings will be among the <hi>Turks,</hi> with all power, and ſignes, and lying wonders. As a Tyrant, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt ſeveral ſtrong holds, he ſeeks to maintain, by what ſupply he hath, ſuch other Forts and Caſtles as yet are in his hands: ſo Satan, being driven out of his <hi>Weſtern hold,</hi> and nothing left him, in a manner, but the <hi>falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets dominion:</hi> here he will be working all the Miracles and lying Wonders he can, to draw multitudes to him. And howſoever <hi>Babylon</hi> be fallen, yet the <hi>Beast</hi> is ſaid to be with the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> becauſe of a party joyning then with the <hi>Turks,</hi> to raiſe up the ruines of the <hi>Great citie,</hi> or the <hi>Beasts dominion</hi> again.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 3. <hi>Sure it is from an abſurdity, becauſe the holy Ghoſt gives not that note of perfection, till the laſt,</hi> Rev. 16.17. <hi>and then he ſaith, It is finiſhed: and therefore the laſt muſt needs make perfect all the other, in all ſtreets and nations, and put a full period to all Tyranny and Idolatry: which we cannot ſay of the firſt. Beſides, the laſt Vial is the moſt univerſal and thorow alſo. Now the Reaſon why the four laſt Vials make a more thorow work then the three firſt, I gave before; becauſe the end of the Beaſts dominion is now come, which was not in the former.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. I think the Abſurdity (if any be) remains ſtill, for any thing is ſaid to the contrary. It was objected, that <hi>when all the Vials are poured out, nothing may be ſignified, &amp;c.</hi> To which we have this Anſwer: <hi>The holy Ghoſt at the laſt (and not before) ſaith, It is finiſhed.</hi> Now what is <hi>finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> but the work and effect of each <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Vial?</hi> That is, as the <hi>firſt Angel,</hi> in witneſſing againſt Idolatry and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40449:48"/> Tyranny, poured out his Vial, and therein (as a brave Champion) did his duty, howbeit Tyranny and Idolatry continued ſtill: ſo the reſt, one after another: And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus <hi>trampled upon the Beaſt, and beat him before them, as the firſt did;</hi> a voice at laſt ſhall be heard, <hi>It is done.</hi> And may not all this be, and yet <hi>earth, ſea, ſun,</hi> &amp;c. remain ſtill?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Methinks it is ſtrangely gathered, <hi>Becauſe the holy Ghoſt ſaith, It is finiſhed; therefore the laſt muſt needs make perfect all the other,</hi> &amp;c. One Scholar may anſwer for the reſt, that they have <hi>all done their Parts or Exerciſes,</hi> and yet it is poſſible every one might perfect his own work.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In granting that the <hi>end of the Beaſts dominion was not come in the three firſt Vials,</hi> you muſt needs grant, (if I am not extremely miſtaken) that no <hi>Vials</hi> are yet poured out. For, as the end of the <hi>Beasts dominion</hi> is not till after the <hi>fourty and two months;</hi> ſo the <hi>last plagues</hi> begin not till then: he is not <hi>grown full enough for the Vials,</hi> (to uſe your own words) till thoſe <hi>months</hi> be expired.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>eleventh Reaſon.</hi> I do not underſtand how you make it an argument againſt the pouring out of any of the Vials to be now; <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in ſo full purity, is not opened till after all the Vials; although the Tabernacle of the Teſtimony, <hi>Rev. 15.5.</hi> Now until it be opened, <hi>Rev. 11.19.</hi> no man is able to enter into it, <hi>Rev. 15.8.</hi> till the ſeven plagues of the ſeven Angels be fulfilled; which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be after the ſeven Vials, <hi>Rev. 16.17, 18.</hi> So that it hinders not but that the Vials may be begun.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> I have ſhewed before, how I think the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> is in a double miſtake about <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.5. &amp; 11.19. Firſt, in taking them apart, as if the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> Chap. 15. ſhould be opened before the <hi>Vials</hi> are poured out; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>viz.</hi> Chap. 11. <hi>not till afterward:</hi> whereas both pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces belong to one matter and time. 2. He takes that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40449:48"/> for the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> which I take to be the <hi>Temple,</hi> Rev. 11.1. Whilſt the <hi>two Witneſſes</hi> propheſied in <hi>ſackcloth,</hi> they had a <hi>Temple:</hi> but the <hi>Teſtimony of the Tabernacle</hi> is not to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened till after their <hi>riſing.</hi> Beſides, if Chriſt <hi>perſonally</hi> ſhall appear between the <hi>ſixth and ſeventh Vial,</hi> Rev. 16.15. and the <hi>thouſand years</hi> take their beginning immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon the <hi>Armageddon-battel;</hi> we muſt riſe higher for light, then to take it from the <hi>Temple</hi> or <hi>Tabernacle.</hi> And ſo much ſeems to be ſignified, by that Angel ſtanding in the ſun, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.17. wherein will be fulfilled that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.25, 26. <hi>And there ſhall be upon every high mountain, and upon every high hill, rivers and ſtreams of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in the day of the great ſlaughter, when the towers fall. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the light of the moon ſhall be as the light of the ſun, and the light of the ſun ſhall be ſevenfold,</hi> &amp;c. Though a man where he ſtands may ſee very much, yet being ſet up higher, as on a hill or mountain, (ſuppoſe as high as the ſun) he ſees a great deal more then he did before. True it is, no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er are the <hi>Witneſſes riſen,</hi> but <hi>the earth is enlightned,</hi> Rev. 18.1. by the <hi>Ark of the Teſtament,</hi> Rev. 11.19. <hi>and the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of the Teſtimony opened in heaven,</hi> Chap. 11.5. But when the <hi>Sun of righteouſneſs ſhall ariſe with healing in his wings,</hi> Mal. 4.2. Saints then ſhall be higher then <hi>Temple</hi> or <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> Rev. 21.22. for their light ſhall be <hi>ſeven times</hi> more then before, as being rais'd to a higher pitch and degree of light and knowledge, then either the <hi>Prophets</hi> or <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 2. <hi>He ſaith, No man ſhall be able to enter in; but he doth not ſay,</hi> No man ſhall be able to go out. <hi>And in this he alludeth to</hi> Solomons Temple, <hi>wherein the Prieſts could not enter,</hi> 2 Chron. 7.2. <hi>they could not go in, but thoſe who were in could go out,</hi> 1 King. 7.10, 11. <hi>being ſo filled with the preſence and glory of the Lord, that they went out. So here, the Angels of the Vials ſhall go out, being ſo filled with the preſence, ſpirit, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40449:49"/> glory of the Lord, that they will not be able to abide in. Though none go in, yet he ſaith not, None go out. So that I cannot ſee how this hinders, but the Vials may be begun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> I think you have laid down a very good Ground, by your diſtinction, to prove that the <hi>Vials</hi> are not begun. For, 1. If thoſe in the <hi>Temple</hi> muſt be <hi>filled with ſuch a preſence, ſpirit, and glory of the Lord, before they go out;</hi> I am ſtrongly perſwaded, that neither <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Armachan, &amp;c.</hi> were any of the <hi>Angels;</hi> nor the <hi>Swediſh</hi> or <hi>Britain Souldiers;</hi> nor yet is the <hi>Temple filled with ſuch a preſence.</hi> It is one thing to be in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and another thing to have it <hi>filled with this glory</hi> you ſpeak of. For ſuch a time will not be, neither is it to be expected, till the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian darkneſs be more expell'd.</p>
               <p>Should a man now make enquiry amongſt the choiceſt Saints concerning <hi>Temple-preſence,</hi> I know what they would ſay, (and not without cauſe) <hi>we have not the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of men, clouds and darkneſs are about us, we want the preſence and ſpirit of God; there is a death, darkneſs and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſpread over all things, as, worſhip, ordinances, Scriptures, &amp;c.</hi> Nevertheleſs, ſure I am, there is as much now of <hi>the preſence and ſpirit of God</hi> with his people, as any of thoſe ever had, who are ſaid to be the <hi>Angels of the firſt Vials.</hi> So then, if there be <hi>no coming out, until the Temple is filled with the preſence, ſpirit and glory of the Lord;</hi> we may conclude, Either none are come out; or if any are, they had not the preſence and Spirit of God; which the holy Ghoſt expreſſeth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As <hi>none are to come out of the Temple, until filled with the Spirit;</hi> ſo not <hi>until they are call'd,</hi> Rev. 16.1. The which <hi>Call,</hi> I do not take to be in <hi>following Providence;</hi> but more then ordinary, as the Prophets and Apoſtles were, by ſome immediate impulſe of ſpirit; the Lord making them now clearly to ſee, that their work and time is come: As
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40449:49"/> I have ſaid before, <hi>A particular and ſpecial call, peculiar to this time of the Vials,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Tilling.</hi> ſaith, which hitherto no man had.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 3. <hi>Whereas he ſaith,</hi> No man; <hi>we must obſerve the ſubject: he doth not ſay,</hi> No Angel; <hi>but,</hi> No man; <hi>which is a different dialect of the holy Ghost, and doubtleſs means ſome other, and not them that execute the Vials; for they are called Angels: and indeed, I think it refers to a more inferiour ſubject; and therefore cannot hinder, but that the Vials which are poured out by Angels (are more glorious inſtruments then common men) may begin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. You have given me occaſion to declare my thoughts of the place. It is true, (as you ſay) <hi>he ſaith not No Angel, but No man;</hi> ſignifying thereby, when the <hi>Vial-time</hi> begins, what a moſt glorious <hi>Reformation</hi> there will be both of <hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>things:</hi> For ſuch ſhall be the light, judgement, zeal, and conſcience of Saints, as <hi>no man</hi> ſhall be admitted into the <hi>Temple:</hi> no carnal and formal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, no corrupt Hypocrites; no ſuch Apoſtates as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4. Now that ſhall be verified: <hi>Holineſs becometh thy houſe, Jehovah, to length of days,</hi> Pſal. 93.5. Hitherto (eſpecially ſince the great Apoſtacie) the vile with the precious have been in the <hi>Temple: Whilst men ſlept, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my came and ſowed tares among the wheat,</hi> Matth. 13.25. What through ignorance, partiality, covetouſneſs, ſelf-love, <hi>MAN</hi> hath entred into the Temple, moſt unworthy perſons have been taken into Church-fellowſhip: but now, <hi>no man is able,</hi> &amp;c. it is ſo <hi>filled with ſmoak from the glory of the Lord, and from his power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then, the meaning is, upon <hi>the riſing of the Witneſſes,</hi> the Church draws to <hi>primitive perfection</hi> both for <hi>light and life.</hi> As the <hi>Tabernacle of the testimony ſhall be opened,</hi> that is, large diſcoveries of Goſpel-myſteries: ſo the <hi>Temple ſhall be ſhut,</hi> as no entrance for <hi>man:</hi> none <hi>but Angels ſhall
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40449:50"/> go in and out.</hi> And though I am not of your opinion, that <hi>this refers to the bleſſed Jeruſalem-eſtate of the thouſand years;</hi> yet it is a fore-runner, and carries the character and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that glorious time. Hence in part will be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.8. &amp; 48.2. <hi>Joel</hi> 3.17. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.1, 2. &amp; 24.3, 4. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 60.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. &amp; 22.15. Compare 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Are ye not carnal, and walk</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>according to man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now whereas Mr. <hi>Tilling.</hi> opinion is, That Saints, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Vials</hi> begin, <hi>ſhall not attain to that purity the Church of Christ enjoyed before the corruptions of Antichrist crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it;</hi> I think otherwiſe; and the Scripture which he quotes, <hi>viz. Rev.</hi> 4.6. in my opinion is againſt him. <hi>For then</hi> (ſaith he, ſpeaking of the Primitive time) <hi>there was a ſea of glaſs clear as cryſtal: here is a ſea of glaſs, but not yet ſo clear as cryſtal.</hi> There is more in <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2. then <hi>a ſea of glaſs:</hi> for it is added, <hi>mingled with fire.</hi> Now the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why theſe words, <hi>mingled with fire,</hi> are left out in Chap. 4.6. it is, becauſe of the purity which the Church then was in, (as to Doctrine and Diſcipline) before the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie of Antichriſt; and ſo <hi>the ſea of glaſs needed no ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with fire.</hi> But the impure and filthy droſs of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt being crept into the Church, then indeed there was cauſe to have the <hi>ſea of glaſs mingled with fire,</hi> whereby to conſume and burn up not onely the <hi>groſſer part of Popery, or the lees and dregs of that Religion;</hi> but the whole, great and ſmall: as the fire leaves no droſs or impurity in ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver refin'd. So then, whereas <hi>the ſea of glaſs</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>mingled with fire,</hi> it is not to denote (as I conceive) any <hi>ſtrugling of the Saints with the Beast, nor hot jars and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions among themſelves;</hi> but, that all the corrupt and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten devices of the Beaſt ſhould be (as droſs in a furnace) utterly conſumed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>Till the ſeven plagues of the ſeven Angels
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40449:50"/> were fulfilled.</hi> Then <hi>Man,</hi> afterward, is able to enter into the Temple.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, The particular <hi>until</hi> is often taken for <hi>never, Gen.</hi> 8.7. &amp; 28.15. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.25. So here.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For your ſenſe of the place, (if I underſtand it) it makes a difference between Saints, as ſome <hi>ſuperiour,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>inferiour.</hi> But I think all Saints, (ſo judged and known) as <hi>Angels,</hi> ſhall enter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Neither will there be any ſuch difference amongſt the people of God after the <hi>Vials</hi> begin.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>And</hi> 4. No man <hi>as then without the Temple: yet</hi> 5. <hi>I think it refers to the bleſſed New-Jeruſalem-ſtate of</hi> 1000 <hi>years,</hi> Rev. 20, 21, &amp; 22. <hi>which is not begun till after the ſeven plagues; and therefore till then, none can enter into it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. Doubtleſs many who are <hi>without,</hi> when the <hi>Temple</hi> is firſt filled with the glory of the Lord, ſhall yet <hi>enter in,</hi> before the Vials are poured out. For the <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Goſpel</hi> is to be preach'd, upon the <hi>riſing of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> whereby many will be called out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and other Gentiles from their idols and vanities, to the faith and obedience of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For referring it to the <hi>New-Jeruſalem-ſtate,</hi> it ſeems to have no footing in the text: for the holy Ghoſt ſpeaks there of no <hi>New Temple</hi> or <hi>State;</hi> but directly of that <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> in which the <hi>ſeven Angels</hi> then were.</p>
               <p>Beſides, in my opinion, ſo to take it, it's far below the ſtile of the holy Ghoſt. For, to ſay, <hi>The new-Jeruſalem-ſtate will not begin till after the ſeuen plagues;</hi> it's a truth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: but how? As if a traveller were told that his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyings muſt be finiſhed, before he can be at home; or a Souldier, till the enemy be ſubdued, he is not to have the glory and honour of the Victory.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 6. <hi>Should we concede to your Argument, the edge
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40449:51"/> thereof would turn as much againſt your own opinion and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion; ſeeing none could enter in, as you grant, till the Temple were opened,</hi> Rev. 11.19. <hi>which is after the ſeventh Trumpet hath ſounded. The Scripture you quote,</hi> Rev. 15.5. <hi>being meant of the Tabernacle of the Teſtimony, whence the Vials go out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; but not out of this Temple, which is not opened till after all the ſeven plagues of the ſeven Angels be fulfilled, as that text expreſſeth</hi> in terminis.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. How the <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſhould be againſt my ſelf, I ſee not. Indeed my opinion is, that both places, (as I ſaid before) relate to one time, and take their beginning before the <hi>Vials:</hi> Neither is there any mention of <hi>a Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle or Temple opened in heaven,</hi> after the Vials are poured out; though you ſay that text <hi>expreſſeth it in terminis.</hi> For <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17, 18. (which you often quote) ſpeaks no ſuch thing, but that <hi>there came a great voice out of the Temple of heaven:</hi> not ſaid <hi>to be then opened,</hi> (as <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. &amp; 15.5.) becauſe it was not opened at that time, but long before.</p>
               <p>But 2. This is true, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. <hi>heaven is ſaid to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened;</hi> which I take to be between the ſixth and ſeventh Vials, ſignifying a moſt glorious ſucceſs of the <hi>everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Goſpel;</hi> partly through the light which came from the <hi>Ark,</hi> Rev. 11.19. and the <hi>Tabernacle of the Testimony,</hi> chap. 15.5. opened before; and partly through the <hi>fall of the Weſtern Babylon,</hi> Chap. 18.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>So that neither by this, nor any of your former Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, is my faith in the Vials begun, ſtirr'd or enervated; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ratified for the preſent, without I ſee more then I do: and am of Mr.</hi> Tilling. <hi>opinion, that the Vials are begun; and that for theſe Reaſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> I know it was Mr. <hi>Tilling.</hi> opinion: ſo <hi>Brightman</hi>'s, <hi>Pareus, Mede,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">Burton, Cotton.</note> many others which I have ſeen: and it is (I think) the opinion of moſt men ſtill, whoſe learning and godlineſs I do willingly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40449:51"/> and do honour the very name of ſome of them; yet neither do I think them ſo learned, but they might erre; nor ſo godly, as in all things to be followed. This reverence every man ſtands bound to give to the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God in other men, That in his difference from them, he be not ſuddenly or eaſily perſwaded; but being jealous of his own heart, he undertake the examination of things, and ſo proceed with fear and trembling; and ſo having <hi>tryed all things, hold fast that which is good,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.21. ſo ſhall he neither wrong the graces of God in himſelf nor in others. But on the other ſide, for a man ſo far to ſuffer his thoughts to be conjur'd into the Circle of any mortal man, or mans judgement, as either to fear to weigh what is offered to the contrary in the balance of the Sanctuary; or finding it to bear weight, to fear to give ſentence on the Lords ſide; yea, though it be againſt the <hi>common opinion of good men:</hi> this is to honour man above God, and to advance a throne above the throne of Chriſt, who is Lord and King for ever.</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs, to the glory of God, and mine own ſhame, that one <hi>Reaſon</hi> why I queſtioned not till of late, but that the <hi>Vials were begun,</hi> it was, becauſe I found ſuch an unanimous accord amongſt Expoſitors therein. Hence I made the leſs ſearch into the thing, there being no doubt made (among them) as to the truth of it. Now it is poſſible, my caſe here may be the caſe of other men.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 1. <hi>Becauſe the two Witneſſes in their Sackcloth-condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the time of the</hi> 42 <hi>months, before their ſlaughter or riſe, pour out plagues, or ſmite with plagues,</hi> Rev. 11.5, 6. <hi>But the Vials are ſuch plagues,</hi> Rev. 15. <hi>Therefore, they pour out Vials.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Becauſe the very ſame ſubjects of the Witneſſes ſmiting with plagues,</hi> Rev. 11.5, 6. <hi>are the ſubjects of the Angels Vials,</hi> Rev. 16.1, 2, 3. <hi>viz. earth, waters turned into blood, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40449:52"/> expreſſed by the holy Ghost in the very ſame phraſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> We have <hi>anſwered</hi> this before: yet farther, thus: The places have no ſuch full agreement as is pretended. For, 1. in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. <hi>waters</hi> there, are before <hi>earth:</hi> but in Chap. 16. there <hi>earth</hi> is before the <hi>waters.</hi> Neither do I think, but, according to the order ſet down, the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> did ſo, <hi>viz. ſmote the waters</hi> firſt in <hi>the days of their prophecie,</hi> prophetically.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>ſea,</hi> which is the <hi>ſubject</hi> of the <hi>ſecond Vial,</hi> Rev. 16.3. in Chap. 11. is not ſo much as named; which is very ſtrange, that the <hi>ſecond Vial</hi> ſhould be thus left, and yet all one thing, and <hi>in the very ſame phraſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. How do they agree in <hi>phraſes?</hi> When the one onely <hi>ſmites the earth,</hi> the other <hi>pours out a Vial on the earth.</hi> Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, here lies a great difference, not ſo much in words, as matter, if well conſidered.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In Chap. 16.4. <hi>the Angel poured out his Vial upon the waters, and they became blood:</hi> but Chap. 11. the <hi>Witneſſes have power over the waters, to turn them into blood.</hi> It is not ſaid they <hi>ſmote the waters,</hi> or that the <hi>waters were turned into blood.</hi> What may be gathered, is one thing; but the <hi>phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> are not alike.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If the places are ſo alike in <hi>phraſes,</hi> why are they made ſo unlike in expoſition? The <hi>first Vial</hi> is applied to <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Luther,</hi> as <hi>ſmiting the Beast</hi> with their mouthes and pens: the <hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>third,</hi> to Souldiers and Armies, and ſo killing men with their ſwords and guns.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 3. <hi>Becauſe the Egyptian plagues alluded to, were begun by the two Witneſſes</hi> Moſes &amp; Aaron, <hi>before the end of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity or ſojourning in Egypt: and it is very evident, this hath ſuch an alluſion,</hi> Rev. 11.8. <hi>becauſe the holy Ghost calls this fourty and two months Egypt alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> If the <hi>Egyptian plagues</hi> by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> (the <hi>two Witneſſes) were all poured out before the end of the captivity;</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:40449:52"/> then following the <hi>Alluſion,</hi> all the <hi>Vials</hi> ſhould be poured out whilſt the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> are in <hi>ſackcloth.</hi> And to ſaythe truth, to take it otherwiſe, it deſtroys the life and light of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. For if the <hi>Vials</hi> begun before the <hi>riſing of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> then muſt they be all poured out before the end of the <hi>fourty and two months,</hi> as the <hi>ten plagues by the two Witneſſes Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> were before the end of their Captivity or ſojourning in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee, by dividing the <hi>Vials,</hi> as ſome to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>riſing,</hi> and ſome after, is contrary to the <hi>Alluſion.</hi> For if ſome were, then were all: but taking it that none were, ſo there is (in my opinion) both reaſon and truth as to the <hi>Alluſion; viz.</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> the <hi>two riſen Witneſſes</hi> (not in <hi>ſackcloth</hi>) neer or about the end of the <hi>four hundred and thirty years,</hi> plagued the <hi>Egyptians:</hi> ſo the <hi>forty and two months</hi> of the <hi>Beasts tyranny</hi> being going out, the Spirit of life from God ſhall enter into his <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> for the pouring out of the <hi>last plagues</hi> upon the <hi>Beasts domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. 4. <hi>For that the remnant (I humbly conceive) are to ſtrike in, and not to begin; to ſucceed and follow, not to direct and lead; to execute, not to prepare: but your opinion makes</hi> 144000, <hi>or the remnant, to begin; and the two Witneſſes to fall in with them: which I ſee not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> Either you or I are here in ſome miſtake, both to the <hi>Remnant</hi> and <hi>Witneſſes.</hi> For, 1. I do not take the <hi>Remnant</hi> (as you do) to be the <hi>one hundred fourty and four thouſand;</hi> but (as I ſaid before) part of the <hi>womans ſeed,</hi> which never <hi>fled into the wilderneſs;</hi> againſt whom the <hi>dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon makes war,</hi> Rev. 12.17. and this, before the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes;</hi> and ſo, in likelihood, refers to the wars in <hi>France, Holland, Germany, Britain,</hi> &amp;c. 2. I take the <hi>one hundred fourty and four thouſand,</hi> and the <hi>riſen Witneſſes,</hi> to be all one. For, (as you ſaid well) <hi>it is a testimony or Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40449:53"/> (not perſons) that is ſlain;</hi> the which <hi>Testimony</hi> or <hi>Truth</hi> (that is, the glorious Cauſe and Intereſt of Chriſt) riſeth and lives again, by a ſpirit of life from God entered into the one hundred fourty and four thouſand.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 5. <hi>For that all the hitherto-plagues upon the Beasts dominion, do ſignifie nothing, if they were not the matter of the Vials.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. The concluſion will not follow. For whilſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were in <hi>Egypt,</hi> no doubt the Lord plagued the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians</hi> at ſeveral times; yet they were none of the <hi>ten last plagues.</hi> To come nearer; when <hi>Abbeys</hi> and <hi>Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi> were put down in <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. his Reign, this was a <hi>plague upon the Beasts dominion,</hi> and ſignified ſomething. So hath he been plagued in <hi>France, Scotland, Bohemia,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> yet reckoned no <hi>Vials.</hi> Beſides, what did the <hi>Goths, Hunnes, Vandals,</hi> &amp;c. but pour out plagues up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Beasts dominion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That they are ſaid to be <hi>the last plagues,</hi> it clearly ſhews, that there were <hi>plagues</hi> upon the <hi>Beasts dominion</hi> before. For the diſtinction between <hi>former</hi> and <hi>later,</hi> muſt be underſtood of the <hi>Beasts dominion</hi> as the <hi>ſubject:</hi> that is, ſeveral plagues ſhould be poured upon it, before the <hi>ſeven last Plagues or Vials</hi> begin.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 6. <hi>And lastly, the ſubjects of the Vials,</hi> Rev. 16.2, 3, 4, 5, &amp;c. <hi>of the first, the ſecond, and the third, as the holy Ghost in Scripture opens them, have been under the very ſame wrath mentioned in the firſt, ſecond, and third Vials: ſo that I am much perſwaded that they are begun, by a Scripture-clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> That which firſt gave me occaſion to queſtion the <hi>beginning of the Vials,</hi> it was, that I could not ſee nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>ſubjects</hi> nor the <hi>effects</hi> of the Vials, <hi>as the holy Ghost opens them,</hi> Rev. 16. <hi>under the ſame wrath,</hi> as they are inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted; neither the <hi>firſt, ſecond,</hi> nor <hi>third:</hi> there being
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40449:53"/> nothing yet done, in my opinion, that carries the chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of <hi>VIAL-WORK</hi> upon it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the <hi>earth</hi> ſhould be taken for the <hi>groſſer part of Popery,</hi> where do we finde in Scripture a ground to raiſe ſuch an Expoſition? 2. That the <hi>ſubject earth</hi> ſhould be <hi>univerſal,</hi> and yet in many places this <hi>groſs earth</hi> never mov'd, but to this day remains as much and as bad as ever. 3. That <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Armachan,</hi> &amp;c. ſhould be <hi>Vial-Angels,</hi> a thing no way ſutable to the deſcription of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>So again, for the <hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>third Vials,</hi> I am not ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as they are applied. <hi>Firſt,</hi> why the <hi>ſecond,</hi> to the <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh war in Germany;</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> to ours in <hi>Britain.</hi> Or, 2. (as others) why the <hi>ſecond</hi> to the <hi>Romiſh diſcipline</hi> or <hi>Hierarchy in England,</hi> Anno Dom. 1641. the <hi>third,</hi> to fall upon <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and <hi>France:</hi> I do not ſee <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-clearneſs</hi> for theſe things. Nor 3. do I underſtand what difference there is between the <hi>earth and ſea,</hi> as they are expounded: for I think the <hi>Romiſh Hierarchy,</hi> viz. <hi>Popes, Cardinals, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Monks, Friers,</hi> &amp;c. with all that rabble, root and branch, as <hi>groſs earthly ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions,</hi> as their Maſs, their Croſſes, Purgatory, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Pilgrimage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore, to make a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction between <hi>Romiſh doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Romiſh diſcipline,</hi> as two diſtinct ſubjects, I am not of that opinion: but as they roſe together, ſo they ſhall fall together, inſeparably, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one and the ſame Vial. I confeſs, in things to come, as they are ſecret, ſo we cannot well judge whether men hit or miſs (in their opinions) till they come to paſs: But in things that are paſt, and ſo viſible, here we can ſay a little more, whether men ſpeak pertinently, and to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:40449:54"/>
               <p>I thought to have forborn the <hi>Queries:</hi> but not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how it might be taken, I have ſet down the <hi>Anſwers</hi> to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answers">
               <head>A few words to your <hi>Queries.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the firſt,</hi> I anſwer: The one of the <hi>living creatures, (for I like not the name of Beasts; nor is it</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>but</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Rev. 15.7. &amp; 4.6. Living creatures, <hi>or</hi> Cherubims, <hi>as</hi> Ezek. 1.5.) <hi>Now this</hi> one <hi>I will not ſay, as ſome do think, to ſignifie the</hi> firſt (<hi>which is the</hi> Lion) <hi>in this place; though in ſome places it doth,</hi> Dan. 10.13. Mar. 16.2. <hi>eſpecially when we ſpeak in order of number, with others,</hi> as Rev. 6.1. <hi>But ſo it is not</hi> in Rev. 15.7. <hi>Wherefore here I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incline to the last; as</hi> Rev. 21.9. <hi>there came one of the ſeven Angels, is meant the last of the ſeven: ſo here,</hi> one of the living creatures, <hi>I do believe is meant the last of the</hi> four animals: <hi>and ſo the holy Ghost ſignifies, by bringing up all with</hi> ONE, <hi>or the</hi> ONE, <hi>as the ſum, or utmoſt, or concluding number of</hi> all. <hi>Beſides this, it agrees very well with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription: for the laſt is the</hi> flying Eagle, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.7. <hi>who gave (I conceive) the Vials to the ſeven Angels,</hi> for theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>For that it is a bird of a moſt excellent ſpirit; and the meaning is, That moſt excellent ſpirits muſt manage all thoſe Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als; and the Angels under this</hi> Eagle-adminiſtration <hi>from the Throne, will be full of ſagacity, quick ſent, and apprehenſion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>See</hi> Job 39.27, 29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then</hi> 2. <hi>for that the Eagle is ſwift, and ſo the most ſutable of all the four living creatures, to give the Vials, for the ſwiftneſs of his diſpenſations in the Vial-days, eſpecially when the two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>For that he is ſo full of courage, that he fears not to ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the</hi> Great Beaſt; <hi>and ſo will the executors of the Vials fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40449:54"/> the Greateſt of the earth, yea the great Beaſt whom the earth hath worſhipped, feared and adored.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>For that the way of the Eagle is a ſtrong and unknown way,</hi> Prov. 30.19. <hi>and ſo the moſt ſutable to give out the Vials, which will be executed in ſtrange and unknown ways, or untrod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den paths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>For that he will flie full to the ſun, with eyes open; and goes out to his prey at noon-day: and ſo will the Vials be openly in the ſight of the ſun; and thoſe that pour them out, will be open-eyed, and move in the full light of the work, with their faces to Jeſus Chriſt, and eying the ſun of righteouſneſs,</hi> Mal. 4.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>He is called, the</hi> flying Eagle: <hi>for he hath his neſt on high in the rock; and ſoaring ſo, he falls from on high right down upon his prey: And ſo will this Vial-work fall from above, upon the heads of them under it,</hi> Hoſ. 8.1. <hi>and there is no eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it. The Eagle falls ſuddenly, in the twinkling of an eye, (ſay ſome) upon his prey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>For that he is accounted the King</hi> of birds: <hi>and ſo the Vials are all the wrath of God and the Lamb, or</hi> the King of Saints.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>The Eagles prey is blood, or the carcaſes of them killed,</hi> Job 39.30. <hi>where the ſlain are, there is ſhe,</hi> Luk. 17.37. <hi>And ſo he is the ſutable adminiſtrator from the throne, to give out the Vials, which turn waters into blood, and pour ſlaughter upon the Beaſts followers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>It appears to me, it is the Eagle too, by the contents of what judgements he hath to ſhew, in</hi> Rev. 6.7, 8, 9. <hi>unto the end. All bring what the four living creatures or Eagle ſaith,</hi> Come and ſee, <hi>unto</hi> (viz.) <hi>the ſword, famine, death, hell, (all which will fall on the Beaſt by thoſe Vials,</hi> Rev. 18.8. &amp; 19.20.) <hi>and the wrath of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 16.16. &amp; 17.14.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>It appears yet further to me, in the order of the four li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving creatures, and their ſeveral times and works, expreſſed by the holy Ghoſt,</hi> Rev. 6.1, 2. <hi>the firſt ſaid,</hi> Come and ſee, <hi>to his
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40449:55"/> conquering with the Goſpel in the Nations: and this was in the primitive times of the ten perſecutions, or before the Beaſt roſe: for the Saints were then under a moſt lion-like, noble, couragious, Angel-like ſpirit. The ſecond, v.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>ſaid,</hi> Come and ſee, <hi>to the</hi> Red horſe, <hi>or</hi> Scarlet beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.3. <hi>wherein the</hi> Riders <hi>had</hi> a great ſword <hi>to ſlay us: this was in the Beaſts riſe and crowning, by cruel perſecutions, murthers, and maſſacres of the Saints; and ſo they were under the miniſtration of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond living creature, (I conceive) like a Calf for Butchery and ſlaughter.</hi> 3. V. 5, 6. <hi>the third living creature ſaid,</hi> Come and ſee, <hi>to him that had the balances to weigh in time of great ſcarcity of God's own bread; onely the oil and wine (as the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointing) were preſerved: and this I think was the miniſtration which the two Witneſſes were under in their Sackcloth-propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who had the face and grace of a man. But now</hi> 4. <hi>the Eagle is the miniſtrator under whom the Angels of the Vials are: and ſo the two Witneſſes, in that ſtate or predicament, are under the Eagle, who flieth high, ſtrong, clear, ſwift,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to me to be the flying Eagle that gives them out, for that they are to reach over all Nations, and to flie over all; which the flying Angel (who flies with the Goſpel over every nation, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, tongue and people) prepares,</hi> Rev. 14.6, 7, 12. <hi>And it ſeems to me the laſt living creature, becauſe the plagues are the laſt plagues which are in the Vials,</hi> Rev. 15.5. <hi>So that for theſe Reaſons, I have hinted my thoughts unto your firſt</hi> Querie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> I have no intent to meddle with things beſides the Point in hand; neither ſhall I ſpeak much here.</p>
               <p>But, 1. The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> (I think) miſſeth the <hi>Queſtion:</hi> for it was not <hi>queried</hi> which of the <hi>four Beaſts</hi> (or <hi>living creatures,</hi> as he rather chuſeth) <hi>gives out the Vials:</hi> But, <hi>if by the Angel pouring out the firſt Vial, Waldo, Wickcliff, Groſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, Armachan, or Luther, be meant; who then is the one of the living creatures that delivers the Vial to them?</hi> that is, how are theſe men, in publiſhing the Goſpel, VIAL-ANGELS,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40449:55"/> and alſo the <hi>living creature</hi> or <hi>Eagle</hi> that puts the Vial into their hands?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Concerning this large diſcourſe of the <hi>flying Eagle,</hi> and <hi>Eagle-adminiſtration,</hi> here is enough ſaid (the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes granted) to ſhew, that no <hi>Vial</hi> is yet poured out.</p>
               <p>For, 1. Muſt all <hi>the Vials be managed by moſt excellent ſpirits, men full of ſagacity, quick ſent and apprehenſion?</hi> Such then have not been yet, ſince the riſe of the Beaſt: Though we ſee light and day at the dawning, yet is not the ſame full and moſt excellent, till a while after. I grant, ſome of the perſons fore-mentioned were good men; but yet had not <hi>moſt excellent ſpirits,</hi> were not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete and <hi>full</hi> to manage any of the Vials.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For <hi>ſwiftneſs of diſperſations in the Vial-days,</hi> what can be more evidently againſt you then this; <hi>viz.</hi> that in <hi>eight or nine-hundred years,</hi> (for ſo long it is ſince the Vials began, according to your Grounds) very little ſhould be done as to the deſtroying of the <hi>groſſer part of Popery;</hi> methinks it rather carries the likeneſs of a <hi>ſnail</hi> ſlowly creeping over the earth, then the ſwiftneſs of an <hi>Eagle</hi> fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the air.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For courage and boldneſs, this is no more then what the Antichriſtians had: Sometimes the victory hath gone on our ſide, otherwhile on theirs. But if the <hi>Swethen King</hi> were a <hi>Vial-Angel,</hi> it's ſtrange he ſhould be ſlain in the War: for my opinion is, that none of the <hi>ſeven Angels</hi> which have <hi>their breſts girded with golden gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles,</hi> Rev. 15.6. ſhall fall by the hand of their enemy, or at any time loſe the Victory.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If <hi>the way of the Vials be ſtrange and unknown,</hi> then were not the perſons ſo often named, the pourers of them out: for neither <hi>Waldo, Huſs, Luther, King of Sweth,</hi> &amp;c. went in untrodden paths; but what they ſaid or did,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40449:56"/> they had Preſidents and Examples before; and ſo were followers of others in known and trodden paths.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Will thoſe who pour out Vials <hi>be open-eyed,</hi> and move in the <hi>FULL LIGHT of their work?</hi> how then can it be fairly applied to ſuch men as ſate in darkneſs, ſaw little of the things of Chriſt, practiſed moſt groſs idolatry, and, for ſome of them, had not <hi>their faces to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, eying the ſun of righteouſneſs;</hi> but their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate advantages?</p>
               <p n="6">6. That <hi>the Eagle falls ſuddenly in the twinkling of an eye</hi> (as it were) <hi>upon his prey;</hi> it is very true, and ſutable to the <hi>Vial-miniſtration:</hi> for ſurely when that Work begins, it ſhall go ſpeedily and proſperouſly on, without obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or let, and all done in a little time. <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If the <hi>Vials are all wrath, even the wrath of God and the Lamb;</hi> then could not <hi>Waldo</hi> or <hi>Luther</hi> pour any forth in preaching the doctrine of the Goſpel. I have ſhewed before, that whatſoever the <hi>Sackcloth-witneſſes</hi> did in <hi>ſmiting the earth with plagues,</hi> it was onely by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof; as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141.5. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.25. It is true, through unbelief and hardneſs of heart, the Lord afterward brought real plagues upon the wicked world, and will bring many more (and greater) in the <hi>Vials.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Eighth is anſwered before, <hi>viz.</hi> in what ſenſe the <hi>Sackcloth-Witneſſes turned waters into blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Ninth and Tenth <hi>Reaſons,</hi> what is there appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Eagle,</hi> is more againſt the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> then the reſt. For if <hi>under the ſecond living creature like a Calf,</hi> be meant <hi>the cruel perſecutions, murthers, and maſſacres of the Saints after the Beaſt roſe;</hi> then cannot the <hi>Eagle-miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> be brought up to the time of the <hi>Beaſts reign:</hi> for who are the Saints then <hi>butchered,</hi> if not the <hi>Sackcloth-Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes?</hi> Therefore, to ſay that at one time they ſhould be under the miniſtration of the <hi>ſecond living creature,</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:40449:56"/> viz. <hi>like a Calf for butchery;</hi> and under the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>fourth living creature,</hi> namely, the <hi>flying Eagle,</hi> in ſmiting and killing their enemies; this cannot be: neither is there any method, order, or reaſon kept (in my opinion) in this <hi>fourfold miniſtration;</hi> unleſs the <hi>Eagle-time</hi> be underſtood after the riſing of the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> in his words following, grants as much, ſaying, <hi>It ſeems to me, the laſt living creature, becauſe the plagues are the laſt plagues which are in the Vials.</hi> If the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> before their riſing, did pour out the <hi>laſt plagues;</hi> who before them poured out the firſt plagues upon the <hi>Beaſts dominion?</hi> Now here I ſee no reaſon why any ſhould begin thoſe <hi>laſt plagues,</hi> either at <hi>Luther</hi> or <hi>Waldo,</hi> and leave out the <hi>Sackcloth-Witneſſes</hi> before their times. I ſhall here in brief ſet down what hath been publikely witneſſed againſt the <hi>Beaſt</hi> many years before either of them.</p>
               <p>In the year 1126 (which was fourty years before <hi>Waldo) Peter Bruis,</hi> ſometime a Prieſt, was ſo zealouſly earneſt againſt the <hi>groſſer parts of Popery,</hi> as firſt in the Dioceſs of <hi>Arles,</hi> of <hi>Ambrun,</hi> and of <hi>Gap;</hi> then after, throughout all <hi>Auvergne, Languedoc,</hi> and <hi>Guien,</hi> he bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and openly preached againſt Tranſubſtantiation, the Sacrifice of the Maſs, Maſſes, Suffrages, and Oblations for the dead, Purgatory, Worſhipping of Images, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Saints, Single life of Prieſts, Pilgrimages, Superſtitious Holy-days, Conſecrations of Waters, Oil, Frankincenſe, &amp; other Romiſh traſh. And withal, ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inveighed againſt the pride and exceſs of the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Prelates, whom he called <hi>Princes of Sodom;</hi> and the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> he termed <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the <hi>mother of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> and confuſion. For which glorious Teſtimony, he was burnt to aſhes.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:40449:57"/>
               <p>About the ſame time, there was one <hi>Henry</hi> a diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his, who as publikely declared againſt the Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemies of the Beaſt; for which they were ſo mad and enrag'd, as being taken, he was bound in Chains, and ſent by <hi>Albertus Cardinal of Oſtia</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> where it is thought he was ſecretly murdered: for he was never ſeen nor heard of afterwards.</p>
               <p>So in the year 1125. one <hi>Arnulph,</hi> a zealous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout man, for reproving the Looſneſs, Covetouſneſs, Pride, and other Vices of the Clergie, was at <hi>Rome,</hi> by their wicked hands, cruelly murdered.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Anno</hi> 855. (before <hi>Waldo</hi> three hundred years) <hi>Grontier</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Collen,</hi> and <hi>Thietgaud</hi> of <hi>Trevers,</hi> with their Colleagues, gave forth this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the world againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſent it to him: <hi>Thou art</hi> (ſay they) <hi>a Wolf unto the Sheep, a Murderer of the Living, and one which thruſteſt men into hell: Thou bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the ſhew of a Biſhop, but art a very Tyrant: Thou art in habit a Paſtor, in heart a Wolf: Thy Title promiſeth as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but in thy Deeds thou carrieſt as a God:</hi> (alluding to the place in 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.4.) <hi>Thou calleſt thy ſelf, A ſervant of ſervants; and ſeekeſt by all means to become a Lord of lords: and conſequently, according to the doctrine of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, thou art the leaſt of all the Miniſters of Gods Church, who yet in thy ambition runneſt headlong to perdition; think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every thing lawful to be done, which pleaſeth thee. We care not for thy words; we fear not thy Bulls, nor yet thy Thunders,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Yea more, <hi>Anno</hi> 734. <hi>Albertus Gallus,</hi> and <hi>Clemens Scotus,</hi> and many other learned men in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> withſtood the Pope in <hi>Reliques, Images, Single life, Purgatory, Supremacie; and openly call'd the Pope the author of Lyes, the diſturber of Peace and Piety, and the corrupter of Chriſtian Doctrine.</hi> So <hi>Claudius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Taurin,</hi> Anno 799.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:40449:57"/>
               <p>I forbear to mention <hi>Bertram,</hi> Anno 812. and the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Florence,</hi> Anno 1114. and many others, who long before <hi>Waldo,</hi> were condemned of Hereſie, for teaching and writing againſt the <hi>groſſer parts of Popery,</hi> as Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, Purgatory, Images, Maſſes, Pilgrimages; and aſſerting the Pope to be Antichriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then, if the <hi>firſt Vial</hi> be to be underſtood of the <hi>Sackcloth-Witneſſes</hi> ſpeaking againſt <hi>the groſſer part of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> the time cannot begin at <hi>Luther</hi> nor <hi>Waldo,</hi> but with the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> before. For (as I ſaid) there is no reaſon why ſuch <hi>flying Eagles</hi> ſhould be left out, who were as <hi>high, valiant, quick,</hi> and <hi>publike</hi> againſt the <hi>Beast,</hi> (eight or nine hundred years paſt) as were <hi>Armachan,</hi> or <hi>Grosthead,</hi> or the like. In a word therefore, how theſe can be the <hi>last plagues</hi> begun ſo long agone, to wit, when the <hi>Sackcloth-Witneſſes</hi> begun firſt to <hi>ſmite the earth,</hi> (which I think I can make it appear, was aſſoon as the <hi>Beast</hi> did riſe) I ſhall leave it to the READER'S judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>Your ſecond Queſtion is anſwered before. For I cannot ſee how any Angel can be ſingle perſons, but the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes principally, and the remnant of the womans ſeed as auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaries and aſsiſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. Neither doth the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> here come home to the Queſtion. For the Queſtion is not ſo much, <hi>Whether a ſingle perſon or a number be meant,</hi> as concerning the condition of the perſons (few or many) which are to pour out the <hi>Vials.</hi> As for Example: If the <hi>Swethen Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> poured out the <hi>ſecond Vial,</hi> as the <hi>Angel</hi> mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.3. then may the <hi>Vial-Angels</hi> or Inſtruments, which ſhall pour out the <hi>laſt plagues,</hi> be viſibly profane and wicked perſons; which is contrary to <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3, 4, 5, 6. That no <hi>ſingle perſon</hi> is meant by any Angel, I agree with the <hi>Anſwerer.</hi> But mark then, in taking the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40449:58"/> 
                  <hi>Swethen Souldiers</hi> to be the <hi>ſecond Angel,</hi> it muſt follow, that each <hi>Angel</hi> may be made up (a part at leaſt) of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, Adulterers, Swearers, Drunkards, and moſt leud wretches: But I think not ſo. For though <hi>no Angel be a ſingle perſon,</hi> yet my opinion is, that all the perſons which ſhall make up each Angel, ſhall be ſanctified ones, <hi>called, and choſen, and faithful,</hi> Rev. 17.18.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Either the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> or <hi>Replyer</hi> is much miſtaken concerning the <hi>Vials:</hi> for I do not think, that either the <hi>two Witneſſes,</hi> or the <hi>Remnant of the womans ſeed,</hi> to be any of the <hi>ſeven Angels,</hi> Rev. 15.</p>
               <p>Otherwiſe then, thus: <hi>The fourty and two months</hi> of the <hi>Beaſts reign</hi> being out, <hi>one hundred fourty and four thouſand</hi> are upon their work. It is true, <hi>the ſpirit of life from God enters into them:</hi> but this is to be underſtood diſtinct from the <hi>remnant,</hi> Rev. 12.17. and after the <hi>riſing</hi> of the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>To the third Queſtion: I confeſs, it is my judgment, that the ſong of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 15.3. <hi>and that ſong,</hi> Chap. 14.3. <hi>are one and the ſame; and that</hi> Hallelujahs <hi>are the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Vials: but with this caution, That the ſong ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeveral parts and degrees, is not ſung all at once; but as the victory ariſeth, and grows higher and higher over the Beaſt, in every generation the ſong goes on, as the effect of every Vial in its degree and proportion, for the redeemed at that day to ſing,</hi> i. e. <hi>redeemed from among men,</hi> Rom. 14.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> We are here ſo agreed, as I hope we ſhall no more differ about the beginning of the <hi>Vials.</hi> You grant, it is one and the ſame <hi>Song.</hi> For the <hi>Caution,</hi> I ſhall wave it, <hi>viz.</hi> about <hi>parts and degrees,</hi> as nothing material: but for the <hi>Song,</hi> Rev. 14. it is doubtleſs after the <hi>Witneſſes are riſen.</hi> Now you ſay, It is the <hi>ſame ſong,</hi> (which muſt be in reſpect of time and perſons, or it's not ſenſe) then, I ſay, it muſt needs be after the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:40449:58"/> how good and how pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell even together!</hi> Pſal. 133.1.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>The fourth Question hath had a full Anſwer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> Through miſtake, this is the <hi>ſixth Querie,</hi> p. 17. The Reader ſhall have the <hi>Anſwer</hi> and <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 52, 53, 54, 55, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the Copie which my friend had, the <hi>fifth Querie</hi> was thus: <hi>To mention but one effect of the Vials ſuppoſed to be poured out,</hi> viz. <hi>the effect of the ſecond Vial on the ſea, in which every living thing died: now the queſtion is, How this was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled either by the Parliament in England, or the Germane war, or any other way, as it is applied unto things paſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which the <hi>Anſwer</hi> is thus: <hi>Under the ſecond Vial, every living thing in that ſea (that was turned into blood) died a civil death, and ſtank like the dead fiſhes,</hi> Exod. 7.18. Iſai. 50.2. Pſal. 105.29. <hi>Every living ſoul in that ſea, that lived, moved, ſwimmed, and delighted in it, as well the Clergical as Laical, were under the wrath of this Vial. As</hi> Beza <hi>ſaith, Whatſoever living creature,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>which is taken for every kinde; and ſo every one, whether Martial, Civil, or Eccleſiaſtical, died a civil death, yea, and a ſpiritual alſo; the ſea being brought into a filthy ſavour to all living ones, or the people of God, by this Vial. Now all that ſtayed in the ſea, ſo died. Wherefore I finde it true, that every ſoul,</hi> i. e. <hi>referr'd to the ſubject-matter of this Vial, died. For, as</hi> Chemnitius <hi>ſaith, ſuch</hi> particulae univerſales non in infinitum exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur, ſed ad materiam ſubjectam reſtringuntur.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> I conceive the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> intends here the <hi>Swethen war;</hi> but he names none. And it was better to forbear the name of perſons, time, action, or Country: for it may be as well applied to <hi>France, England, Holland, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> as <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But 1. Though it be true, a number of Papiſts died
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40449:59"/> in that War, yet for ought I know, as many of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther party. Beſides, things afterward came to that paſs, as the PROTESTANTS had more Loſs then Advantage by that <hi>War.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. I do not know what you mean by a <hi>ſpiritual death:</hi> if you mean, as to <hi>ſin,</hi> they were as dead before, and ſo not ſlain by the <hi>Vial.</hi> If you apply it to a <hi>ſecond death,</hi> it is beyond my <hi>line.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. There was as <hi>filthy ſavour</hi> before that War, and ſince, as then: very little was done that time, either to increaſe or abate the ſtink.</p>
               <p n="4">4. What <hi>fiſh</hi> ſoever died in that <hi>Sea,</hi> (turned into blood) it ſoon multiplied again: it ſeems the <hi>Sea</hi> was not very bloody; for the fiſh increas'd and multiplied as faſt as before.</p>
               <p n="5">5. I think there is as little ground to carry the <hi>ſecond Vial</hi> to the <hi>Swethen war,</hi> as by <hi>earth</hi> to underſtand the <hi>groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer part of Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, I cannot believe that the <hi>Swethen Army</hi> were ever in the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> and from thence went forth <hi>clothed in pure and fine linen,</hi> &amp;c. with golden Vials.</p>
               <p>Beſides, to deliver my opinion freely, (and I think moſt men now are of my opinion) for that <hi>Swethen War,</hi> more fitly may it be ſet forth under <hi>Kytes</hi> and <hi>Ravens,</hi> then by the <hi>Eagle,</hi> as the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> hath deſcribed that <hi>King of birds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>ſixth and last Question</hi> which my friend had (for the Book hath more then he ſaw) was this: <hi>Whereas ſome reſtrain the riſing of the Witneſſes to the fourth Vial, others to the fifth, we queſtion what Reaſons and Grounds ſuch have; and why may not the riſing of the Witneſſes and firſt Vial contempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which the <hi>Anſwer</hi> is: <hi>Why the riſing of the two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and the firſt Vial may not contemporize, I have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:40449:59"/> before: that I begun with your Queries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> The difference between us is <hi>ſtated</hi> here. I think, the <hi>riſing of the Witneſſes,</hi> and <hi>the beginning of the Vials,</hi> contemporize. The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> is otherwiſe minded, and refers his Reader to what he hath written before. For my part, I do the ſame, and have done for this time. Now if I hear that this which is done be acceptable and uſeful to the Saints <hi>waiting for the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> for whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I have publiſhed it, I ſhall (by the good hand of God aſſiſting me) according to that light which <hi>the Father of lights</hi> hath given in the <hi>Vials,</hi> ſpeedily ſet forth an <hi>Expoſition</hi> of them; it being already prepared for that purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40449:60"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BY reaſon of the Author's far diſtance from the Preſs, more Faults have eſcaped than either He or the Printer could have wiſh'd: ſome of the chief are theſe: <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>The Title over the Pages, ſhould be onely (as you finde it towards the latter end of the Book) <hi>Truth with Time.</hi> P. 14. in marg. at the letter <hi>a,</hi> read, <hi>Of this opinion are many good men.</hi> P. 16. l. 31. read, <hi>to ſing the ſong.</hi> P. 31. l. 18. for <hi>rather,</hi> r. <hi>neither.</hi> P. 32. l. 30. you muſt take that Anſwer to be the anſwer to the ſecond Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. P. 50. l. 1. leave out Mr. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other Miſtakes there are, which thou art de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to take notice of, and correct thy ſelf.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40449:60"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
